<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" article-type="research article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Evaluation and Management</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2476-1737</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Scientific Research Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12677/em.2016.94003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">EM-19257</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>EM20160400000_73799330.pdf</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>经济与管理</subject><subject> 人文社科</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
 
 
  大学管理去行政化的文化藩篱与实践导向
  
 
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>朱</surname><given-names>为鸿</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>null</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label><addr-line>肇庆学院高等教育研究所，广东 肇庆</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail:</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>09</volume><issue>04</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Copyright  2014 by authors and Scientific Research Publishing Inc. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY). http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
 
 
   
   中国大学由于受中国传统行政文化的制约，大学行政权力泛化倾向突出，学术权力长期被压制，去行政化成为当前大学管理改革的重要方向。去行政化要求大学管理改革深入到文化层面，其核心是围绕学术组织配置权力结构，保障教师的学术自由权和学生的参与权利，使行政权力和政治权力更好地为学术事务发展服务。 With the constraints of Chinese traditional bureaucracy culture, bureaucratic rule over the uni-versity shows a tendency to expand its power, which has suppressed the academic power. So de-bureaucracy should be the aim of university management reform. De-bureaucracy entails the reconstruction of the university cultural system. Its main task is to form a reasonable power structure within the academic organization so as to ensure the teachers’ academic autonomy and the students’ involvement in research, enabling the administrative power and the political power to serve the academic undertaking.
    
  
 
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>大学管理，去行政化，学术自治，学生参与, University Management</kwd><kwd> De-Bureaucracy</kwd><kwd> Academic Autonomy</kwd><kwd> Students’ Involvement</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>摘 要</title><p>中国大学由于受中国传统行政文化的制约，大学行政权力泛化倾向突出，学术权力长期被压制，去行政化成为当前大学管理改革的重要方向。去行政化要求大学管理改革深入到文化层面，其核心是围绕学术组织配置权力结构，保障教师的学术自由权和学生的参与权利，使行政权力和政治权力更好地为学术事务发展服务。</p><p>关键词 :大学管理，去行政化，学术自治，学生参与</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>With the constraints of Chinese traditional bureaucracy culture, bureaucratic rule over the university shows a tendency to expand its power, which has suppressed the academic power. So de-bureaucracy should be the aim of university management reform. De-bureaucracy entails the reconstruction of the university cultural system. Its main task is to form a reasonable power structure within the academic organization so as to ensure the teachers’ academic autonomy and the students’ involvement in research, enabling the administrative power and the political power to serve the academic undertaking.</p><p>Keywords:University Management, De-Bureaucracy, Academic Autonomy, Students’ Involvement</p></sec></body><ref id="hanspub.19257-ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple"></mixed-citation></ref></article>