<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" article-type="research article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JOCR</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Organic Chemistry Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2330-5231</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Scientific Research Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12677/JOCR.2017.53019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">JOCR-21613</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>JOCR20170300000_23786925.pdf</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>化学与材料</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
 
 
  国际有机化学命名法研究(二)现代取代命名法
  Studies on the International Nomenclature of Organic Chemistry: (II) Modern Substitutive Nomenclature
 
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>曹</surname><given-names>忠民</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>null</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label><addr-line>大连理工大学化工学院，辽宁 大连</addr-line></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail:</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>08</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>05</volume><issue>03</issue><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Copyright  2014 by authors and Scientific Research Publishing Inc. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY). http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
 
 
  
    从历史发展和化学原理对IUPAC取代命名进行了研究，发现其中不合理的论述和命名过程是由于错误地将特性基团看作官能团，并且代替了官能团。正确地将特性基团作为形成官能团的取代基，同时将这两种基团合理地用于取代命名，结果形成以取代后缀为标志的现代取代命名。它较无特性基团参与的取代命名更为系统化，更便于对不同结构化合物的命名，并且与CA取代命名一致。
    IUPAC substitutive nomenclature is studied from its historical development and chemical theory. It is found that mistaking and using characteristic group as functional group result in forming ir-rational naming rules and procedures. By taking characteristic group as a substituent producing functional group after substitution and correctly using these two groups in the nomenclature, modern substitutive nomenclature, characterized by the substitutive suffix, is formed. Modern substitutive nomenclature is more systematic and more versatile in naming organic compounds of various structures than the previous substitutive nomenclature without characteristic group in-volved. It is also in agreement with the “naming selection principle” of CA. 
  
 
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>取代命名法，官能团，特性基团, Substitutive Nomenclature</kwd><kwd> Functional Group</kwd><kwd> Characteristic Group</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>国际有机化学命名法研究(二)现代取代命名法<sup> </sup></title><p>曹忠民</p><p>大连理工大学化工学院，辽宁 大连</p><p>收稿日期：2017年7月15日；录用日期：2017年8月4日；发布日期：2017年8月7日</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.21613-formula21"><graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x5_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula></sec><sec id="s2"><title>摘 要</title><p>从历史发展和化学原理对IUPAC取代命名进行了研究，发现其中不合理的论述和命名过程是由于错误地将特性基团看作官能团，并且代替了官能团。正确地将特性基团作为形成官能团的取代基，同时将这两种基团合理地用于取代命名，结果形成以取代后缀为标志的现代取代命名。它较无特性基团参与的取代命名更为系统化，更便于对不同结构化合物的命名，并且与CA取代命名一致。</p><p>关键词 :取代命名法，官能团，特性基团</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.21613-formula22"><graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x6_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><p>Copyright &#169; 2017 by author and Hans Publishers Inc.</p><p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY).</p><p>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p><p><img src="http://image.hanspub.org:8080\Html/htmlimages\1-2890033x\e70a10f1-7c93-45ea-9603-062237856e4b.png" /><img src="http://image.hanspub.org:8080\Html\htmlimages\1-2890033x\e898c85e-ffc4-45c9-b817-14224a4d6960.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>1. 引言</title><p>取代命名法是应用最广的，也是IUPAC命名法中最主要的系统命名方法。CA有机化合物的命名，除少数例外，基本上都用这种方法。从Liege会议以来，IUPAC与CA的取代命名法是平行发展的 [1a] ，CA命名系统基本上与IUPAC命名法保持一致 [2a] ，CA服务部(Chemical Abstracts Service, CAS)中一些杰出命名专家都曾在IUPAC有机化学命名委员会(CNOC)服务 [2b] 。出于制作索引的需要，CA命名规则虽较IUPAC取代命名法更加严格、详尽，要通过更多的步骤，最后形成化合物独一无二的名称。但在命名基本原则上与IUPAC命名法是一致的。在编写“蓝皮书”过程中，英国化学家Cahn起草C部初稿 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.21613-ref3">3</xref>] 时，引入了他个人有关官能团和类别的错误概念 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.21613-ref4">4</xref>] 。他所定义的官能团实际上不是官能团，而是形成官能团的取代基 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.21613-ref5">5</xref>] 。C部初版时，基本上保留原定义文字，但将官能团名称改为特性基团 [6a] [7a] [7b] 。这样，特性基团就成了官能团的同义词，主特性基团也就被认为等同于Liege命名法的主官能团 [6a] 。由于用特性基团代替了官能团，IUPAC取代命名法与CA的取代命名法出现了分歧。本文将从取代命名发展历史和化学原理出发，并参照CA命名有关论述，对IUPAC取代命名法进行探讨，阐明IUPAC取代命名中出现各种不合理的问题是由于混淆了特性基团与官能团两种不同的基团。通过对它们加以区别且合理地用于取代命名，最后形成更为系统化、更便于多种不同结构有机化合物的命名，并与CA命名系统一致的现代取代命名法。</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>2. 取代命名法的发展史</title><p>取代命名法创始于日内瓦会议。日内瓦命名法虽相当简单，主要涉及到开链化合物的命名，但所提出基于化学结构的命名原则 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.21613-ref8">8</xref>] 为后来取代命名的发展奠定了基础。取代名称主要由母体、前缀和后缀三部分组成。前缀代表取代基对于母体的取代，在取代名称中用取代基的具体化学名称来表示，是用来描绘所命名化合物分子构造；后缀代表化合物的类别或所含的官能团，除个别例外，用相应类名的一个音节来表示。关于后缀在取代命名中的作用，历史上有如下记载：</p><p>“In order to distinguish various classes of compounds the Congress* agreed to make use of appropriate suffixes, the ending -al, for example, was to denote an aldehyde, -one a ketone and -ol an alcohol or phenol, … aliphatic compounds containing the -CN group were to be denoted by the suffix -nitrile,” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.21613-ref9">9</xref>] (*指the Geneva Congress)。</p><p>后缀代表类别的设定，建立起“官能团”、自然语言中的“类名”与化学语言中的“后缀”三者统一的基本关系。后缀与类别在结构上都表示官能团的存在。三者是通过不同方式表示一类化合物的化性或类别。这种关系成为取代命名中所必须遵守的基本原则，同时也是从化合物的结构式形成取代名称的依据。根据已知的官能团化学式 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.21613-ref10">10</xref>] 可以直接从分子结构式确定化合物所属类别和所含的官能团，从而形成取代名称的后缀。所以后缀的形成必须通过官能团确定。为了与现代取代名称中的取代后缀有所区别，将日内瓦命名法中表示含有官能团的后缀称为“官能后缀”。列日命名法(IUPAC称之为列日规则 [6b] ，以下沿用此名)对日内瓦命名法中后缀含义未作修改，只是将原来可以同时表示分子中多种官能团的多个后缀，如pentanaloloicacid，改为仅用从多种官能中选出的主官能(principal function)的后缀作为唯一后缀，其余官能都用前缀表示 [11a] 。主官能可通过由各种官能按照一定顺序排列的“官能优先顺序”(order of precedence of functions)来选择 [11b] 。按照列日规则提出的设想，后来IUPAC [6c] 和CA [1b] 分别制定了根据化合物类别、按一定顺序排列的选择主官能顺序表(以下简称“顺序表”)。后缀代表主官能的提出，使得日内瓦命名法的命名程序也要同时做出相应的修改。命名的第一步不再是选择最长碳链作为母体主链，而是首先确定主官能团，然后再选择母体主链。对于只含一个主官能团的化合物，选择母体主链的先决条件是必须包括主官能团；对于含有多个同一主官能团的化合物，则母体主链须包括最多数同一主官能团 [11c] 。如果官能团含有碳原子，主官能团的碳原子也就必须包括在主链内，这样会限制在有些情况下选出较为合理的母体。如链端官能团(即只能在链端或伯碳上形成的、含有碳原子的官能团，如醛、腈、羧酸及其衍生物等)位于环上时，主链只能是主官能团本身的一个碳原子，而不是更为合理的环，致使在编辑索引时，占分子绝大部分的环因成为取代基而不能出现在标题母体中，结果环上带有各种官能团系列的化合物不能编排在一起；又如，开链上带有多个同一链端主官能的命名，含有官能团碳原子的主链只能包括链两端的两个主官能团，而不能包括最多数同一主官能团，其余的主官能团只好用前缀表示。如果将抽象地表示(不具体改变母体的构造)含有官能团的“官能后缀”，改为通过取代基对母体的取代形成官能团的取代后缀，主官能团中碳原子就可以来自取代基，母体的选择也就可以不再受主链必须包括主官能团碳原子的限制，从而可以选出合理的母体。特性基团是形成取代后缀的取代基。含碳的特性基团“蓝皮书”称之为特殊特性基团(Exceptional characteristic groups) [6d] 。引入取代运作形成后缀，“官能后缀”改为取代后缀(Substitutive suffix [12a] , Substituent suffix [1c] )使得上述含链端官能团化合物能形成更合理的名称，更便于检索，改进了取代命名法。在含链端官能团化合物取代命名中，因分子结构不同，虽然用不同的后缀来表示含碳与不含碳两种不同特性基团的取代，但由于原子间相互作用与影响，两种不同特性基团形成同一官能团。也就是说，两种不同后缀表示同一类别，或代表同一官能团。CA的羧酸命名说明了这一问题，下面是CA对于羧酸命名的说明和几个实例 [1d] ：</p><p>“The ‘-oic acid’ suffix is employed for acyclic mono- and dicarboxylic acids of carbon chains, including ‘a’—named acids; the ‘-carboxylic acid’ suffix is used for acyclic polycarboxylic acids and compounds in which the carboxyl group is attached to a ring, a monoatomic hydride, or a heterocyclic chain”。</p><p>例 [1d] ：</p><p>1.<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x9_hanspub.png" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> Pentanedioic acid (戊二酸)</p><p>2. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x10_hanspub.png" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>1,2,3-Propanetricarboxylic acid (1,2,3-丙三羧酸*)</p><p>3. <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x11_hanspub.png" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>1-Anthracenecarboxylic acid (1-蒽羧酸*)</p><p>*后缀–carboxylic acid尚无适当的汉语译名。中文有机化学文献中多译为“甲酸” [13a] ，这是错误的。“甲酸”是一个具体化合物的名称，其中“甲”代表省略“烷”字的甲烷母体，“酸”表示由羧基和氧基共同取代形成的官能团-COOH基的后缀。作为一个具体化合物名称的“甲酸”当然不可能成为代表一类化合物官能团的后缀。再者，“取代名称1-蒽甲酸”中有蒽和甲两个母体，也是不合理的。在后缀-carboxylic acid没有合理的汉语名称之前，本文姑且将它译为“羧酸”。</p><p>如果用不含碳取代基来命名，例2中化合物的名称将为3-Carboxypentanedioic acid，在这一名称中，后缀-dioic acid只包括两个主官能团(羧基)，第三个只好用前缀表示；例3的名称将为1-Anthracenylmethanoic acid，在这个名称中，母体只能是甲烷，而占分子主要部分的蒽反而成了取代基，这不仅是母体不合理，而且在索引制作中，按照这样命名，甲酸将成为标题母体(Index heading parent)，蒽基成了取代基，结果使蒽环上带有官能团的各种化合物在索引中不能编排在一起，未能发挥结构近似的化合物编排在一起的便利。</p><p>取代命名法的发展过程说明了两个问题：1) 取代后缀是在官能团形成的“官能后缀”的基础上得来的，而不是在废除官能团情况下由特性基团代替官能团单独形成的；2) 从特性基团在现代取代命名法的作用，进一步说明它是取代基而不是官能团。</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>3. 有关现代取代命名法的理论探讨</title><sec id="s5_1"><title>3.1. 官能团，主官能团，特性基团，主特性基团</title><p>作者已从理论上 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.21613-ref5">5</xref>] 和取代命名的发展历史阐明：特性基团是取代基，经取代进入分子后方能形成官能团。但“蓝皮书”在主特性基团的定义中明确表示，主特性基团是用后缀表示的特性基团，它等同于列日规则中的主官能团，说明特性基团就是官能团。原文表示如下：</p><p>“Principal groups: the characteristic group chosen for expression as suffix in a particular name. (This is equivalent to the ‘principal function’ of the Liege rules.)” [6a] <sup> </sup></p><p>“蓝皮书”虽未明确地否定特性基团是取代基，但从特性基团的定义(用“incorporated into”来表示特性基团进入母体的方式，以及将不可能通过取代进入母体的基，&gt;C=X，列为特性基团)和选择母体的首要条件(“Maximun number of substituents corresponding to the principal group”) [6e] 可以看出，“蓝皮书”并不将特性基团看作是取代基。不过在后来发表的、作为修改和补充的《IUPAC有机化合物命名法指南》(以下简称《指南》)中，对特性基团不是取代基的错误观点作了更正，明确指出特性基团是取代基 [12b] ，特性基团也不再包括只能出现在碳链中间的&gt;C=X：</p><p>“It has been customary to regard these substituents as characteristic (or functional) when the link between substituent and parent is not a carbon-carbon bond, for example, -OH, =O, and -NH, but many exceptions are recognized, such as -COOH and -CN.” [12b]</p><p>《指南》虽然正确地承认特性基团是取代基，但仍然保留“蓝皮书”的特性基团就是官能团和后缀代表主特性基团 [6a] 的错误观点。特性基团是(形成官能团的)取代基和它不是官能团两种不同提法是同一问题的两个方面，一种‘基’在形成后缀的作用上，不可能既是取代基又是官能团，二者有本质的不同。它们的差异在于前者是与分子结构无关的一般的(化学)‘基’，而后者则是分子的有机组成部分，它代表分子的主要化性。未进入分子前特性基团是取代基，进入分子后在分子结构影响下，成为有相同或不相同化学组成的官能团。即使是化学组成相同，它们的本质仍然是不同的。例如，特性基团羟基与醇羟基虽然化学组成相同，但它们的本质是不同的，后者不再是与分子结构无关的一般的羟基，而已是烷基碳上的醇羟基，不同于同一特性基团在酰碳上取代形成的羧酸羟基。《指南》既承认特性基团是取代基，又仍然认为特性基团等同于官能团、后缀代表主特性基团，是自相矛盾的。结果也就不可能改正“蓝皮书”最后形成的后缀代表主特性基团，而不是代表主官能团的错误含义(见下)。</p><p>由于一个名称代表一个具体化合物，所以在取代命名中，不仅要了解两种基之间的结构差异和相互关系，更须要明确从一种基合理地形成另一种基的可能性。从结构上讲，特性基团经取代在分子内能形成官能团，但由于同一特性基团取代不同结构碳原子的氢，能形成不同的官能团，所以从一种特性基团不能确定取代后能具体形成哪一种官能团。也就是说，从特性基团出发，不可能在一化合物分子结构式中识别与它相对应的官能团或确定该化合物类别，但反之，从官能团却可以直接明确形成它的特性基团。所以特性基团与官能团之间相互转换关系是单向的，这就决定了在取代命名中用特性基团代替官能团，既不可能从分子结构式中识别官能团，也不可能从多种特性基团通过由化合物类别按一定顺序编排的“顺序表”中选出主特性基团。形成取代后缀的主特性基团不是来自多种特性基团，而只能是来自主官能团。所以作为取代基的主特性基团不是利用“顺序表”从多种特性基团选出的有代表性的唯一的特性基团，而是根据主官能团化学式选出的取代能形成主官能团的(可能不只一个)特性基团。</p></sec><sec id="s5_2"><title>3.2. 取代前缀与取代后缀</title><p>取代命名中前缀代表母体上客观存在的基。形成前缀命名运作所涉及的取代反应可能是实际上不能发生的，但前缀所代表的基必须是实际存在的。这些母体主链上存在的基，机械地说明分子构造，有如CA对于前缀的说明：</p><p>“Substituent prefixes are employed to denote atoms and chemical groups attached to an index heading parent.” [1e]</p><p>由于取代所引入的基与所表示的主链上存在的基相同，所以前缀是用取代基的具体化学名称来表示。取代后缀则不同，它主要的作用是表示化合物的类别，也就是代表体现化合物化性的主官能团。形成官能团的取代基是一种含有杂原子的特殊取代基——特性基团。由于杂原子与相连碳原子相互影响与作用，特性基团进入分子后，往往须与分子中碳原子结合，方能形成客观存在的、真实代表分子主要化性的官能团。“蓝皮书”混淆了特性基团与官能团，自然也混淆了前缀与后缀，结果取代后缀错误地代表了作为取代基的主特性基团，而不是代表决定类别和体现分子主要化性的主官能团。《指南》虽然正确地说明特性基团是取代基，但并未否定特性基团是官能团，实际上与“蓝皮书”一样，仍然混淆了取代前缀与取代后缀，有如下面的说明，两种‘缀’都是代表取代所引入的基：</p><p>“The substitutive operation involves the exchange of one or more hydrogen atoms for another atom or group. This process is expressed by a prefix or suffix denoting the atom or group being introduced” [12a] 。</p><p>两书对于特性基团是否取代基虽然持不同观点，但它们在由特性基团形成取代后缀过程的不同步骤中都忽略了一条重要的化学基本原则——原子间相互作用与影响，“蓝皮书”中将取代基特性基团定义为官能团，在《指南》中则最后将取代基主特性基团看作是主官能团。结果殊途同归，形成的后缀都是错误地代表主特性基团，而不是代表主官能团。CA对于取代后缀代表主官能团作了明确的表示：</p><p>“Substituent suffixes of molecular skeleton parent compounds are chosen to represent the principal chemical functional group (or groups) in accordance with the order of precedence of compound classes.” [1c]</p><p>取代后缀代表官能团，并不排除通过特性基团的取代，机械地描述母体构造的作用。所以取代后缀除主要代表官能团外，同时也说明了特性基团对母体上的氢原子取代后对母体构造的改变。这样，取代后缀可以说有双层含义，主要代表主特性基团取代所形成的主官能团，同时也表示取代对母体构造的改变。后缀代表主官能团是对全分子而言，表示构造的改变只是对母体而言。所以CA在说明母体与后缀形成索引标题母体时，将后缀与取代基联系起来：</p><p>“They (指母体——本文作者) are transformed into index heading parents by appending, as a suffix, the substituents which represent the principal functional group of the compound;” [1f] 。</p><p>可以完全肯定地说，取代后缀是代表主特性基团取代所生成的主官能团。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s6"><title>4. 取代命名法的命名步骤</title><p>列日规则主要命名步骤很简单，即根据官能团、类别和后缀三者统一的原则，依据官能团的化学式可以直接从分子结构式中确定所含的官能团。当分子中同时含有多种官能团时，通过“顺序表”可以从多种官能团选出形成后缀的主官能团。IUPAC虽然用与官能团本质不同的特性基团代替了官能团，但从IUPAC的命名“一般法则”(General Principles) [6f] [12c] 和有关命名论述来看，后缀形成的过程仍然与列日规则基本相同，原文如下：</p><p>“(b) determine the kind of characteristic group to be cited as suffix (if any) or as a functional class name. Only one kind of characteristic group (the principal group) can be cited as suffix of functional class name.” [12c]</p><p>同时从多种特性基团选出主特性基团的方式与从多种官能团选出主官能团完全相同。</p><p>“The principal characteristic group is the one that characterizes the class occurring earliest in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table10">Table 10</xref>*”. [11d] (*即“顺序表”)</p><p>前面讨论中已经明确，特性基团不可能依照自己的化学式来确定分子结构式中所含的官能团，同时也不可能转换为相应的类别，从多种特性基团中利用“顺序表”来选择主特性基团，所以IUPAC的命名“一般法则”实际上是行不通的。再者，“一般法则”所讲的用后缀表示的主特性基团可以同时作为官能类名(functional class name)也是不能成立的。官能类名是指官能类名称(Functional class name) [12d] 中的类名(class name)部分。官能类名名称是IUPAC将原来的普通名称经过系统化形成的一种系统名称。最初称为基官能名称(Radicofunctional name) [6g] [12c] 。这一命名方法是仿照无机化合物的二元命名法(Binary nomenclature) [13a] [13b] ，将有机化合物分子分为烃基和官能团两部分，分别命名，所以最初被称作基官能命名法。取代名称的取代后缀与基官能名称的官能类名都代表官能团，所以从官能团出发形成的主官能团当然既可以作取代名称的取代后缀，也可以作基官能名称的官能类名。特性基团不同于官能团，所以主特性基团不可能作为基官能名称的类名。</p><p>由于IUPAC混淆了特性基团与官能团，“一般法则”所讲述的取代名称虽然未改变后缀的形式，但已使后缀具有了错误的含义，不再代表主官能团，而是代表主特性基团。所以对于后缀与官能类名不相同的具体问题，也就无法做出合理的解释。例如丁酮的取代名称Butanone后缀-one表示 = 0，它的基官能名称Ethyl methyl ketone的官能类名ketone 却代表&gt;C=0，后缀与官能类名各表示不同的基，对此，IUPAC做出了如下说明：</p><p>“The characteristic group that can be cited as suffixes in substitutive nomenelature are not necessarily identical with the groups designated by the name of a corresponding functional class when functional class names are formed (e.g., butanone and ethyl methyl ketone, where –one denotes =0 and ketone denotes -CO-),” [12f] 。</p><p>这里所说的后缀与官能类名“不必然相同”(“not necessarily identical”)不仅没有合理的依据，并且与“一般法则”中的论点也是矛盾的。它们既然“不必然相同”，选出的主特性基团又如何能同时可以作后缀和官能类名呢？后缀-one代表特性基团 = 0，而官能类名ketone则代表官能团-CO-，它们并不是“不必然相同”，而是根本不相同。再如Ethanenitrile中表示N<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x12_hanspub.png" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>的取代的后缀-nitrile与基官能名称Ethyl cyanide表示-CN的官能类名cyanide [6h] 也是不同的。</p><p>命名“一般法则”的第二步“(c) detemine the parent hydride”是选择作为母体的主链。“蓝皮书”中选择主链的首要条件是：“(a) Maximum number of substituents corresponding to the principal group” [6c] 。这里“principal group”是指主特性基团。确定一类化合物的主链是根据链上决定分子主要化性的主官能团 [11c] ，而不是主特性基团。所以CA选择索引名称(Index name)分子骨架(Molecular skeleton)所依据的首要条件就是“(a) Greatest number of the principal chemical functional group” [1g] CA的分子骨架相当于IUPAC的主链。</p><p>“蓝皮书”直接将特性基团等同于官能团，结果后缀就代表主特性基团。《指南》虽然承认特性基团是取代基，但混淆了前缀与后缀：</p><p>“The substitutive operation involves the exchange of one or more hydrogen atoms for another atom or group. This process is expressed by a prefix or suffix denoting the atom or group being introduced.” [12a]</p><p>后缀代表取代基(特性基团)所引入的基，结果后缀仍然是代表主特性基团。</p><p>IUPAC虽然用特性基团代替官能团，按照命名“一般法则”，只利用特性基团，却能完成从理论上讲行不通的命名运作，最后形成形式上与正确名称相同的取代名称。从“蓝皮书”与《指南》的文字的叙述中很难看出问题的所在，但从命名实践所用的化学式就不难看出如何完成理论上行不通的命名步骤的。下面是IUPAC论述取代命名中的两个实例：</p><p>例1 [6i] <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x13_hanspub.png" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></p><p>Principal group <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x14_hanspub.png" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> -al</p><p>Parent hydride Nonane</p><p>Substituent 4-Formylcyclohexyl</p><p>Name 9-(4-Formylcyclohexyl)nonal</p><p>例2 [12g] <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x15_hanspub.png" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula></p><p>Principal group &gt;(C)=O -one</p><p>Parent hydrideHeptane</p><p>Substituent Hydroxy-</p><p>Name 7-Hydroxyheptan -2-one</p><p>除例2化合物含有羟基外，两例化合物均含有=O基，根据上面的理论探讨，由于特性基团不具备相连碳原子结构信息，所以不能确定两例中=O基所形成的官能团为醛基或酮基，也就是说，最后无法识别分子中所含的官能团，从而形成相应的后缀。但两个例子实际上分别得出正确的取代后缀，—al和—one。从主特性基团的化学式不难看出，正确的后缀之所以能形成，是由于主特性基团的化学式不再是特性基团，都具有了官能团的结构信息。这种不含碳却具有表示碳原子结构价键的不合理的化学式，使得特性基团=O基能自我地分为形成醛基的氧−(CH)=O，和酮基的氧&gt;(C)=O，在一种官能团价键掩盖下成为具有官能团结构信息的、不合理的化学式。通过这种不合理的化学式，特性基团得以从化合物分子结构式中识别所含的官能团，并且可以纳入“顺序表”与−OH比较，成为主特性基团(例2)。特性基团不合理的化学式是IUPAC“一般法则”讲述的取代命名法错误的核心。为了便于讨论，以下简称它为“伪官能团”。</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>5. “伪官能团”是IUPAC取代命名法存在问题的核心</title><p>从命名实例可以看到，IUPAC取代命名法有关论述中所指的特性基团并不是“蓝皮书”与《指南》两书中定义的特性基团 [6a] [12b] [12h] ，而是“伪官能团”。“伪官能团”首先出现在IUPAC取代命名法的“特性基团”与前、后缀关系表中 [6j] [12i] 。该表主要由以下四列组成：1. Class; 2.Formula; 3. Prefix; 4. Suffix。第二列是特性基团的化学式。其中除为了使命名运作能选出更为合理的母体，特性基团包括了与杂原子相连的碳原子的特殊特性基团外，一般的特性基团均应为杂原子或杂原子基。但表中多价的特性基团（即取代后杂原子以多重键与碳相连）均以“伪官能团”形式出现，如−(CH)=O，&gt;(C)=O，−(C)<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x16_hanspub.png" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula> N，−(C)OOH等。括弧中碳原子表示它不属于该化学式。“伪官能团”在化学组成上虽然与特性基团相同，但它的的自由价键已成为含碳官能团的自由价键。它实际上所表示的是无碳原子的含碳官能团，或者说是具有含碳官能团自由价键的特性基团。所以“伪官能团”是化学组成与自由价键分离产生的不合理结构。它既不是官能团，也不是特性基团。在取代命名中IUPAC利用它的含碳官能团的自由价键来完成只有官能团才能做到的命名步骤，利用它的特性基团化学组成最终说明后缀代表特性基团而不是代表官能团。</p><p>IUPAC在取代命名中是用特性基团来代替官能团。特性基团在“蓝皮书”和《指南》中都有明确的定义，但实际上用的不是所定义的特性基团，而是“伪官能团”，《指南》中有关论述说明了这一问题：</p><p>“The presence of a characteristic group can be denoted by a prefix or suffix attached to the parent name. Such prefixes and suffixes are illustrated in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5">Table 5</xref>*.” [12j]</p><p>“The principal characteristic group is the one that characterizes the class occurring earliest in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table10">Table 10</xref>#. All other characteristic groups are cited as prefixes. Some suffixes and prefixes to be used with the general classes listed in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table10">Table 10</xref> are given in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table5">Table 5</xref>*.” [12f]</p><p>(*用“伪官能团”表示特性基团的特性基团与前、后缀关系表；#为“顺序表”)</p><p>按照IUPAC命名“一般法则”所形成的取代名称虽然形式上仍与正确名称相同，但后缀的含义是错误的，当将名称转换为原来的结构式，就会暴露出因错误的后缀含义，以致不能还原为正确表达的官能团结构式。将名称转换为原来的结构式的过程IUPAC与AC均有论述，分别称之为“Name Interpretation” [12k] 与“Chemical Structural Diagrams from CA Index Names” [1h] 。下面引用《指南》中从名称变为结构式的两个实例：</p><p>例1 [12m]</p><p>2,3-dichloro-6-[4-chloro-2-（hydroxymethyl）-5-oxohex-3-en-1-yl]pyridine-4-carboxylic acid</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.21613-formula23"><graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x17_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><p>例2 [12n]</p><p>3-(2,3-dihydroxypropyl)-α-methylquinoline-2-pentanoic acid</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.21613-formula24"><graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x18_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><p>例1是以-carboxylic acid为后缀表示特殊特性基团-COOH取代形成官能团羧酸的名称。由于作为取代基的特性基团与官能团有相同化学组成，代表取代所引入的基恰好与官能团形式相同，结果得出形式上正确、羧基连在吡啶环上化合物的结构式名称：</p><p>“The suffix ‘carboxylic acid’ together with its locant, ‘4’, describes the presence of a carboxy group, -COOH, at position 4 of the parent hydride ‘pyridine’ giving the structure and numbering shown below: ”</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.21613-formula25"><graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x19_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><p>例2与例1不同，是以-oic acid为后缀，表示由氧基与羟基两种特性基团在伯碳上共同取代形成官能团的羧酸名称。IUPAC用“伪官能团”代替特性基团，结果后缀不是代表两价的氧基与一价的羧基共同取代形成的羧基，而是表示“不含碳的羧基”。但IUPAC仍然称它为“carboxy”!:</p><p>“The suffix ‘-oic acid’ denotes the presence of a carboxy [−(C)OOH ]group attached to the parent hydride pentane, giving the structure and numbering shown as below. Note that the carbon atom of the carboxy group is included in the parent chain …”</p><p>CH<sub>3</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-CH<sub>2</sub>-COOH</p><p>5 4 3 2 1</p><p>并且还补充说，这个“carboxy”的碳原子包括在母体链中。它本不含碳，又何从谈起它的碳原子包括在母体链中呢！这两个从取代名称转换为结构式的例子进一步说明IUPAC命名“一般法则”所论述的取代命名存在的问题。特性基团不具备分子中与之相连碳原子结构信息，不可能完成取代命名中形成后缀的所有步骤。作为“不含碳的官能团”的“伪官能团”在完全违反化学原理的情况下获得了表现官能团的结构，虽然不合理地形成了取代后缀，但这样形成的取代后缀不仅它的形成不合理，而且表达了错误结构，它代表特性基团，而不是代表体现分子化性和决定化合物类别的官能团。</p><p>取代后缀代表特性基团造成了后缀与类别含义的分离，引起了矛盾。类别与后缀本应表达同一概念，不过前者是自然语言，而后者是化学语言。由于后缀一般只用类名的一个音节，后缀与类别含义分离引起的矛盾并不明显，但当二者为同一词时，这种矛盾就表面化了。如nitrile一词同为nitrile类化合物的后缀与类名，却分别表示为N<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x20_hanspub.png" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>与CN，而后缀-carbonitrile与类名nitrile虽是不同的词，却都代表相同的CN。所以在“蓝皮书”腈类命名有关规则中，特别用附注加以说明 [6k] [6m] 。但这两个附注对原来的矛盾并未能做出合理解释，不过重申了矛盾的内容。中文有机化学命名中，由于文字关系，无法用名称的一个音节来做后缀，后缀与类名含义分离的矛盾较为明显。在腈类命名中，除有与“蓝皮书”中同样的矛盾外，用后缀“腈”字表示N<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="http://html.hanspub.org/file/2-2970089x21_hanspub.png" xlink:type="simple"/></inline-formula>，破坏了汉字结构与意义的关系，“腈”与“氰”代表两个化学组成不同的基，不再有如“胺”与“氨”那样，按照汉字结构与意义的关系，分别表示有机与无机两个化学组成相同的基。再者，在酮类命名中，同一化合物CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>COCH<sub>3</sub>的取代名称为丁酮，基官能名称为甲乙酮，“蓝皮书”出版前两个名称中的“酮”字均表示酮基或羰基，但出版后，前者的“酮”字改为表示氧基，而后者的“酮”字则仍表示羰基。结果造成氧基与羰基两个词间的混乱。“蓝皮书”中文译本中，将原文“oxo” [6n] [6o] 误译为羰基 [13b] [13c] ，不能不说是IUPAC国际命名法的错误影响造成的。</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>6. 合理的IUPAC取代命名法</title><p>综上所述，合理的取代命名必须遵守以下两点：(1) 命名的第一步，确定该化合物类别或所含主官能团，必须是通过官能团的化学式，而不是从特性基团得来；(2) 主特性基团不能从多种特性基团选出，它只能是来自主官能团，并在命名的最后一步，作为主官能团的取代基形成取代后缀，CA对于主特性基团有如下的说明：</p><p>“In substitutive nomenclature, a principal chemical group is that substituent of a molecular skeleton which is selected for expression as a suffix.” [1i]</p><p>这一说明中CA用“principal chemical group”代替IUPAC的“principal characteristic group”。这可能是由于CA将“characteristic group”只看作是一般的(化学)基(chemical group)。</p><p>“蓝皮书”和《指南》中“一般法则”(General principles)所讲的取代命名法不符合上述两点，尤其是用“伪官能团”代替特性基团，更是不合理。但“蓝皮书”C-1至C-9章各类化合物分类的取代命名法规则却与C-0章“一般法则”所讲述的有所不同。C-1至C-9章的前言虽然明确指出：“The following Subsections C-1to C-9 illustrate how the general principles set out in the subsection C-0 are applied to various types of compound” [6p] ，但实际上C-1至C-9章化合物分类命名仍然遵循列日命名法的基本原则，下面援引C-3中醛与酮的命名规则来说明它与“一般法则”命名规则的差异：</p><p>“The term ‘aldehyde’ is applied to compounds which contain the group –CHO attached to carbon. Aldehydes are named by means of the suffix ‘-al’, ‘-aldehyde’ , or ‘-carbaldehyde’ …” [6n]</p><p>“The generic name ‘ketone’ is given to compounds containing an oxygen atom doubly bound to a single carbon atom with the carbonyl group &gt;C=0 joined to two carbon atoms. Ketones are named by means of the suffix ‘-one’, …” [6o] <sup> </sup></p><p>上述两段引文说明两类化合物的命名都首先提到标志化合物类别的基，如醛的-CHO，酮的&gt;(C)=O。从功能和化学组成来看，这两个基应该分别为醛与酮的官能团。所以这里醛与酮的命名与列日命名法完全相同，都是从各自的官能团开始。随后指出名称中后缀代表的类别，明确了醛与酮的命名仍然是遵守官能团、类别、后缀三者相互对应和统一的基本原则。命名过程是利用官能团直接形成用后缀表示的主官能团与类别，而与特性基团完全无关。这显然与列日命名法是一致的，不过列日命名法中“Aldehydes are characterized by the suffix al” [11d] ，“Ketones will receive the ending one” [11e] 所描述的后缀是“官能后缀”，而“蓝皮书”C-3章中的-al和–one已不是原来表示含有官能团的“官能后缀”，而是代表由主特性基团取代形成主官能团的取代后缀。作为链端官能团醛的后缀增加了由特性基团形成的取代后缀“carbaldehyde”说明了这一问题。“carbaldehyde”与-al都代表醛类与醛官能团，所不同的是，它们分别表示由不同的取代基(主特性基团) −CHO与=O形成的醛基。从上述醛与酮的命名可以看到，C-3章中的命名规则与C-0章“一般法则”所规定的完全不同，它反映了取代命名的历史发展过程，符合上述理论探讨，确定分子中所含的官能团和化合物的类别与特性基团无关，主特性基团只是作为主官能团的取代基在形成取代后缀最后一步参与命名，与现代CA取代命名原则上一致。</p><p>正确处理特性基团与官能团的关系和合理地使用特性基团是形成合理的取代命名的关键。这样也就不会有“伪官能团”出现在命名过程中。如将原来的“特性基团与前、后缀关系表” [6j] [12i] 中“伪官能团”化学式作如下修改，该表就成为取代命名法合理的概括：</p><p>此表形式上虽然与“特性基团与前、后缀关系表”相似，但实际所表达的概念完全不同。首先是利用官能团而不是特性基团形成后缀；再者，将特性基团看作是形成官能团的取代基，使主特性基团成为主官能团的“定向”取代基，从而将“官能后缀”改进为取代后缀。表中主特性基团列的化学式与“伪官能团”根本不同，碳原子与它的自由价键分离的不合理现象不复存在，它合理地表示作为“定向”取代基的主特性基团。</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>7. 结论</title><p>(1) 实质为取代基的特性基团等同于官能团是IUPAC取代命名法出现问题的根源，将特性基团改为“伪官能团”是错误的核心。</p><p>(2) 有机化学命名的历史发展和化学原理说明，合理的取代命名首先必须从官能团确定类别。正确地处理特性基团与官能团的关系，合理地将特性基团用于形成取代后缀是合理的取代命名法的必要步骤。</p><p>(3) 合理的取代命名法是与CA取代命名一致的现代取代命名法。</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>致谢</title><p>本论文系作者遗稿。发表前承大连理工大学化工学院蒋景阳教授精心校核，作者子女对此谨表示诚挚的谢意！</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>文章引用</title><p>曹忠民. 国际有机化学命名法研究(二)现代取代命名法Studies on the International Nomenclature of Organic Chemistry: (II) Modern Substitutive Nomenclature[J]. 有机化学研究, 2017, 05(03): 142-152. http://dx.doi.org/10.12677/JOCR.2017.53019</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>参考文献 (References)</title></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chemical Abstract: Index Guide 1992-1996, Appendix IV, Chemical Substance Index Names: (a) 117 I, 101, Foreword; (b) 118 I, 106; (c) 128 I, 131; (d) 150 I, 165 (a); (e) 128 I, 132; (f) 128 I, 130 (b); (g) 131 I, 138 (a); (h) 250 I, L Chem-ical Diagrams from Index Names; (i) 150 I, 164.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Giles Jr., P.M. and Metanomski, W.V. (1993) The History of Chemical Abstract Service (CAS). In: Kisakurek, M.V., Ed., Organic Chemistry: Its Language and Its State of the Art, VHCA, Basel, (a) 173; (b) 191.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Loening, K.L. (1993) Organic Nomenclature: The Geneva Conference and the Second Fifty Years: Some Personal Observations. In: Kisakurek, M.V., Ed., Organic Chemistry: Its Language and Its State of the Art, VHCA, Basel, 37.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cahn, R.S. and Dermer, O.C. (1979) Introduction to Chemical Nomenclature. 5th Edition, Butterworths Ltd., London, 43.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">曹忠民. 国际有机化学命名法研究: (一)官能团与特性基团[J]. 有机化学研究, 2017, 5(3): 137-141.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">IUPAC Nomenclature of Organic Chemistry, Sections A, B, C, D, E, F and H, 1979 Edition, Oxford: Pergamon Press: (a) 81-82, Glossary; (b) Xvii, Introduction to 1969 Edition of Sections A, B and C; (c) 86, Table II; (d) 89, C-0.11; (e) 98, C-13.11 (a); (f) 85,C-0.0; (g) 112, C-0.2; (h) 270, C-832.4; (i) 95, C12.6 (3); (j) 88, Table III; (k) 269, C-832.1; (m) 269, C-832.2; (n) 162,C-301.1; (o) 167, C-311.1; (p) 144, Preamble to Sections C-1 to C-9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Verkade, P.E. (1985) A History of the Nomenclature of Organic Compounds. D Riedel Publishing Co., Dordrecht, (a) 238; (b) 378; (c) 278; (d) 29; (e) 77.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Traynham, J.G. (1993) Organic Nomenclature: The Geneva Conference 1892 and the Following Fifty Years. In: Kisakurek, M.V., Ed., Organic Chemistry: Its Language and Its State of the Art, VHCA, Basel, 2.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Crosland, M.P. (1978) Historical Studies in the Language of Chemistry. Dover Publications, Inc., New York, 351.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">(1996) Kirk-Othmer Encyclopedia of Chemical Technology. 4th Edition, John Wiley and Sons, Inc., New York, 249-250.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Patterson, A.M. (1933) Definitive Report of the Commission on the Reform of the Nomenclature of Organic Chemistry Translation with Comments. Journal of the American Chemical Society, 55, 3905-3925. (a) 3921,§51; (b) 3921,§52; (c) 3913,§18; (d) 3915,§26; (e) 3916§27. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1021/ja01337a001</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">IUPAC Commission on the Nomenclature of Organic Chemistry, Panico, R., Powell, W.H. and Richer, J.C. (1993) A Guide to IUPAC Nomenclature of Organic Compounds, Recommendations 1993. Blackwell Science Ltd., Oxford. (a) 22, R-1.2.1; (b) 59, R-3.0; (c) 68, R-4.1; (d) 15, R-0.2.3.3.4; (e) 14, R-0.2.3.3.3; (f) 70; (g) 73, R-4.2.2; (h) 13, R-0.2.2.2; (i) 63, Table 5; (j) 62, R-3.2.1.1; (k) 143, R-6; (m) 144, R-6.2; (n) 145, R-6.3.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.21613-ref13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">国际纯化学和应用化学联合会: 有机化学命名法A, B, C, D, E, F和H部, 1979 [M]. 北京: 中国科学出版社, 1987: (a) 114, C-11.11b; (b) 203, C-301.1; (c) 210, C-311.1.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>