<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" article-type="research article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IJE</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Ecology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2324-7967</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Scientific Research Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12677/IJE.2020.94038</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">IJE-38487</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>IJE20200400000_67544910.pdf</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>生命科学</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
 
 
  人虎冲突产生原因及影响分析及解决对策
  Analysis of Causes and Effects of Human-Tiger Conflict and Countermeasures
 
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>高</surname><given-names>壮勇</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>王</surname><given-names>建锋</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>张</surname><given-names>明海</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>东北林业大学野生动物与自然保护地学院，黑龙江 哈尔滨</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><addr-line>null</addr-line></aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>04</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>09</volume><issue>04</issue><fpage>294</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Copyright  2014 by authors and Scientific Research Publishing Inc. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY). http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
 
 
  
    随着野生虎种群数量的逐步回升，虎分布区域内人虎冲突是目前绝大多数虎分布国家在虎保护工作中亟待解决的问题之一。本文在界定了人虎冲突基本涵义和主要表现形式的基础上，从虎与人双方角度，阐述了由虎引发的和由人引发的人虎冲突的原因和驱动因素；探讨了人虎冲突的显著影响和潜在影响。研究分析认为，人虎冲突表现形式可分为直接和间接人虎冲突两大类型，其中间接人虎冲突是主要表现形式，必须引起虎保护利益相关者的高度重视。人虎双方不仅是冲突的受害者也是引发者，仅从人或虎的单方角度出发很难从根本上解决人虎冲突问题。最后，本文从科学管理人虎共用区域、精准扶持居民替代生计、出台人虎冲突补偿的统一标准、开展虎保护宣教活动、推行跨学科联合研究等5个方面提出了解决人虎冲突的对策或建议。
    With the gradual recovery of wild tiger populations, human-tiger conflicts in tiger distribution areas is one of the most urgent problems in tiger conservation in most tiger distribution countries. On the basis of defining the basic concept and main patterns of human-tiger conflicts, this paper were expounds the human-tiger conflict causes and driving factors, and discussed the significant and potential effects from both tiger and human aspects. According to the analysis, human-tiger conflict can be divided into two patterns: direct conflict and indirect conflict, of which indirect conflict is the main manifestation and must be paid great attention by the stakeholders of tiger protection. Human and tiger are not only the victims but also the initiators of the conflict. Finally, we puts forward countermeasures or suggestions to solve the human-tiger conflict from five aspects, such as scientific management of the common area of tigers, precise support for residents’ alternative livelihood, unified standard of compensation for human-tiger conflict, tiger protection publicity and education activities, and implementation of interdisciplinary joint research. 
  
 
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>人虎冲突，冲突原因，冲突影响，解决对策，共用区域管理, Human-Tiger Conflict</kwd><kwd> Conflict Reasons</kwd><kwd> Conflict Influence</kwd><kwd> Solutions</kwd><kwd> Common Area Management</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>摘要</title><p>随着野生虎种群数量的逐步回升，虎分布区域内人虎冲突是目前绝大多数虎分布国家在虎保护工作中亟待解决的问题之一。本文在界定了人虎冲突基本涵义和主要表现形式的基础上，从虎与人双方角度，阐述了由虎引发的和由人引发的人虎冲突的原因和驱动因素；探讨了人虎冲突的显著影响和潜在影响。研究分析认为，人虎冲突表现形式可分为直接和间接人虎冲突两大类型，其中间接人虎冲突是主要表现形式，必须引起虎保护利益相关者的高度重视。人虎双方不仅是冲突的受害者也是引发者，仅从人或虎的单方角度出发很难从根本上解决人虎冲突问题。最后，本文从科学管理人虎共用区域、精准扶持居民替代生计、出台人虎冲突补偿的统一标准、开展虎保护宣教活动、推行跨学科联合研究等5个方面提出了解决人虎冲突的对策或建议。</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>关键词</title><p>人虎冲突，冲突原因，冲突影响，解决对策，共用区域管理</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Analysis of Causes and Effects of Human-Tiger Conflict and Countermeasures<sup> </sup></title><p>Zhuangyong Gao<sup>*</sup>, Jianfeng Wang, Minghai Zhang<sup>#</sup></p><p>The College of Wildlife and Protected Area, Northeast Forestry University, Harbin Heilongjiang</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/3-2640272x4_hanspub.png" /></p><p>Received: Oct. 4<sup>th</sup>, 2020; accepted: Oct. 28<sup>th</sup>, 2020; published: Nov. 4<sup>th</sup>, 2020</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/3-2640272x5_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>With the gradual recovery of wild tiger populations, human-tiger conflicts in tiger distribution areas is one of the most urgent problems in tiger conservation in most tiger distribution countries. On the basis of defining the basic concept and main patterns of human-tiger conflicts, this paper were expounds the human-tiger conflict causes and driving factors, and discussed the significant and potential effects from both tiger and human aspects. According to the analysis, human-tiger conflict can be divided into two patterns: direct conflict and indirect conflict, of which indirect conflict is the main manifestation and must be paid great attention by the stakeholders of tiger protection. Human and tiger are not only the victims but also the initiators of the conflict. Finally, we puts forward countermeasures or suggestions to solve the human-tiger conflict from five aspects, such as scientific management of the common area of tigers, precise support for residents’ alternative livelihood, unified standard of compensation for human-tiger conflict, tiger protection publicity and education activities, and implementation of interdisciplinary joint research.</p><p>Keywords:Human-Tiger Conflict, Conflict Reasons, Conflict Influence, Solutions, Common Area Management</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.38487-formula10"><graphic xlink:href="//html.hanspub.org/file/3-2640272x7_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><p>Copyright &#169; 2020 by author(s) and Hans Publishers Inc.</p><p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/3-2640272x8_hanspub.png" /> <img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/3-2640272x9_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>1. 引言</title><p>虎(Panthera tigris)是位于生态系统中食物链顶端的代表性大型食肉动物之一，是全球生物多样性保护的旗舰物种和保护伞物种，在维持健康自然生态系统功能中占据不可替代的重要地位，虎种群的有效保护和可持续生存对全球生态安全具有深远意义 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref1">1</xref>]。因此，野生虎的保护业已引起世界保护组织和虎分布国家政府的普遍重视和高度关注。在种群管理、栖息地恢复、产品贸易、保护立法和执法等诸多方面，采取了一系列技术措施或政策保障，从而使虎种群及其栖息地呈现出逐渐恢复的良好态势。与此同时，随着虎在某些特定区域出现频次的不断增高和分布范围的不断扩大，虎和人的共用区域正在增长，越来越多的虎迁移出保护区，导致人虎冲突频发 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref2">2</xref>]。目前这种情况在虎分布地区已不属个例，大多虎分布国家都受到了不同程度的人虎冲突影响。例如，2007~2014年间，尼泊尔赤湾国家公园发生的人虎冲突占比在全部人兽冲突事件中超过50%，有人员伤亡的事件占人虎冲突事件总数的70.7%，其余均是牲畜损失，赔偿总额为93,618美元；这期间4只虎被当地居民报复性杀害 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref3">3</xref>]。近年来，在我国黑龙江、吉林两省的东部林区以及西藏的墨脱地区，每年都有发生人虎冲突的报道，而且发生的频次呈逐年增高的趋势。如何有效化解人虎冲突问题，这不仅关系到虎的生存安全和人的生命及财产安全，而且关系到虎保护工作的成效及社会公众对野生动物保护的态度。为此，本文以人虎冲突的基本涵义为出发点，分析对人虎冲突产生的原因及影响，探讨解决人虎冲突解决对策，籍以为我国野生虎种群保护及其栖息地恢复提供理论和技术参考。</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>2. 人虎冲突的涵义</title><p>广义上讲，所谓的人虎冲突是指人与虎在特定情景下或特定区域内发生的直接或间接的生存安全或利益上相互侵害、相互制约的现象。在冲突过程中，人与虎双方不仅都是受害者，也都是引发者。 即冲突是由人或虎引发的，对双方都产生负面影响的事件如恐惧、受伤、死亡和财产或生计损失的事件，是参与者双方在争夺有限的生存空间和资源产生的结果。尽管目前报道的人虎冲突表现形式较多，但归纳起来主要有以下两大类型：</p><p>(1) 直接人虎冲突。这类人虎冲突最易引起人们关注的典型表现形式。主要包括：虎伤害或捕食人、家畜等；人捕杀或驱赶虎等，其引发的原因简单，产生的影响直接，解决方案较易制定。</p><p>(2) 间接人虎冲突。这是一类在人虎共用区普遍存在的最常见的表现形式。主要包括两种情形：一种情形是由于虎的出没间接导致了出现点辐射范围内人们生产、生活方式的改变。如在虎出没区域内的林业生产经营、防火巡护、山野菜、蘑菇、野果采摘、中药材采挖与培育、农业生产与放牧等生产活动的正常开展，以及出行安全、牲畜安全和村屯社区安全等均受到了不同程度的影响；与此恰恰相反的另一种情形是，由于人类在虎分布活动区域开展各种经济和社会活动，如修筑高等级公路、铁路、军事边界围栏、水利工程、农业和林业生产(采伐森林)等，这些人为活动对虎的卧息、迁移、捕食、繁殖行为及栖息地选择等生存活动产生了重要影响。由于这类冲突具有表现形式上的间接性、时间尺度上的延伸性、空间范围上的隐域性及发生频次上的普遍性等特点，因此其引发的原因较为复杂，产生的生态影响最为深远，为虎保护利益相关者高度关注的一类人虎冲突问题。</p><p>人虎冲突所受的损害情况、对野生动物保护的认知、国情、宗教、民俗文化等方面反应出当地人民对虎的风险意识和社会反映 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref4">4</xref>]，虎对家畜的捕食情况、人为干扰的情况、分布区域猎物丰度、数量及分布等方面反应出虎引发冲突对当地居民的影响 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref5">5</xref>]。虎伤害居民与家畜，造成经济损失和人对森林资源的占用，对虎的报复性杀戮等。尽管这些冲突侧面反映了人类对野生虎保护，种群数量恢复工作的成效，突出了人口增长与城市化发展的进步。但是，虎的数量恢复需要更多的栖息地，人的发展需要占据更多的自然资源，人虎产生了领地上的碰撞，随着这样的进展，不仅虎的保护会陷入僵局，当地居民的生计与生命安全受到了威胁。</p><p>现有的人虎冲突研究由于数据收集普遍滞后于冲突发生时间，只能依靠走访调查或相关部门提供的记录作为基础数据。但是调查的村庄过于偏远或居民与当局的关系较差导致获得报告有偏见时，获得的数据无法代表冲突分布情况 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref6">6</xref>]。这些繁杂的步骤和冗长的冲突调查间隔往往会忽略一部分已发生的冲突，如发生在保护区之外的不予补偿的牲畜等，记录的数据与实际的冲突情况有出入 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref7">7</xref>]。</p><p>如果从长远角度解决人虎冲突，需要探究人虎双方引发冲突的原因以及对双方造成的影响，从根本上了解人虎冲突由起因到事件发生到引发的深远影响的关系，才能更加准确的对人虎冲突频发的区域实施管理与解决措施。</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>3. 人虎冲突的原因及驱动因素</title><sec id="s7_1"><title>3.1. 虎引发冲突的原因</title><sec id="s7_1_1"><title>3.1.1. 环境因素</title><p>冲突对于虎来说是被迫的，由于人为干扰导致栖息地退化，虎不断由保护区核心区向缓冲区或者由森林深处向森林边缘扩散，缓冲区和森林边缘是就人类的村庄、道路、牧场等活动区域 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref8">8</xref>]。而虎保护活动的成功也会造成这种局面，种群数量的恢复，导致虎种群数量超过环境容纳量，进而更多的虎向外迁移。栖息地的选择使虎迁移到距人更近的区域，导致当地居民无法维持正常的生活与生计如林下资源收集、放牧、农业生产等，产生负面情绪与恐惧心理，间接引发冲突。虽然虎在共用区域通过生理习性在时间上避开了部分人类干扰活动，但难以在空间上避开人类活动，这一点与其他大型食肉动物相似 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref9">9</xref>]。</p></sec><sec id="s7_1_2"><title>3.1.2. 猎物因素</title><p>众所周知，环境因素会导致野生猎物数量的下降，野生猎物的数量与种类受人为干扰的影响，致使许多地区的猎物丰度不足 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref10">10</xref>]，种群数量超过环境容纳量使虎对野生猎物的平均获取程度已经达到最低限度，这促使虎间接冲突变为对人畜进行攻击的直接冲突。研究表明野生猎物量减少，虎更有可能捕食家畜，而且会因野生猎物量减少的趋势而调整对家畜捕食的策略，即：当野生猎物量开始减少时，会选择最佳可供选择的家畜(牛)；当野生猎物资源过少时，会选择捕食所有可供选择的猎物(马、羊、狗等)满足生存条件 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref11">11</xref>]。</p></sec><sec id="s7_1_3"><title>3.1.3. 生理因素</title><p>生理因素方面引发冲突集中于对野生猎物的获取程度已经达到最低限度的虎。大多研究表示极少数的成年虎会引发冲突，没有领地的亚成体虎、老年虎以及受伤的虎更容易引起冲突，这一类虎往往因为由发育未完全或捕食能力退化造成捕食能力的欠缺，所以将捕食目标转向家畜；而如犬齿断裂这种自然伤害通常不会严重影响捕食能力，并且在大多数情况下这种轻微的自然伤害不会构成虎伤害人畜的直接原因 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref12">12</xref>]。除了对猎物的获取，带崽的母虎会导致冲突的发生，出于对幼崽的保护，在领地内遇人时母虎更容易发起攻击产生冲突。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s7_2"><title>3.2. 人引发冲突的原因</title><sec id="s7_2_1"><title>3.2.1. 发展因素</title><p>由于社会的发展需求，人类活动范围主动与虎活动范围发生重叠，产生了越来越多的人虎共用区域。道路建设、水电工程、农业和林业生产等人为活动对虎的干扰极为严重，同时也大大增加了人虎冲突的几率。研究表明，人为干扰对虎的负面影响超出了野生猎物量减少对虎的负面影响，这种原因由人主导且已经蔓延到虎食物链的各个层次，并形成了自上而下的影响，造成直接性或间接性的干扰，这是由人引发冲突的主要诱因之一 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref13">13</xref>]。人们对虎的容忍程度取决于它们与虎相遇的可能性、对相关机构的信任程度及对虎的耐受性。由于社会发展造成的干扰导致直接与间接冲突的几率增加，不仅降低了人对相关机构的信任度与对虎的耐受性，还会阻碍发展进度。</p></sec><sec id="s7_2_2"><title>3.2.2. 生计因素</title><p>绝大多数受人虎冲突威胁的居民，因保护活动的推行，创收活动的类型和数量越来越受到限制。定居在森林边缘和虎保护区周边的家庭中，绝大多数都依靠该地区的自然资源获得收入和维持生活。进行采集野菜、柴薪等森林资源；为牲畜收集草料等活动时为了生计会频繁的进入人虎共用区域；对虎的生存活动产生影响等，进一步增加了直接冲突的可能性。该地区居民或利益相关者不仅面临着在冲突赔偿与维持生计活动之间的选择，而且他们将被社会因素、经济因素和景观与自然资源因素辖制 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref14">14</xref>]。有研究表明，人与虎的冲突程度是由该地区的贫困水平决定的。此外，虎保护行动使当地居民生计受限，如南亚等国冲突严重地区的居民会因人虎冲突陷入无法发展，导致不可避免的贫穷恶性循环之中 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref15">15</xref>]。</p></sec><sec id="s7_2_3"><title>3.2.3. 安全因素</title><p>虎分布区的居民进行维持生计的活动加剧了人虎冲突的几率，由于担心经济动物被捕食和个人生命受侵害，使当地居民对虎保护的态度消极。虽然绝大多数冲突区域都有赔偿制度，但是为了保护自身的生命财产安全，居民仍会主动与虎产生冲突。20世纪90年代，西藏墨脱县虎害严重导致当地针对性的猎杀引发冲突的虎，而如今的墨脱县，野生虎种群仅剩下1~3只 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref16">16</xref>]。即使人们相信相关机构可以提供保护，但是信任并不能产生人对虎的容忍度 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref17">17</xref>]。例如在俄罗斯成立相关的反应小组来处理由冲突事件时，通常将引发冲突的虎驱逐或射杀，这不仅极易引发虎对居民的二次冲突，也无法避免居民为了安全问题进行的报复性杀戮 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref18">18</xref>]。</p></sec><sec id="s7_2_4"><title>3.2.4. 利益因素</title><p>利益因素是为了与生计因素区分，尤其因当地管理者给予的冲突赔偿额度被质疑，向相关部门证明人畜遇袭涉及的许多复杂问题时，双方的信任度逐渐丧失，部分居民甚至不惜铤而走险进行盗猎活动以获取利益，这同时也进一步加剧人虎冲突的程度 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref19">19</xref>]。盗猎是人引发与虎直接冲突的重要表现，每年都有大量的虎死于盗猎。不仅体现了人受利益的驱使，还体现了打击盗猎活动中相关机构与盗猎者之间将人虎冲突升级至人与人冲突 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref20">20</xref>]。</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s8"><title>4. 人虎冲突的影响</title><sec id="s8_1"><title>4.1. 人虎冲突的显著影响</title><sec id="s8_1_1"><title>4.1.1. 直接冲突的显著影响</title><p>直接冲突的显著影响是最有案可查的，通过研究者对冲突数据的采集过程可以看出，这些数据大多来源于正式或非正式口头访问调查、问卷调查、相关部门提供的赔偿数据、媒体报道等渠道 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref21">21</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref22">22</xref>] 包括对人生命安全保障的缺失、牲畜被捕食的经济损失；对虎的捕杀与驱逐造成的种群数量下降等影响。</p><p>研究者也将这种显著影响作为第一着眼点。因为现有的人虎冲突研究方法已经建立了框架来量化冲突程度、频率和原因，并突出了缓解所涉及的主要问题。但是单纯的衡量直接冲突造成的显著影响，得出的缓解策略往往效果没那么显著。原因在于的缓解策略的制定都是以支付赔偿金为主，无论是向受害人及其家属的赔偿，还是对因冲突造成牲畜损失的赔偿，赔偿速度的缓慢，赔偿的额度远低于医疗费用和牲畜平均市价都会造成受害者的不满。这些情况在低收入国家尤为常见 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref3">3</xref>]。</p><p>除补偿之外，也有很多不同方式的缓解策略如管制狩猎、一些国家正在着手清除引发冲突的虎和减少森林共用资源等正在实施 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref23">23</xref>]，但是从报道的结果来看这些方法收效甚微。这些效果不显著的原因归结于冲突频发地区居民对森林的依赖性与相关单位的投资侧重性。这种影响解决的不彻底还会促进间接冲突的衍变为直接冲突，其影响会更显著。已有的研究表明，随着人虎冲突的不断升级，引发冲突的虎被杀的可能性也在上升，尤其冲突越严重的地区，对虎被处死的接受程度也越高 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref24">24</xref>]。</p></sec><sec id="s8_1_2"><title>4.1.2. 间接冲突的显著影响</title><p>间接冲突因其表现形式的多样性，对人与虎造成的显著影响更广泛。通常表现为人虎共用区域内社会发展进度缓慢、居民生计难以维持、收入降低；迁入共用区域的虎数量上升、人虎直接冲突事件增加等。从逐年上升的人虎冲突事件数量与越来越多的虎在共用区域内的死亡报道可以发现，这种影响更能引发当地居民对虎的消极态度，出于对虎冲突的恐惧或个人利益驱使，人虎冲突频繁的国家甚至会激起当地居民自发对虎的报复性杀害。而现存的缓解策略如生态移民、开发生态旅游等其他生计的方法大多也来自于这种显著影响。然而由于间接冲突引发原因的复杂性，现有策略无法同时顾及人与虎双方的利益。</p><p>以低收入国家重新安置冲突地区居民这种方式为例，主观上生态移民之后，居民们将避开风险区，退出与虎的共用森林不再受冲突袭扰，绝大多数的受访者进也对重新安置表现出积极态度 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref25">25</xref>]。但是居民对生态移民的要求是得到所需的基本生活设施支持，包括电力、住房、饮用水、医疗、学校、交通和通信保障等 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref26">26</xref>]。这就意味着相关单位要对这部分着重投资。根据管理者的权衡，每年因冲突赔付的损失与生态移民整个流程的资金投入二者的经济比较是一方面，另一方面生态移民之后这些居民的生计选择也是一个问题，如果处理不当，即使解决了人虎冲突的问题，会不会引发新一轮的人与人的冲突。再者，生态移民之后，捕食能力下降的虎将失去家畜这一猎物来源，对这些虎的生存也带来了危机，导致虎死亡率上升。凡此种种，这均造成了目前不可见，但会延伸到显著影响解决之后未预计到的潜在影响。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s8_2"><title>4.2. 人虎冲突的潜在影响</title><p>潜在影响是冲突事件中未得到合理解决或延缓解决，造成受害者与受损者心理上或社会上的影响，也可以看作为显著影响催生的影响或二次影响。主要表现为受冲突侵害居民因生理缺失导致心理创伤、家庭主要成员遇袭身亡加重家庭负担、冲突中受伤的虎引发二次冲突、对虎的消极态度进行报复性杀戮、共用区域内的生产扩大促进人虎冲突等。这种影响往往需要结合生态学、地理学、社会学等共同研究 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref23">23</xref>]。</p><p>潜在影响也更能反映在缓解冲突时，单纯的减缓显著影响是一把双刃剑，这种直观的方式会对冲突的双方都造成伤害。例如，将引发冲突的虎迁移来替代处死或关进动物园，这种做法被认为是可行的替代办法，并作为一种潜在的保护方式，在缓解冲突的同时可以虎减少的死亡率，补充或重建野生种群数量 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref27">27</xref>]。但根据现有研究证明，引发冲突的虎超过一半都存在身体缺陷，包括自然伤、种内斗争受伤以及枪伤、套伤等。随着虎种群的恢复，数量超过环境容纳量后，更多的虎会迁出，使这些本就捕食能力退化的虎更加岌岌可危，并可能激发虎对人或家畜的持续性攻击 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref28">28</xref>]。</p><p>对潜在影响研究的不足，根本原因在于过度关注单方面需求，即关注虎生态需求或人补偿需求。虽然越来越多的研究者已经关注到潜在影响的严重性，但对于双方的解决办法仍集中在短期的有效性上。例如，当家畜的数量达到一定程度，直接冲突会加剧，同时被虎杀害的数量也会增加，即使野生猎物数量远高于正常可持续水平也会促成这样的结果 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref29">29</xref>]。人对自然资源的利用获取得不到满足，导致相关利益者经济受损，受冲突侵害的人群产生负面情绪，从而对虎做出过激行动或者获利举动；对引发冲突的虎进行处死或封闭，也会导致野生虎数量下降，从而失去了对其保护的初衷，使进一步的管理陷入僵局。这意味着面对资金短缺、物种和栖息地减少、信息缺乏以及策略成功的不确定性，决策者往往是被迫选择缓解人虎冲突的策略 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref30">30</xref>]。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s9"><title>5. 解决人虎冲突的对策与建议</title><sec id="s9_1"><title>5.1. 科学管理人虎共用区域，为虎保留足够生存空间</title><p>人虎冲突集中区域多是人虎共用资源地，在空间尺度上，居民为了生计，虎为了生存，二者争夺其中资源。为了避免资源竞争，支持虎保护事业的成功进行，应该科学的管理人虎共用区域，为虎保留足够的生存空间，开辟一片专属于虎的“不可侵犯的区域” [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref31">31</xref>]，即禁止人类频繁进入的区域，仅限管理与巡视人员定期进入收集定位观测相机数据与种群数量调查等活动。对这片区域的虎种群数量增长趋势做出预测，根据划定区域的大小、栖息地类型以及猎物丰度等，对该地区可承载虎的最大只数进行严格限制。针对虎数量随时间逐渐增长至超过环境容纳量的问题，除因伤病死亡与自然死亡外，对丧失领地的老年虎与伤虎等易迁出栖息地引发冲突的虎进行主动收容至野生动物园等相关机构进行管理，防止虎因捕食能力降低而选择迁出区域，从根本上避免由虎迁出而引发的直接与间接冲突。</p><p>由于多数虎引发的冲突集中于猎物不足这一原因，故应在虎不可侵犯区域内引入该地区原有的野生猎物，在不破坏该地区生态平衡的前提下，增加野生猎物种群数量与丰度，以维持虎的食物获取程度。同时，为避免野生猎物如野猪、狍、梅花鹿等数量增长速度超过虎恢复速度，在虎数量恢复缓慢时需对野生猎物数量进行宏观调控，避免引发野猪数量过多侵害农田等其他人兽冲突。这一对策针对虎的长久保护，避免了人虎共用区域的产生，使人与虎没有在空间尺度上的交集，消除了人与虎在野外相遇的条件，在保护虎的同时杜绝了冲突的隐患。</p></sec><sec id="s9_2"><title>5.2. 精准扶持居民替代生计，有效缓解人虎冲突</title><p>目前的策略很少有彻底的、长期的冲突缓解方案，居民受冲突影响后，为了维持生计仍会继续生活在虎的阴影下。而冲突往往由复杂和深层次的原因导致，如果从长远的角度来看，必须用更广泛的方法来改善这样的冲突形式 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref32">32</xref>]。为了满足人虎共用区域内居民的生计需求与，回避由于生态移民或者禁牧等策略带来的负面影响，需要选择长期有效的替代生计来规避日常生产生活中受虎的负面影响，保护居民的生命财产安全。即将林下经济活动、农业生产以及放牧等活动用其他合理生计替代，降低人与虎相遇的几率，达到缓解人虎冲突的效果。</p><p>由于共用区域内居民普遍都是该地区最贫穷的居民，经济能力的限制使他们无法为自己寻找替代生计，长久以来的农业生产与林下活动也导致可胜任的工作有限，所以替代生计需要当地政府以及相关机构的精准扶持。例如在不可侵犯区域外围开发为生态旅游景观，在景观与不可侵犯区中间建立缓冲区防止虎迁出至景观区引发冲突的可能。对当地居民进行培训成为景区工作人员，让以前的资源利用者作为如今的资源保护者。由相关机构协助当地自主管理，所得收益除维护景区支出与相关管理费用外，其余收益合理分配以作为员工收入，使保护工作顺利进行的同时维持了当地居民的生计，也杜绝了居民进入虎分布区对虎造成人为干扰甚至引发冲突。</p></sec><sec id="s9_3"><title>5.3. 尽快出台人虎冲突补偿的统一标准，消除虎保护的负面影响</title><p>经济补偿是冲突发生后最直观消除负面影响的短期的缓解措施 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref33">33</xref>]。由于人虎冲突发生的地点和当地社区情况不同，因此制定的补偿措施也各有差异，经济补偿主要的问题就存在于标准的不统一。目前我国针对人虎冲突严重的地区还没有统一的补偿标准，均由各省份自行拟定推行，而不同地区的补偿差异与相同地区内受害者之间的补偿差异会提高对虎的消极态度。所以从消除虎保护的负面影响方面，所以统一补偿标准是必要的。</p><p>标准的制定主要在于定损，即人员伤亡补偿取决于医疗费、误工费、丧葬费等费用；牲畜补偿取决于虎的取食量、残骸的可利用量和当地该种牲畜的平均价格等。统一这些标准因各地的经济差异，从补偿比例标准进行统一是最有效的选择。以牲畜补偿为例，牲畜平均价格减去可利用残骸获取的金额，剩下的差价根据牲畜的死亡地点分析以下三种情况：牧主刻意引诱虎捕食、散养牲畜与虎相遇被捕食、虎主动进入牧区捕食，并根据三种情况制定不同占比，刻意引诱虎捕食补偿比例最低、虎主动进入牧区捕食补偿比例最高，以避免利用伤病牲畜死亡谋取利益。</p><p>相关部门的记录因为补偿制度的限制，为了确保数据的真实性常常需要经过报损、当地部门组织专家调查组和实地核查等步骤 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref34">34</xref>]，这不仅增加相关部门的工作量，也增大了经济负担。对于补偿统一标准的执行最好由保险公司进行，只需要受虎威胁的居民为自己或牲畜购买保险，冲突发生后直接向保险公司报损，公司便会依照补偿标准在实地勘察过后进行补偿。由于人虎冲突的几率性，并非所有参保的居民都会受到冲突危害，保险公司也可以从人虎冲突险中获得利益。减轻了相关部门的工作与经济负担，居民也可以得到合理的补偿。</p></sec><sec id="s9_4"><title>5.4. 定期开展虎保护宣教活动，提升公众参与的积极性</title><p>早期人们对人与虎的冲突意识不强，直到发展到冲突对社会经济的等方面造成压力，对双方的影响增大，管理相关研究才开始出现。为了人与虎对立的传统观点的转变，需要让受冲突侵害的人们更好的了解冲突如何发生和为什么发生 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref35">35</xref>]。这就需要制定合理的虎保护教育活动。虎的保护教育策略在部分虎分布地区已经取得成效，对受教育者的影响有一定良性效果，这种方式对与虎共存的态度有一个优异的引导作用。尤其对于受到虎伤害的家庭，根深蒂固的仇恨与对濒危物种的保护，孰轻孰重在各人心里能否转变，这需要教育开展的可靠性与长久的时效性 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref36">36</xref>]。虎保护教育不局限于相关从业者，所有生活在冲突区域内的居民都应参与其中，起到相互督促学习的作用，让居民真正能了解到虎的重要性以及与虎共存的可行性。</p></sec><sec id="s9_5"><title>5.5. 倡导并推行跨学科联合研究，制定人虎冲突解决方案</title><p>从上述对人虎冲突的相关影响可以看出，对人虎双方的限制产生了矛盾，出于对虎保护的追求，为了避免对虎的迫害，必须令利益相关者存在最低限度的容忍；出于人的生计的维护，与虎的冲突在所难免，补偿计划会减轻眼前的经济损失，累积的非经济损失，例如未来的潜在收益损失以及投入的时间和精力 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.38487-ref37">37</xref>]。这种复杂的问题思考仅靠保护生态学的角度无法涵盖，跨学科的研究方法将是协调人民生计与自然关系的关键。在潜在冲突形成之前，通过生态学对虎生物学特性的研究、经济学对经济损失的研究、社会学对居民负面情绪的研究等多学科的结合，建立复合策略来解决将要出现的争议。这也将是未来对人虎冲突研究的重心，只有将繁琐的问题拆分交由相关专业的研究者，最后整合为整个问题的解答，才能提出科学合理的解决人虎冲突的策略，既为野生虎提供足够的自由栖息环境使其种群数量恢复，又能为生活在人虎共用区内的居民提供生产和生活保障，逐步达到人–虎和谐共处的境地。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s10"><title>文章引用</title><p>高壮勇,王建锋,张明海. 人虎冲突产生原因及影响分析及解决对策Analysis of Causes and Effects of Human-Tiger Conflict and Countermeasures[J]. 世界生态学, 2020, 09(04): 294-303. https://doi.org/10.12677/IJE.2020.94038</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>参考文献</title></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">马建章, 张明海, 姜广顺, 陆军. 我国老虎及其栖息地保护面临的挑战与对策[J]. 野生动物学报, 2015, 36(2): 129-133.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Aryal, A., Lamsal, R.P., Ji, W. and Raubenheimer, D. (2016) Are There Sufficient Prey and Protected Areas in Nepal to Sustain an Increasing Tiger Population? Ethology Ecology &amp; Evolution, 28, 117-120.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/03949370.2014.1002115</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Dhungana, R., Savini, T., Karki, J.B. and Bumrungsri, S. (2016) Mitigating Human-Tiger Conflict: An Assessment of Compensation Payments and Tiger Removals in Chitwan National Park, Nepal. Tropical Conservation Science, 9, 776-787. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/194008291600900213</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McKay, J.E., St John, F.A.V., Harihar, A., Martyr, D., Lead-er-Williams, N., Milliyanawati, B., Agustin, I., Anggriawan, Y., Karlina, Kartika, E., Mangunjaya, F., Struebig, M.J. and Linkie, M. (2018) Tolerating Tigers: Gaining Local and Spiritual Perspectives on Human-Tiger Interactions in Sumatra through Rural Community Interviews. PLoS ONE, 13, e0201447. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0201447</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Johnson, A., Vongkhamheng, C., Hedemark, M. and Saithongdam, T. (2006) Effects of Human-Carnivore Conflict on Tiger (Panthera tigris) and Prey Populations in Lao PDR. Animal Conservation, 9, 421-430.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-1795.2006.00049.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Miller, J.R.B., Jhala, Y.V. and Jena, J. (2016) Livestock Losses and Hotspots of Attack from Tigers and Leopards in Kanha Tiger Reserve, Central India. Regional Environmental Change, 16, 17-29. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10113-015-0871-5</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chakrabarti, S., Jhala, Y.V., Dutta, S., Qureshi, Q., Kadivar, R.F. and Rana, V.J. (2016) Adding Constraints to Predation through Allometric Relation of Scats to Consumption. Journal of Animal Ecology, 85, 660-670.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/1365-2656.12508</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lamichhane, B.R., Persoon, G.A., Leirs, H., Musters, C.J.M., Subedi, N., Gairhe, K.P., Pokheral, C.P., Poudel, S., Mishra, R., Dhakal, M., Smith, J.L.D. and de longh, H.H. (2017) Are Conflict-Causing Tigers Different? Another Perspective for Understanding Human-Tiger Conflict in Chitwan Na-tional Park, Nepal. Global Ecology and Conservation, 11, 177-187. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gecco.2017.06.003</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Xiao, W.H., Hebblewhite, M., Robinson, H., Feng, L.M., Zhou, B., Mou, P., Wang, T.M. and Ge, J.P. (2018) Relationships between Humans and Ungulate Prey Shape Amur Tiger Occurrence in a Core Protected Area along the Sino-Russian Border. Ecology and Evolution, 8, 11677-11693. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.4620</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Barber-Meyer, S.M., Jnawali, S.R., Karki, J.B., Khanal, P., Lohani, S., Long, B., MacKenzie, D.I., Pandav, B, Pradhan, N.M.B., Shrestha, R., Subedi, N., Thapa, K. and Wikramanayake, E. (2012) Influence of Prey Depletion and Human Disturbance on Tiger Occupancy in Nepal. Journal of Zoology, 289, 10-18. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-7998.2012.00956.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Khorozyan, I., Ghoddousi, A., Soofi, M. and Waltert, M. (2015) Big Cats Kill More Livestock When Wild Prey Reaches a Minimum Threshold. Biological Conservation, 192, 268-275. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2015.09.031</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Goodrich, J.M., Seryodkin, I.V., Miquelle, D.G., Kerley, L.L., Quigley, H.B. and Hornocker, M.G. (2011) Effects of Canine Breakage on Tiger Survival, Reproduction and Human-Tiger Conflict. Journal of Zoology, 285, 93-98.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-7998.2011.00819.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Li, Z.L., Kang, A., Gu, J.Y., Xue, Y.G., Ren, Y., Zhu, Z.W., Liu, P.Q., Ma, J.Z. and Jiang, G.S. (2016) Effects of Human Disturbance on Vegetation, Prey and Amur Tigers in Hunchun Nature Reserve, China. Ecological Modelling, 353, 28-36. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2016.08.014</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Young, J.C., Marzano, M., White, R.M., Mccracken, D.I., Redpath, S.M., Carss, D.N., Quine, C.P. and Watt, A.D. (2010) The Emergence of Biodiversity Conflicts from Biodi-versity Impacts: Characteristics and Management Strategies. Biodiversity and Conservation, 19, 393-73-3990. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10531-010-9941-7</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Inskip, C., Ridout, M., Fahad, Z., Tully, R., Barlow, A., Barlow, C.G., Islam, M.A., Roberts, T. and MacMillan, D. (2013) Human-Tiger Conflict in Context: Risks to Lives and Live-lihoods in the Bangladesh Sundarbans. Human Ecology, 41, 169-186. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10745-012-9556-6</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">王渊, 刘务林, 刘锋, 李晟, 朱雪林, 蒋志刚, 冯利民, 李炳章. 西藏墨脱县孟加拉虎种群数量调查[J]. 兽类学报, 2019, 39(5): 504-513.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Struebig, M.J., Matthew, L., Deere, N.J., Martyr, D.J., Betty, M., Faulkner, S.C., Le Comber, S.C., MangunJaya, F.M., Leader-Williams, N., McKay, J.E. and St John, F.A.V. (2018) Addressing Human-Tiger Conflict Using Socio-Ecological Information on Tolerance and Risk. Nature Communications, 9, 3455. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-018-05983-y</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Goodrich, J.M., Seryodkin, I.V., Miquelle, D.G. and Bereznuk, S.L. (2010) Conflicts between Amur (Siberian) Tigers and Humans in the Russian Far East. Biological Conservation, 144, 584-592. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2010.10.016</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Das, C.S. (2012) Tiger Straying Incidents in Indian Sundarban: Statistical Analysis of Case Studies as Well as Depredation Caused by Conflict. European Journal of Wildlife Research, 58, 205-214. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10344-011-0565-3</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Young, J.K., Ma, Z., Laudati, A. and Berger, J. (2015) Hu-man-Carnivore Interactions: Lessons Learned from Communities in the American West. Human Dimensions of Wildlife, 20, 349-366. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/10871209.2015.1016388</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nyhus, P.J. and Tilson, R. (2004) Characterizing Hu-man-Tiger Conflict in Sumatra, Indonesia: Implications for Conservation. Oryx, 38, 68-74. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0030605304000110</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wang, T.M., Feng, L.M., Mou, P., Wu, J.G., Smith, J.L.D., Xiao, W.H., Yang, H.T., Dou, H.L., Zhao, X.D., Cheng, C.Y., Zhou, B., Wu, H.Y., Zhang, L., Tian, Y., Guo, Q.X., Kou, X.J., Han, X.M., Miquelle, D.G., Oilver, C.D., Xu, R.M. and Ge, J.P. (2016) Amur Tigers and Leopards Return-ing to China: Direct Evidence and a Landscape Conservation Plan. Landscape Ecology, 31, 491-503. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10980-015-0278-1</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Barua, M., Bhagwat, S.A. and Jadhav, S. (2013) The Hidden Dimensions of Human-Wildlife Conflict: Health Impacts, Opportunity and Transaction Costs. Biological Conservation, 157, 309-316. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2012.07.014</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Inskip, C., Fahad, Z., Tully, R., Roberts, T. and Macmillan, D. (2014) Understanding Carnivore Killing Behaviour: Exploring the Motivations for Tiger Killing in the Sundarbans, Bangladesh. Biological Conservation, 180, 42-50.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2014.09.028</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Harihar, A., Verissimo, D. and MacMillan, D.C. (2015) Beyond Compensation: Integrating Local Communities’ Livelihood Choices in Large Carnivore Conservation. Global Environmental Change, 33, 122-130. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2015.05.004</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ramesh, T., Kalle, R., Sankar, K., Qureshi, Q., Giordano, A.J. and Downs, C.T. (2019) To Resettle or Not? Socioeconomic Characteristics, Livelihoods, and Perceptions toward Resolving Human-Tiger Conflict in the Nilgiri Biosphere Reserve, India. Land Use Policy, 83, 32-46. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landusepol.2019.01.019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Goodrich, J.M. and Miquelle, D.G. (2005) Translocation of Problem Amur Tigers Panthera tigtis altaica to Alleviate Tiger-Human Conflicts. Oryx, 39, 454-457. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0030605305001146</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gurung, B., Smith, J.L.D., Mcdougal, C., Karki, J.B. and Bar-low, A. (2008) Factors Associated with Human-Killing Tigers in Chitwan National Park, Nepal. Biological Conservation, 141, 3069-3078. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2008.09.013</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ahearn, S.C., Smith, J.L.D., Joshi, A.R. and Ji, D. (2001) TIGMOD: An Individual-Based Spatially Explicit Model for Simulating Tiger/Human Interaction in Multiple Use Forests. Ecological Modelling, 140, 81-97.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0304-3800(01)00258-7</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Barlow, A.C.D., Greenwood, C.J., Ahmad, I.U. and Smith, J.L.D. (2010) Use of an Action-Selection Framework for Human-Carnivore Conflict in the Bangladesh Sundarbans. Conservation Biology, 24, 1338-1347. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1523-1739.2010.01496.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bhardwaj, G.S. and Kumar, A. (2019) The Comparison of Shape Indices and Perimeter Interface of Selected Protected Areas Especially with Reference to Sariska Tiger Reserve, India. Global Ecology and Conservation, 17, e00504.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gecco.2018.e00504</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Dickman, A.J. (2010) Complexities of Conflict: The Importance of Considering Social Factors for Effectively Resolving Human-Wildlife Conflict. Animal Conservation, 13, 458-466. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-1795.2010.00368.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zarco-González, M.M., Monroy-Vilchis, O., Sima, D., López, A. and García-Martínez, A. (2018) Why Some Management Practices Determine the Risk of Livestock Predation by Felids in the Selva Maya, Mexico? Conservation Strategies. Perspectives in Ecology and Conservation, 16, 146-150. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pecon.2018.06.007</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">张常智. 东北虎及其猎物种群监测和人虎冲突研究[D]: [博士学位论文]. 哈尔滨: 东北林业大学, 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Messmer, T.A. (2000) The Emergence of Human-Wildlife Conflict Management: Turning Challenges into Opportunities. International Biodeterioration &amp; Biodegradation, 45, 97-102. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0964-8305(00)00045-7</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mukhacheva, A.S., Derugina, V.V., Maksimova, G.D. and Soutyrina, S.V. (2015) Amur Tiger Conservation Education Program: A Pilot Study on Program Effectiveness. Integrative Zoology, 10, 403-407. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/1749-4877.12145</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38487-ref37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Crespin, S.J. and Simonetti, J.A. (2018) Reconciling Farming and Wild Nature: Integrating Human-Wildlife Coexistence into the Land-Sharing and Land-Sparing Framework. Ambio, 48, 131-138.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s13280-018-1059-2</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>