<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" article-type="research article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Advances in Psychology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2160-7273</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Scientific Research Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12677/AP.2020.1011194</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AP-38715</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>AP20201100000_65390077.pdf</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>人文社科</subject><subject> 合作期刊</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
 
 
  进化心理学视阈下宽恕的心理机制
  The Psychological Mechanism of Forgiveness in the Perspective of Evolutionary Psychology
 
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>余</surname><given-names>浩然</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>姚</surname><given-names>本先</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>张</surname><given-names>威威</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>潘</surname><given-names>俊星</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>武</surname><given-names>杨杰</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff3"><addr-line>合肥师范学院，安徽 合肥</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><addr-line>安徽师范大学教育科学学院，安徽 芜湖</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>null</addr-line></aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>11</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1664</fpage><lpage>1675</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Copyright  2014 by authors and Scientific Research Publishing Inc. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY). http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
 
 
   
   进化心理学认为，宽恕的心理机制是为了应对同种侵犯的适应性问题而演化出来的。宽恕的心理机制对侵犯者的剥削风险和关系价值进行评估，并在综合考虑剥削风险和关系价值之后做出是否宽恕的决策。在这一理论框架下，一些研究探讨了剥削风险和关系价值对宽恕的影响，建立了宽恕心理机制的模型，还发现了宽恕心理机制对道歉的影响。 未来的研究需要对剥削风险和关系价值的定义和测量进行深入的研究，探索宽恕的心理机制的内在过程及其相应的神经机制。 Evolutionary psychology asserts that the psychological mechanism of forgiveness evolved in re-sponse to the adaptive problem named transgression from conspecifics. The psychological me-chanism of forgiveness assesses the exploitation risk and relationship value of the aggressor and makes a decision about whether to forgive after comparing exploitation risk and relationship value. Within this theoretical framework, several studies have explored the impact of exploitation risk and relationship value on forgiveness, modeled the psychological mechanism of forgiveness, and also found the impact of the psychological mechanism of forgiveness on apology. Future research is needed on the definition and measurement of exploitation risk and relationship value to explore the processes underlying the psychological mechanisms of forgiveness and their corresponding neural mechanisms. 
  
 
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>进化心理学，宽恕，关系价值，剥削风险，心理机制, Evolutionary Psychology</kwd><kwd> Forgiveness</kwd><kwd> Relationship Values</kwd><kwd> Exploitation Risk</kwd><kwd> Psychological Mechanism</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>摘要</title><p>进化心理学认为，宽恕的心理机制是为了应对同种侵犯的适应性问题而演化出来的。宽恕的心理机制对侵犯者的剥削风险和关系价值进行评估，并在综合考虑剥削风险和关系价值之后做出是否宽恕的决策。在这一理论框架下，一些研究探讨了剥削风险和关系价值对宽恕的影响，建立了宽恕心理机制的模型，还发现了宽恕心理机制对道歉的影响。 未来的研究需要对剥削风险和关系价值的定义和测量进行深入的研究，探索宽恕的心理机制的内在过程及其相应的神经机制。</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>关键词</title><p>进化心理学，宽恕，关系价值，剥削风险，心理机制</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>The Psychological Mechanism of Forgiveness in the Perspective of Evolutionary Psychology<sup> </sup></title><p>Haoran Yu<sup>1</sup>, Benxian Yao<sup>2*</sup>, Weiwei Zhang<sup>1</sup>, Junxing Pan<sup>1</sup>, Yangjie Wu<sup>1</sup></p><p><sup>1</sup>School of Educational Science, Anhui Normal University, Wuhu Anhui</p><p><sup>2</sup>Hefei Normal University, Hefei Anhui</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/11-1132055x4_hanspub.png" /></p><p>Received: Oct. 19<sup>th</sup>, 2020; accepted: Nov. 12<sup>th</sup>, 2020; published: Nov. 23<sup>rd</sup>, 2020</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/11-1132055x5_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Evolutionary psychology asserts that the psychological mechanism of forgiveness evolved in response to the adaptive problem named transgression from conspecifics. The psychological mechanism of forgiveness assesses the exploitation risk and relationship value of the aggressor and makes a decision about whether to forgive after comparing exploitation risk and relationship value. Within this theoretical framework, several studies have explored the impact of exploitation risk and relationship value on forgiveness, modeled the psychological mechanism of forgiveness, and also found the impact of the psychological mechanism of forgiveness on apology. Future research is needed on the definition and measurement of exploitation risk and relationship value to explore the processes underlying the psychological mechanisms of forgiveness and their corresponding neural mechanisms.</p><p>Keywords:Evolutionary Psychology, Forgiveness, Relationship Values, Exploitation Risk, Psychological Mechanism</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.38715-formula2"><graphic xlink:href="//html.hanspub.org/file/11-1132055x7_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><p>Copyright &#169; 2020 by author(s) and Hans Publishers Inc.</p><p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/11-1132055x8_hanspub.png" /> <img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/11-1132055x9_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>1. 宽恕的心理机制是进化而来的</title><p>进化心理学是心理学领域一种新的范式，是基于进化论解释人类心理是如何演化而来的元理论，为整合心理学各领域的知识提供了概念框架(Buss, 2005)。进化心理学的主要观点是，人类的心理是为了应对在人类演化过程中反复出现的生存和繁衍的适应性问题，提高适合度(fitness，代表了生物个体成功地生存和繁衍的概率)，由自然选择塑造而成的，而人类所面临的生存和繁衍的问题纷繁复杂，各种问题差异巨大，需要人类处理不同类型的信息，做出不同的反应，因此为了高效地解决这些问题，人类进化出了许多心理机制(psychological mechanism)，这些心理机制专门解决特定类型的适应性问题(Buss, 2005, 2009, 2015)。进化形成的心理机制作为有机体内部的一组决策规则，必须是解决了进化历史中反复出现的生存和繁衍的特定问题。心理机制通过接受小部分特定的信息，向有机体预示它正面临的适应性问题，根据其决策规则将信息转换为生理活动、其他心理机制所需的信息或者外显行为，来形成特定适应性问题的解决方案(Buss, 2015)。正是因为这样的心理机制帮助有机体成功地生存和繁衍，所以它们才得以存在于现存的有机体身上。</p><p>进化心理学视角下的宽恕的心理机制(forgiveness)就是在人类进化过程中形成的(McCullough, Kurzban, &amp; Tabak, 2013a)。具有社会性的物种普遍存在着同种个体间侵犯的现象，通过侵犯同种的其他个体，侵犯者可以获得食物、配偶和领地等提高自身适合度的收益(Cluttonbrock &amp; Parker, 1995)。远古人类也要应对来自同种个体的侵犯(Pinker, 2012)，为了防止再次受到侵犯，受害的一方可以选择报复做出侵犯行为的一方(McCullough et al., 2013a)，然而宽恕也是灵长类动物和人类比较常见的应对方式(De Waal &amp; Pokorny, 2005; De Waal, 2000; McCullough, 2008)。宽恕可以给受害者带来几个方面的好处。首先，虽然受害者可以通过报复侵犯者来弥补自己的损失，但是由于侵犯者也可以反过来报复受害者，使得受害者蒙受更大的损失，所以这样不断的相互报复会使得两败俱伤，对双方都没有好处，而选择宽恕可以避免“冤冤相报”的循环。不仅如此，报复还可能会破坏长期的、建设性的关系，从而使受害者不能在将来得到侵犯者的帮助，比如侵犯者是受害者的朋友或者亲属，受害者选择报复，可能会破坏他(她)与侵犯者的关系，甚至与侵犯者反目成仇(Burnette, McCullough, Van Tongeren, &amp; Davis, 2012; McCullough, 2008; McCullough et al., 2013a)。因此，为了避免报复可能造成的更大损失，受害者可以选择宽恕侵犯者。研究者通过计算机仿真实验发现，在多轮囚徒困境博弈中，当两个参与者都采取“针锋相对”(tit-for-tat)的策略(参与者在第一轮游戏中选择合作，之后的每一轮中的选择合作还是背叛取决于上一轮中另一位参与者的决定) (Rapoport, Chammah, &amp; Orwant, 1965)，只要出现一次背叛，最终会导致参与者陷入相互背叛的循环，进而降低双方的收益。如果采取“慷慨的针锋相对(generous tit for tat)”的策略(参与者在第一轮游戏中选择合作，之后如果上一轮游戏中另一方采取合作，则本轮中参与者采取合作，反之如果另一方采取背叛，则本轮中参与者有可能采取合作，也有可能采取背叛) (Wu &amp; Axelrod, 1995)，就会降低陷入相互背叛的循环的可能性(McCullough et al., 2013a)，因而从长远来看更有利于双方的利益。对人类的亲密关系的研究也发现，为了维护亲密关系，关系中的双方必须宽恕对方危害较小的侵犯，否则由于受害者往往夸大自己所受的伤害，他(她)会给予侵犯者更大的伤害，这会使侵犯者感到不公平，并更大程度地报复受害者，于是双方便陷入了报复升级的循环(Fitness &amp; Peterson, 2008)，最终使他们都付出高昂的代价，所以亲密关系中的人比非亲密关系中的人更能宽恕彼此的小的侵犯。总之宽恕对维护有价值的关系、避免报复不断升级以及避免化友为敌都有积极的作用。面对在人类进化过程中反复发生的来自同种个体的侵犯，人类进化出了宽恕的心理机制，来应对这一适应性问题，从而更好地维护人际合作，提高自身成功地生存和繁衍的概率。</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>2. 宽恕的心理机制的决策过程</title><p>进化而来的宽恕的心理机制为了应对同种个体侵犯的问题，必须将特定的输入信息转换为有机体关于宽恕的决策，这样的输入信息得到加工从而计算出剥削风险(exploitation risk)和关系价值(relationship value)。在计算出剥削风险和关系价值之后，宽恕的心理机制对它们的大小进行比较，进而决定是否宽恕。如果计算出的关系价值大于剥削风险，则宽恕的心理机制更倾向于宽恕，反之当剥削风险大于关系价值时，宽恕的心理机制倾向于不宽恕。剥削风险是指侵犯者在未来可能给受害者造成的适合度损失的可能性，关系价值指受害者与侵犯者持续交往而带来适合度增加的可能性(Billingsley &amp; Losin, 2017; Burnette et al., 2012; McCullough, 2008; McCullough et al., 2013a; McCullough, Luna, Berry, Tabak, &amp; Bono, 2010; McCullough, Pedersen, Tabak, &amp; Carter, 2014; Petersen, Sell, Tooby, &amp; Cosmides, 2012)。</p><p>对剥削风险的评估取决于两个方面的信息，一方面是侵犯者再次侵犯受害者的意愿，另一方面是侵犯者是否有造成侵犯的能力(McCullough et al., 2013a)。例如，假设一位受害者遭到了侵犯，但侵犯者无意做出侵犯，并且在没有他人强迫的情况下表示自己以后绝不会再次侵犯受害者，那么侵犯者很大可能上不会再做出侵犯(Fehr, Gelfand, &amp; Nag, 2010; McCullough et al., 2010; McCullough et al., 2006)。再比如，在侵犯发生之后，侵犯者对受害者表示同情、道歉、做出补偿或者后悔，也表明侵犯者不愿再对受害者造成侵犯(Gold &amp; Weiner, 2000; Nadler &amp; Liviatan, 2006)。因此，受害者更愿意宽恕那些无意间、在不可避免的情况下或者没有意识到行为后果的情况下造成侵犯的人。但是侵犯者的上述表现不一定准确反映了其真实的想法，口头道歉可能是假装出来的(Frank, 1988)，因此道歉的可信度就成了受害者需要考虑的因素(Henrich, 2009)。例如，侵犯者不仅向受害者道歉，还做出了相应的补偿来弥补侵犯给受害者造成的损失(King-Casas et al., 2008)，或者侵犯者允许受害者报复自己(Matsumura &amp; Hayden, 2006)，甚至是通过自杀来表达自己的歉意(Syme &amp; Hagen, 2019)，都能反映侵犯者对维护和受害者关系的强烈意愿，因此是更可信的道歉。而且脸红也是表明侵犯者愧疚的重要线索，受害者认为那些在侵犯之后脸红的人比那些不脸红的人更具有同情心而且更值得信任(De Jong, Peters, &amp; De Cremer, 2003)，因为脸红往往标志着侵犯者的愧疚有强烈的生理唤醒，说明产生了较强的惭愧情绪，所以这样的表现反映了侵犯者不愿再伤害受害者。除了上述的与判断侵犯者意图有关的信息之外，如果有信息显示侵犯者不再有侵犯的能力，那么受害者也会更愿意宽恕侵犯者。比如在部落战争中，失败的一方会放下武器，表明自己放弃了侵犯的能力，而胜利的一方会对他们网开一面，不再伤害他们(McCullough et al., 2013a)。总之侵犯者在主观上没有侵犯意图，表现出后悔、惭愧或者向受害者真诚地道歉都标志着侵犯者有较低的剥削风险。</p><p>进化而来的宽恕的心理机制还要计算维持与侵犯者的关系会在将来给受害者带来多少收益，即剥削风险的大小。如果受害者还能在未来从他(她)和侵犯者的关系中获得好处，那么受害者会倾向于宽恕侵犯者。进化心理学假设宽恕往往与亲密(closeness)、承诺(commitment)以及依恋(attachment)有关(McCullough et al., 2013a)，而这些反映了关系价值。来自多个实证研究的结果都表明，人们更愿意宽恕那些与自己的关系较为亲密的人(Finkel, Rusbult, Kumashiro, &amp; Hannon, 2002; Karremans &amp; Aarts, 2007; McCullough et al., 2010)，这正是由于在亲密关系中双方更容易获得长期的互动带来的好处，而与不太亲密的人之间的关系难以获得较大的收益。如果受害者认为继续维持和侵犯者的关系可以帮助自己达成一些重要的目标，那么受害者对侵犯者的关系价值的评价也会更高(Ohtsubo &amp; Yagi, 2015)。虽然亲密关系可以通过交往建立起来，但是寻找可靠伙伴的过程本身也要付出代价(Hruschka &amp; Henrich, 2006)，所以维持现有的亲密关系往往是更好的做法，受害者也就倾向于宽恕与自己有亲密关系的侵犯者。</p><p>宽恕的心理机制通过对相关信息进行加工，评估剥削风险和关系价值的相对大小，使个体做出是否宽恕的决策，在心理测量上这样的过程可以被认为是个体在某些动机上的变化。起初有研究者认为宽恕是受害者对侵犯者在三种动机水平上的变化，包括1) 对侵犯者实施报复的动机水平的降低，2) 回避侵犯者的动机水平的降低和3) 对侵犯者表达善意的动机水平的提高，并根据这一模型编制了包含报复、回避和善意三个维度的人际侵犯动机量表(Transgression-Related Interpersonal Motivations Inventory，简称TRIM-18)来测量宽恕(McCullough et al., 2013a; McCullough et al., 1998; McCullough &amp; Root, 2007; McCullough, Root, &amp; Cohen, 2006; McCullough, Worthington, &amp; Rachal, 1997)。然而被试在人机侵犯动机量表的各维度分量表上的得分具有较高的相关性(McCullough et al., 2006)，这意味着假设的三个维度无法被区分开。进一步的研究表明宽恕的各个维度可以被整合为一条敌意到友善(hostility to friendliness)的态度连续体(attitudinal continuum)，而宽恕就是被试在这一态度连续体上向友善端的变化(Forster et al., 2019)。神经影像学研究也表明，宽恕是对报复的抑制。作为情绪管理、控制冲动以及其他抑制活动的脑区，背外侧前额叶(dlPFC)，可能还包括腹外侧前额叶(vlPFC)和背侧扣带回(dACC)，参与了对前脑岛(anterior insula)和纹状体(striatum)活动的抑制作用，前脑岛与憎恶等负性情感的体验有关，纹状体和渴望回报有关，两者会在受害者遭到侵犯时被激活，即它们的活动反应了受害者的报复动机。与抑制活动相关的脑区抑制了与报复相关的脑区的活动，从而下调了负性情感的体验和对奖赏回报的渴求(Billingsley &amp; Losin, 2017)。所以来自心理测量和神经影像学的研究结果表明，宽恕和报复可以看成是同一个态度连续体上的两个极端，抑制报复就意味着宽恕。宽恕的心理机制就是通过比较关系价值和剥削风险的大小而决定在宽恕态度上的倾向性，进而使个体是宽恕还是不宽恕。</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>3. 宽恕的心理机制的实证支持</title><sec id="s7_1"><title>3.1. 剥削风险和关系价值对宽恕的影响</title><p>Burnette等(2012)为剥削风险和关系价值对宽恕的影响提供了初步的证据。在研究的第一部分，Burnette等人探索了处于恋爱关系中的大学生对其情侣的宽恕与关系价值和剥削风险的关系。首先研究人员让被试填写了关系价值和剥削风险量表(Relationship Value and Exploitation Risk Scale，包含关系价值和剥削风险两个分量表)，这些大学生需要就他们与恋爱对象的关系价值和剥削风险进行评分。接着，被试填写两个测量宽恕的量表，一个量表是和解或报复动机量表(exit/neglect/voice/loyalty scale)，另一个量表是人机侵犯动机量表的简化版(TRIM-12)。研究中两个量表都用来测量被试对其情侣的宽恕水平。对三个量表测量结果的分析表明，剥削风险和关系价值的分数之间存在负相关关系，人机侵犯动机量表的简化版的分数和关系价值的分数存在正相关，两种宽恕量表的分数都和剥削风险的分数存在负相关，而且更高的剥削风险对应着更低的宽恕水平，关系价值和剥削风险对宽恕的影响存在交互作用(Burnette et al., 2012)。为了进一步验证以上结果，研究的第二部分Burnette等人在实验中操纵关系价值和剥削风险，考察不同水平的关系价值和剥削风险对宽恕的影响。实验设置四个条件，分别是高关系价值和低剥削风险、高关系价值和高剥削风险、低关系价值和低关系风险以及低关系价值和高剥削风险。实验的结果与第一部分的研究结果一致，即剥削风险高而关系价值低时，个体倾向于宽恕，反之关系价值高而剥削风险低时个体倾向于不宽恕(Burnette et al., 2012)。</p><p>一项纵向研究采用了不同于关系价值和剥削风险量表的工具测量关系价值和剥削风险，并且考察了关系价值和剥削风险在和解行为(conciliatory behavioral)与宽恕的关系中起到的中介作用(McCullough et al., 2014)。和解行为是指侵犯者向受害者表达歉意的行为，比如口头的道歉或实物的补偿，这种行为会让侵犯者看起来值得被宽恕。被试需要回忆一个与自己关系要好的人做出的侵犯，并且对这个人的关系价值、剥削风险、做出的和解行为以及宽恕的程度进行评分。研究结果表明，随着时间的推移，被试报告的侵犯者在侵犯后的最初几天内做出和解行为的程度与报告的侵犯者的关系价值以及剥削风险都存在相关关系，并且剥削风险和关系价值部分中介了和解行为对宽恕的影响，这意味着和解行为可以通过降低剥削风险和提高关系价值来提高宽恕水平(McCullough et al., 2014)。</p><p>既然剥削风险和关系价值影响着个体的宽恕，那么如果强迫个体做出与剥削风险和关系价值不匹配的决策时，个体应当会感到不适。有研究就从这种反证的角度为进化而来的宽恕的心理机制的理论提供了证据(Luchies et al., 2019)。研究者采用了调查研究和实验研究对宽恕不匹配关系价值和剥削风险时被试的反应进行了探索。研究的结果表明，无论是在调查研究中被试对真实发生的侵犯事件的回忆，还是在实验室情境下经历了模拟的侵犯事件，当侵犯者做出很少的补偿而受害者却同意了高水平的宽恕时，后者会不太愉快，而如果他们做出的是低水平的宽恕则会比较愉快，因为较少的补偿说明了剥削风险较高，因此不应该做出高水平的宽恕；当侵犯者做出了足够的补偿而受害者却同意了低水平的宽恕时，后者会不太愉快，因为充足的补偿说明关系价值较高，低水平的宽恕可能会威胁到受害者与侵犯者的有价值的关系。上述研究结果表明，个体在做出宽恕与否的决定时，其感知到的侵犯者的关系价值和剥削风险不仅参与了个体的宽恕决策，而且还是个体做出宽恕时必不可少的参考信息。神经科学的研究也发现，宽恕涉及到与社会评价(social valuation)相关的腹内侧前额叶(vmPFC)，这一脑区参与了对未来的损失和收益的评估(Fourie, Hortensius, &amp; Decety, 2020)，正好对应着宽恕的心理机制对剥削风险和关系价值风险的评估。因此剥削风险和关系价值是宽恕决策中不可或缺的、具有决定性作用的因素。</p></sec><sec id="s7_2"><title>3.2. 为宽恕的心理机制建模</title><p>有研究者基于信号检测论和错误管理理论(error management theory)对宽恕的心理机制的内部决策过程进行了建模(Tan, Luan, Gonzalez, &amp; Jablonskis, 2018; Tan, Luan, &amp; Katsikopoulos, 2017)。因为宽恕是为了维持和侵犯者的关系，但是基于已有的经验并不能对侵犯者未来的行为进行准确的判断，因此可以将宽恕决策看成是一种信号检测，即在不确定性情境下的决策。那么正确的决策是宽恕了“盟友”或者不宽恕“仇人”，错误的决策是宽恕了“仇人”或者不宽恕“盟友”。这里的“盟友”是指将来会帮助受害者的侵犯者，“仇人”是指将来还会给受害者带来损失的侵犯者。根据信号检测理论，Tan等(2017)假设宽恕的决策有两个子过程，一个是评估证据强度，另一个是决定判断标准。证据强度是指侵犯者是否对受害者表现出亲社会性，包括了三个线索(分别为：“侵犯者是否有意伤害？”、“侵犯者是否对侵犯负有责任？”和“侵犯者是否表达了真诚的道歉？”)，而判断标准取决于宽恕决策的两类错误(宽恕“仇人”或不宽恕“盟友”)所造成损失的相对大小，其中关系价值被视为是不宽恕“盟友”造成的损失，剥削风险被视为宽恕“仇人”造成的损失，那么当关系价值大于剥削风险时，受害者会选择冒险的判断标准避免“错误–不宽恕”(即不宽恕“盟友”)，反之受害者会选择保守的判断标准避免“错误–宽恕”(即宽恕“仇人”) (见图1)。在研究中，研究人员运用富兰克林规则(Franklin’s rule)和快速–节俭决策法(fast-and-frugal trees)两种基于信号检测论的决策模型对被试在假想的侵犯事件情境下的证据强度以及判断标准进行拟合。富兰克林规则是处理离散值线索的线性模型。快速–节俭决策法是启发式决策模型，它假定个体会优先检验最重要的线索，如果线索满足一定条件，则做出决策，停止检验次优先级的线索，否则查看下一个线索是否满足一定条件，以此类推(见图2)。</p><p>图1. 用信号检测论理解宽恕决策(adapted from Tan et al., 2017)</p><p>通过上述模型所采用的实验方法，得到侵犯事件对应的证据强度、被试看待三个线索的在决策中的重要性权重以及被试的判断标准之后就可以验证被试选择的判断标准是否在避免成本较高的决策错误，还可以通过比较模型对被试宽恕决策的预测和被试真实的决策结果来检验两种决策模型的拟合准确度。实验的结果表明，如果关系价值大于剥削风险，当两种模型选定的判断标准较为冒险时可以更好地拟合被试的宽恕决策，反之如果关系价值小于剥削风险，两种模型选定的判断标准较为保守时可以更好地拟合被试的宽恕决策，而且两种模型的拟合准确度都很高。上述结果说明富兰克林规则和快速–节俭决策法都可以很好地拟合宽恕决策，而且还表明被试会通过调整判断标准来避免代价较高的决策错误。</p><p>为了更好地辨别富兰克林规则和快速–节俭决策法哪个模型可以更好地拟合宽恕决策，Tan等(2018)又在之前实验的基础上运用过程追踪工具(process-tracing tool)进行了研究。过程追踪工具可以通过记录和分析被试的反应时和信息获取模式来判断被试采取的是哪种决策过程。研究结果并不完全支持两种模型中的任何一方，反应时的结果符合快速–节俭决策法的表现，相反信息获取模式符合富兰克林规则的表现。这可能意味着，虽然宽恕的心理机制可以运用信号检测论和错误管理理论进行研究，但是这一心理机制的内部过程依然有待进一步的探索。这项考察的线索增加到了四个，相对之前的研究加入了“侵犯者是否第一次做出这样的侵犯行为”的线索，研究人员认为加入这一线索可以更好地模拟真实的宽恕决策中个体要加工的信息。这也说明将来的研究还可能在宽恕的心理机制的建模中纳入其他新的线索。</p><p>图2. 用快速–节俭决策法为宽恕建模(adapted from Tan et al., 2017)</p></sec><sec id="s7_3"><title>3.3. 宽恕的心理机制对道歉的影响</title><p>进化心理学认为心理机制作为有助于生存和繁衍的适应器(adaptation)一定普遍存在于整个人类物种之中(Buss, 2015)，因此侵犯者和受害者一样也有宽恕的心理机制，并且可以认识到自己的侵犯行为会引起受害者宽恕的心理机制的反应。如果侵犯者想要维持与受害者的关系，那么他(她)会通过相应的行为来促使受害者宽恕自己。有研究就从侵犯者的角度出发，考察了关系价值对侵犯者成本高昂的道歉的影响(Ohtsubo &amp; Yagi, 2015)。研究人员将关系价值定义为关系的工具性(instrumentality)，即某人在多大程度上提高了另一个人实现积极目标的可能性。与某一伙伴的关系的工具性，会提升一个人对这一伙伴的亲密感(Fitzsimons &amp; Shah, 2008)，为了更好地验证进化心理学的假设，研究中采用的是与适合度直接关联的关系的工具性作为自变量。通过关系的工具性量表，被试对他们现实生活中的某个朋友对他们在达成6个方面的目标(学业成绩、社团活动、求职活动、社会关系、兼职以及其他被试追求的目标)上是否有帮助或者妨碍进行打分。之后的研究结果表明，在控制了亲密感的情况下，关系的工具性对侵犯者的高昂的道歉有显著影响，关系价值越高，侵犯者越愿意向受害者做出道歉，说明侵犯者确实会为了维护有价值的关系而做出道歉(Ohtsubo &amp; Yagi, 2015)。</p><p>如果侵犯者的道歉是为了维护他和受害者的关系，那么侵犯者的道歉应该要通过提高受害者对关系价值的评价来提高受害者的宽恕水平。有研究者(Forster et al., 2018)对这一推论进行了验证，他们通过多轮囚徒困境游戏(iterated prisoner dilemma)进行实验，研究了关系价值在道歉对宽恕的影响中所起到的中介作用。在游戏开始前被试被告知他们会被随机任命为“接收者”或者“发送者”的角色，发送者可以发送文本以及任务中的收益给参与游戏的另一个人，而接收者将看到屏幕上显示的发送者发送的文本信息，事实上所有的被试都被任命为接收者。在12轮的囚徒困境博弈之后，陌生人会第一次发消息给被试，表明希望双方在接下来的每轮游戏中都选择合作，而紧接着的7轮游戏陌生人都会选择背叛，这就让被试遭到了侵犯。7轮结束之后被试会接收到三种信息中的一种，这三种信息分别作为道歉、激怒和对照条件，代表了道歉作为自变量的不同水平。之后被试在关系价值和剥削风险量表上对陌生人的关系价值和剥削风险进行评价，接着再进行10轮的囚徒困境的决策，并填写人机侵犯动机量表-陌生人版(TRIM-NCO)来测量被试对陌生人的宽恕水平。对实验数据进行后分析发现，与对照组相比接收到道歉信息的被试表现出了对陌生人更高水平的宽恕，而接收到激怒信息的被试则表现出了更低水平的宽恕，而无论是道歉或者激怒都是通过影响了被试对陌生人的关系价值和剥削风险的评价而影响了被试对陌生人的宽恕水平。因此关系价值和剥削风险确实在道歉对宽恕的影响中起到了中介作用(Forster et al., 2018)。</p><p>除了上述通过心理测量进行的研究之外，还有研究通过对人类关系区域档案(Human Relations Area Files)中来自53个文化的473个文本记录的真实的自杀行为进行研究(Syme &amp; Hagen, 2019)，文本分析的结果表明某些案例中自杀行为的功能是侵犯者向那些受到侵犯行为伤害的人做出的代价高昂的道歉，而且这种现象普遍存在于各种人类文化之中。总之进化心理学的相关研究表明，为了维护与受害者的关系，侵犯者会做出道歉使受害者更有可能宽恕自己。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s8"><title>4. 讨论与展望</title><p>长久以来，临床心理学家们将报复视为一种“疾病”，将宽恕视为对报复的“治疗”，围绕这一思想，大量的研究旨在验证宽恕使人们摆脱创伤的经历和报复的情感，从而给人的健康带来怎样的好处(McCullough et al., 2013a)。随着研究的深入，心理学家们发展出了多种理论来解释宽恕(Worthington, Rueger, Davis, &amp; Wortham, 2019)。其中，进化心理学理论没有简单地将报复看成是一种“疾病”，而认为报复和宽恕都是进化而来的心理机制，用来应对同种侵犯这一进化过程中的适应性问题，前者是受害者为了使侵犯者受到惩罚而不敢再做出伤害，后者则是受害者为了避免破坏与侵犯者的关系，期望侵犯者在将来可以给自己帮助。宽恕的心理机制在决定是否宽恕侵犯者时要加工侵犯者有关的信息，计算关系价值和剥削风险，并且在综合考虑两者之后做出宽恕与否的决策。当受害者认为关系价值高而剥削风险低时，他(她)倾向于宽恕侵犯者；当受害者认为剥削风险高而关系价值低时，他(她)更倾向于不宽恕侵犯者。无论做何选择，受害者都是为了提高自身的适合度(McCullough et al., 2013a)。自然选择过程让那些有利于生存与繁衍的心理机制留存下来，而正是因为宽恕的心理机制有利于解决同种侵犯的适应性问题，提高个体的适合度，所以才普遍存在于人类个体之中。</p><p>围绕着关系价值和剥削风险在宽恕的心理机制中起到的关键作用，研究者们进行了许多研究，同时也发现了许多有待解决的问题。一个主要问题是，现有的测量工具还不能很好地测量关系价值和剥削风险。研究者们开发了各不相同的测量工具对关系价值和剥削风险进行测量(Burnette et al., 2012; McCullough et al., 2014; Ohtsubo et al., 2018; Ohtsubo &amp; Yagi, 2015; Smith et al., 2020)，但是发现关系价值和剥削风险存在着较强的相关性，也就是说已有的测量工具无法将关系价值和剥削风险分离开来，这也可能是由于关系价值和剥削风险以某种方式相互影响而导致的。还有研究比较了三种不同的工具所测得的关系价值，均发现了它们可以显著地预测宽恕(Smith et al., 2020)，这表明关系价值的测量工具还可以进一步整合。总之将来的研究要探索更加有效的关系价值和剥削风险的测量方法，使关系价值和剥削风险的测量有统一的标准，同时还要探索关系价值和剥削风险之间的关系，理解两者如何相互作用。</p><p>比起如何测量关系价值和剥削风险这一问题，一个更重要的问题是该如何定义关系价值和剥削风险。关系价值和剥削风险在测量工具上的多样性反映了研究者们对这两个概念的理解存在差异。Tan等(2018)对宽恕的心理机制进行建模时将与侵犯行为直接相关的线索区别于受害者所感知到的关系价值和剥削风险，认为这些线索是用来评估信号检测过程中的证据强度，而把关系价值和剥削风险作为两种信号检测的决策错误的犯错代价，并假设宽恕的心理机制存在着评估证据强度和选择判断标准两个子过程，这样就把原本属于剥削风险的侵犯者的道歉和伤害意图等线索分离了出来，使得从定义上来看关系价值和剥削风险不再受到侵犯者的道歉和伤害意图的影响，然而Ohtsubo和Yagi (2015)的研究又表明道歉和侵犯者的主观意图都影响了受害者感知到的剥削风险和关系价值。因此将来在对宽恕的心理机制进行建模时还要在模型中纳入这种关系，而不是将这些线索独立于关系价值和剥削风险。对关系价值和剥削风险的定义不够明确还表现在目前的研究基本上只考察了侵犯者的伤害意图、侵犯的严重性(或者表述为侵犯者是否值得责备)、侵犯行为发生的次数以及侵犯者的道歉对关系价值和剥削风险的影响(McCullough et al., 2014; Ohtsubo et al., 2018)，但是影响关系价值和剥削风险的因素众多，还有亲缘关系、交往历史以及依恋关系(McCullough et al., 2013a)等等相对独立于侵犯的较为稳定的因素，这些因素到底如何影响关系价值和剥削风险进而影响宽恕还有待将来的研究去探索。</p><p>部分研究者认为，和剥削风险、关系价值一样，受害者与侵犯者之间的情感也对宽恕起到了作用。Ohtsubo和Yagi (2015)发现了在控制了以关系的工具性作为操作性定义的关系价值之后，亲密感也可以显著地预测成本高昂的道歉，这可能是由于亲密感提高了侵犯者向受害者进行社会交换的意愿而导致的，并且关系的工具性引发了侵犯者的愧疚感(sense of guilty)。Smith等(2020)的研究发现同情在关系的工具性对宽恕的影响中起到部分的中介作用。以上结果可能意味着受害者是否做出宽恕，侵犯者是否做出道歉，都会受到彼此之间的情感的影响。然而从进化心理学的角度来看，虽然情感看上去代表着“非理性”，与计算适合度得失的关系价值和剥削风险的“理性”相对立，但是情感本身是演化而来的心理机制所产生的，有助于远古人类解决生存和繁衍的适应性问题，而宽恕的心理机制必然要包含情感(McCullough et al., 2013a)，情感通过关系价值和剥削风险影响到了宽恕决策。因此将来的研究要探索情感到底如何影响了关系价值和剥削风险进而影响宽恕。</p><p>进化心理学关于宽恕的心理机制的理论还需要用于宽恕的神经机制的研究。现有的有关宽恕的神经机制的研究还面临着两个问题，一个是“宽恕”概念的复杂性，二是研究方法上的困难。进化心理学有关宽恕的心理机制的理论可以对解决两个问题有所帮助，因为该理论解释了宽恕是进化而来的心理机制，明确了宽恕的功能，对宽恕的心理机制的决策过程也做了阐释，因此神经科学可以采用进化心理学对宽恕的定义进行研究。在研究方法上，Billingsley和Losin (2017)认为现有研究主要采用的是实验法，研究的宽恕只发生在实验室人为匹配的单次关系(one-shot relationship)的陌生人之间，并没有考察诸如亲人、情侣、朋友之间的宽恕，而且这些范式所产生的也只是损失少量金钱这样的侵犯行为，没有涉及到现实生活中会发生的更严重的侵犯，所以将来的研究需要像已有的进化心理学关于宽恕的研究那样考察真实的人际关系中发生的、严重的侵犯行为所涉及的宽恕，还能用上关系价值和剥削风险量表等测量关系价值和剥削风险的方法，以及测量宽恕的人际侵犯动机量表。除了上面两个主要问题之外，考虑到宽恕的心理机制可以运用信号检测论和错误管理理论加以诠释，那么宽恕的心理过程可能存在着对决策后果的不确定性的感知。未来研究可以将宽恕决策可能涉及到的对不确定性的感知作为研究对象，探索前岛叶作为与不确定性的感知相关的脑区(Loued-Khenissi, Pfeuffer, Einh&#228;user, &amp; Preuschoff, 2020)在宽恕决策中的激活是否与个体感知到不确定性有关。</p><p>未来的研究还可以探索的问题包括：伴随人的发展宽恕的心理机制会发生怎样的变化；宽恕的心理机制为什么存在个体差异；怎样将进化心理学有关宽恕的理论从只涉及两人的互动关系运用到群体的互动关系当中(McCullough, Kurzban, &amp; Tabak, 2013b)。对于上述问题的回答，将有助于理解宽恕这一广泛存在于人类以及其他物种中的现象，有助于人们更科学地研究人际甚至群体间冲突的解决之道。</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>文章引用</title><p>余浩然,姚本先,张威威,潘俊星,武杨杰. 进化心理学视阈下宽恕的心理机制The Psychological Mechanism of Forgiveness in the Perspective of Evolutionary Psychology[J]. 心理学进展, 2020, 10(11): 1664-1675. https://doi.org/10.12677/AP.2020.1011194</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>参考文献</title></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Billingsley, J., &amp; Losin, E. A. R. (2017). The Neural Systems of Forgiveness: An Evolutionary Psychological Perspective. Frontiers in Psychology, 8, Article No. 737. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00737</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Burnette, J. L., McCul-lough, M. E., Van Tongeren, D. R., &amp; Davis, D. E. (2012). Forgiveness Results from Integrating Information about Rela-tionship Value and Exploitation Risk. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 38, 345-356.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1177/0146167211424582</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Buss, D. M. (2005). The Handbook of Evolutionary Psychology. Hoboken, NJ: John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Buss, D. M. (2009). The Great Struggles of Life: Darwin and the Emergence of Evolutionary Psychology. American Psychologist, 64, 140-180. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1037/a0013207</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Buss, D. M. (2015). Evolutionary Psychology: The New Science of the Mind. Hove: Psychology Press.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.4324/9781315663319</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cluttonbrock, T. H., &amp; Parker, G. A. (1995). Punishment in Animal Societies. Nature, 373, 20-216.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1038/373209a0</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">De Jong, P. J., Peters, M. L., &amp; De Cremer, D. (2003). Blushing May Signify Guilt: Revealing Effects of Blushing in Ambiguous Social Situations. Motivation and Emotion, 27, 225-249. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1023/A:1025059631708</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">De Waal, F. B. (2000). Primates—A Natural Heritage of Conflict Resolution. Science, 289, 586-590.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1126/science.289.5479.586</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">De Waal, F. B., &amp; Pokorny, J. (2005). Primate Questions about the Art and Science of Forgiving. In E. L. Worthington (Ed.), Handbook of Forgiveness (pp. 17-32). New York: Brun-ner-Routledge.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fehr, R., Gelfand, M. J., &amp; Nag, M. (2010). The Road to Forgiveness: A Meta-Analytic Synthesis of Its Situational and Dispositional Correlates. Psychological Bulletin, 136, 894-914. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1037/a0019993</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Finkel, E. J., Rusbult, C. E., Kumashiro, M., &amp; Hannon, P. A. (2002). Dealing with Betrayal in Close Relationships: Does Commitment Promote Forgiveness? Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 82, 956-974.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1037/0022-3514.82.6.956</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fitness, J., &amp; Peterson, J. (2008). Punishment and Forgiveness in Close Relationships: An Evolutionary, Social-Psychological Perspective. In J. P. Forgas, &amp; J. Fitness (Eds.), Social Rela-tionships: Cognitive, Affective, and Motivational Processes (pp. 255-269). Sydney Symposium of Social Psychology Vol. 10, New York: Psychology Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fitzsimons, G. M., &amp; Shah, J. Y. (2008). How Goal Instrumentality Shapes Rela-tionship Evaluations. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 95, 319-337. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1037/0022-3514.95.2.319</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Forster, D. E., Billingsley, J., Russell, V. M., McCauley, T. G., Smith, A., Burnette, J. L., Ohtsubo, Y., Schug, J., Lieberman, D., &amp; McCullough, M. E. (2019). Forgiveness Takes Place on an Attitudinal Con-tinuum from Hostility to Friendliness: Toward a Closer Union of Forgiveness Theory and Measurement. Journal of Per-sonality and Social Psychology, 119, 861-880. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1037/pspi0000227</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Forster, D. E., Russell, M., Billingsley, J., Burnette, J., Kurzban, R., Ohtsubo, Y., &amp; McCullough, M. E. (2018). Apologies Promote Forgiveness and Restore Cooperation by Increasing Perceived Relationship Value.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.31234/osf.io/f28ya</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fourie, M. M., Hortensius, R., &amp; Decety, J. (2020). Parsing the Compo-nents of Forgiveness: Psychological and Neural Mechanisms. Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews, 112, 437-451. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.neubiorev.2020.02.020</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Frank, R. H. (1988). Passions within Reason: The Strategic Role of the Emotions. New York: WW Norton &amp; Co.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gold, G. J., &amp; Weiner, B. (2000). Remorse, Confession, Group Identity, and Expectancies about Repeating a Transgression. Basic and Applied Social Psychology, 22, 291-300. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1207/S15324834BASP2204_3</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Henrich, J. (2009). The Evolution of Costly Displays, Coop-eration and Religion: Credibility Enhancing Displays and Their Implications for Cultural Evolution. Evolution and Human Behavior, 30, 244-260.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2009.03.005</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hruschka, D. J., &amp; Henrich, J. (2006). Friendship, Cli-quishness, and the Emergence of Cooperation. Journal of Theoretical Biology, 239, 1-15. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.jtbi.2005.07.006</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Karremans, J. C., &amp; Aarts, H. (2007). The Role of Automaticity in Determining the In-clination to Forgive Close Others. Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, 43, 902-917. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.jesp.2006.10.012</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">King-Casas, B., Sharp, C., Lomax-Bream, L., Lohrenz, T., Fonagy, P., &amp; Montague, P. R. (2008). The Rupture and Repair of Cooperation in Borderline Personality Disorder. Science, 321, 806-810. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1126/science.1156902</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Loued-Khenissi, L., Pfeuffer, A., Einhäuser, W., &amp; Preuschoff, K. (2020). Anterior Insula Reflects Surprise in Value-Based Decision-Making and Perception. Neuroimage, 210, Article ID: 116549.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.neuroimage.2020.116549</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Luchies, L. B., Finkel, E. J., Coy, A. E., Reid, C. A., Van Tongeren, D. R., Davis, J. L., &amp; Green, J. D. (2019). People Feel Worse about Their Forgiveness When Mismatches be-tween Forgiveness and Amends Create Adaptation Risks. Journal of Social and Personal Relationships, 36, 681-705. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1177/0265407517740983</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Matsumura, S., &amp; Hayden, T. J. (2006). When Should Signals of Submission Be Given? A Game Theory Model. Journal of Theoretical Biology, 240, 425-433. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.jtbi.2005.10.002</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCullough, M. E. (2008). Beyond Revenge: The Evolution of the Forgiveness Instinct. Hoboken, NJ: John Wiley &amp; Sons.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCullough, M. E., &amp; Root, L. M. (2007). Forgiveness as Change. In Handbook of Forgiveness (pp. 115-132). Abingdon-on-Thames: Routledge.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCullough, M. E., Kurzban, R., &amp; Tabak, B. A. (2013a). Cognitive Systems for Revenge and Forgiveness. Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 36, 1-15. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1017/S0140525X11002160</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCullough, M. E., Kurzban, R., &amp; Tabak, B. A. (2013b). Putting Revenge and Forgiveness in an Evolutionary Context. Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 36, 41-58. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1017/S0140525X12001513</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCullough, M. E., Luna, L. R., Berry, J. W., Tabak, B. A., &amp; Bono, G. (2010). On the Form and Function of Forgiving: Modeling the Time-Forgiveness Relationship and Testing the Valuable Relationships Hypothesis. Emotion, 10, 358-376.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1037/a0019349</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCullough, M. E., Pedersen, E. J., Tabak, B. A., &amp; Carter, E. C. (2014). Conciliatory Gestures Promote Forgiveness and Reduce Anger in Humans. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 111, 11211-11216. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1073/pnas.1405072111</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCullough, M. E., Rachal, K. C., Sandage, S. J., Worthington, E. L., Brown, S. W., &amp; Hight, T. L. (1998). Interpersonal Forgiving in Close Relationships: II. Theoretical Elaboration and Measurement. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 75, 1586-1603. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1037/0022-3514.75.6.1586</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCullough, M. E., Root, L. M., &amp; Cohen, A. D. (2006). Writing about the Benefits of an Interpersonal Transgression Facilitates Forgiveness. Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology, 74, 887-897.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1037/0022-006X.74.5.887</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCullough, M. E., Worthington, E. L., &amp; Rachal, K. C. (1997). Interpersonal Forgiving in Close Relationships. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 73, 321-336. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1037/0022-3514.73.2.321</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nadler, A., &amp; Liviatan, I. (2006). Intergroup Reconciliation: Effects of Adversary’s Expressions of Empathy, Responsibility, and Recipients’ Trust. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 32, 459-470.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1177/0146167205276431</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ohtsubo, Y., &amp; Yagi, A. (2015). Relationship Value Promotes Costly Apology-Making: Testing the Valuable Relationships Hypothesis from the Perpetrator’s Perspective. Evolution and Human Behavior, 36, 232-239.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2014.11.008</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ohtsubo, Y., Matsunaga, M., Tanaka, H., Suzuki, K., Kobayashi, F., Shibata, E., &amp; Ohira, H. (2018). Costly Apologies Communicate Conciliatory Intention: An fMRI Study on Forgiveness in Response to Costly Apologies. Evolution and Human Behavior, 39, 249-256. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2018.01.004</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Petersen, M. B., Sell, A., Tooby, J., &amp; Cosmides, L. (2012). To Punish or Repair? Evolutionary Psychology and Lay Intuitions about Modern Criminal Justice. Evolution and Human Behavior, 33, 682-695.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2012.05.003</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pinker, S. (2012). The Better Angels of Our Nature: Why Violence Has Declined. New York: Penguin Group USA.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rapoport, A., Chammah, A. M., &amp; Orwant, C. J. (1965). Prisoner’s Dilemma: A Study in Conflict and Cooperation (Vol. 165). Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.3998/mpub.20269</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Smith, A., McCauley, T. G., Yagi, A., Yamaura, K., Shimizu, H., McCul-lough, M. E., &amp; Ohtsubo, Y. (2020). Perceived Goal Instrumentality Is Associated with Forgiveness: A Test of the Valuable Relationships Hypothesis. Evolution and Human Behavior, 41, 58-68. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2019.09.003</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Syme, K. L., &amp; Hagen, E. H. (2019). When Saying “Sorry” Isn’t Enough: Is Some Suicidal Behavior a Costly Signal of Apology? Human Nature, 30, 117-141. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1007/s12110-018-9333-3</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tan, J. H., Luan, S., &amp; Katsikopoulos, K. (2017). A Signal-Detection Approach to Modeling Forgiveness Decisions. Evolution and Human Behavior, 38, 27-38. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1016/j.evolhumbehav.2016.06.004</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tan, J. H., Luan, S., Gonzalez, T., &amp; Jablonskis, E. (2018). Testing Er-ror-Management Predictions in Forgiveness Decisions with Cognitive Modeling and Process-Tracing Tools. Evolutionary Behavioral Sciences, 12, 206-217.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1037/ebs0000114</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Worthington, E. L., Rueger, S. Y., Davis, E. B., &amp; Wortham, J. (2019). “Mere” Christian Forgiveness: An Ecumenical Christian Conceptualization of Forgiveness through the Lens of Stress-and-Coping Theory. Religions, 10, 44.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.3390/rel10010044</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.38715-ref46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wu, J., &amp; Axelrod, R. (1995). How to Cope with Noise in the Iterated Prisoner’s Dilemma. Journal of Conflict Resolution, 39, 183-189. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org /10.1177/0022002795039001008</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>