<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" article-type="research article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Advances in Psychology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2160-7273</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Scientific Research Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12677/AP.2021.111005</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AP-39786</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>AP20210100000_62309961.pdf</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>人文社科</subject><subject> 合作期刊</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
 
 
  情绪识别中群内优势效应研究的回顾与展望
  The Review and Prospect of In-Group Advantage Effect in Emotion Recognition
 
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>杨</surname><given-names>宏</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sub>1</sub></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>*</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>内蒙古师范大学心理学院，内蒙古 呼和浩特</addr-line></aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>01</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>01</issue><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>47</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Copyright  2014 by authors and Scientific Research Publishing Inc. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY). http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
 
 
   
   情绪识别中的群内优势效应是指人们在判断与自己具有相同文化背景人物的情绪时，其识别情绪的准确性要高于判断与自己文化背景不同人物的情绪的准确性。通过对群内优势效应的相关文献进行梳理，从面部情绪识别、声音情绪识别、躯体情绪识别以及相关的理论解释进行分析，发现该研究领域存在发展性研究匮乏、被试和实验材料的异质性以及操作困难等问题，进而提出情绪识别中群内优势效应研究的展望，进一步完善群内优势效应的发展性研究，提高跨文化情绪交流的效果并制定促进跨文化情绪交流的干预方案。 The in-group advantage effect in emotion recognition means that when people judge the emotions of people with the same cultural background as themselves, the accuracy of identifying emotions is higher than that of people with different cultural backgrounds. Based on the literature review of in-group advantage effect and the analysis of facial emotion recognition, voice emotion recognition, body emotion recognition and related theoretical explanations, it is found that there are some problems in this research field, such as the lack of developmental research, the heterogeneity of subjects and experimental materials, and the operational difficulties. Furthermore, this paper puts forward the prospect of the research on in-group advantage effect in emotion recognition, further improves the developmental research of in-group advantage effect, improves the effect of cross-cultural emotional communication, and formulates intervention programs to promote cross-cultural emotional communication. 
  
 
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>情绪识别，群内优势效应，文化差异，方言理论, Emotion Recognition</kwd><kwd> In-Group Advantage Effect</kwd><kwd> Cultural Difference</kwd><kwd> The Dialect Theory</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>摘要</title><p>情绪识别中的群内优势效应是指人们在判断与自己具有相同文化背景人物的情绪时，其识别情绪的准确性要高于判断与自己文化背景不同人物的情绪的准确性。通过对群内优势效应的相关文献进行梳理，从面部情绪识别、声音情绪识别、躯体情绪识别以及相关的理论解释进行分析，发现该研究领域存在发展性研究匮乏、被试和实验材料的异质性以及操作困难等问题，进而提出情绪识别中群内优势效应研究的展望，进一步完善群内优势效应的发展性研究，提高跨文化情绪交流的效果并制定促进跨文化情绪交流的干预方案。</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>关键词</title><p>情绪识别，群内优势效应，文化差异，方言理论</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>The Review and Prospect of In-Group Advantage Effect in Emotion Recognition<sup> </sup></title><p>Hong Yang</p><p>School of Psychology, Inner Mongolia Normal University, Hohhot Inner Mongolia</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/5-1132106x4_hanspub.png" /></p><p>Received: Dec. 3<sup>rd</sup>, 2020; accepted: Jan. 6<sup>th</sup>, 2021; published: Jan. 15<sup>th</sup>, 2021</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/5-1132106x5_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>The in-group advantage effect in emotion recognition means that when people judge the emotions of people with the same cultural background as themselves, the accuracy of identifying emotions is higher than that of people with different cultural backgrounds. Based on the literature review of in-group advantage effect and the analysis of facial emotion recognition, voice emotion recognition, body emotion recognition and related theoretical explanations, it is found that there are some problems in this research field, such as the lack of developmental research, the heterogeneity of subjects and experimental materials, and the operational difficulties. Furthermore, this paper puts forward the prospect of the research on in-group advantage effect in emotion recognition, further improves the developmental research of in-group advantage effect, improves the effect of cross-cultural emotional communication, and formulates intervention programs to promote cross-cultural emotional communication.</p><p>Keywords:Emotion Recognition, In-Group Advantage Effect, Cultural Difference, The Dialect Theory</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.39786-formula13"><graphic xlink:href="//html.hanspub.org/file/5-1132106x6_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><p>Copyright &#169; 2021 by author(s) and Hans Publishers Inc.</p><p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/5-1132106x7_hanspub.png" /> <img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/5-1132106x8_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>1. 引言</title><p>情绪识别是指从他人的面部表情、言语声调以及肢体动作中推断出情绪信息的能力，它不仅是一种重要的心理能力，也是个体进行社会交往的必要前提(彭聃龄，2004)。达尔文在《人类和动物的表情》一书中曾提出：人的表情是天生的、普遍的，人们能够识别来自不同文化或种族的人的情绪和表情(Darwin, 1872)。大量研究也证实了达尔文的观点，得出情绪识别具有普遍性的结论(Ekman, 1972; Izard, 1971; Matsumoto, 1992; Matsumoto &amp; Assar, 1992; Romney, Moore, &amp; Rusch, 1997)，如Elfenbein和Ambady (2002a, 2002b, 2003a, 2003b)发现不同文化的人们具有由面部表情、语言和肢体等组成的普遍情感系统(universal affect program)。但随着相关研究的不断深入，有研究者认为情绪的表达和识别是后天习得的，具有文化差异性(Biehl, Matsumoto, Ekman, Hearn, Heider, Kudoh, &amp; Ton, 1997; Brooks, 1994; Elfenbein &amp; Ambady, 2002b; Masuda, Ellsworth, Mesquita, Leu, Tanida, &amp; Veerdonk, 2008; Russell, 1994)。</p><p>近年来，越来越多的研究者倾向于认同情绪识别的跨文化普遍性与差异性共存的整合观点(Elfenbein &amp; Ambady, 2002a, 2002b; Mesquita &amp; Frijda, 1992; Mesquita, Frijda, &amp; Scherer, 1997; Scherer &amp; Walbott, 1994)，并提出群内优势效应(in-group advantage)，即人们在判断与自己具有相同文化背景人物的情绪时，其准确性高于判断与自己文化背景不同人物的情绪的准确性。群内优势效应的提出更好地阐释了不同文化背景下人们在识别情绪时所表现出来的相似性和差异性。为此，本文对近年来情绪识别中的群内优势效应的相关研究进行梳理，并对未来该领域的研究进行展望。</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>2. 情绪识别群内优势效应的现状研究</title><p>传统的情绪理论认为，面孔是情绪表达与交流的主要载体，面部表情在情绪识别中起主导作用，因此情绪识别的相关研究大多集中在面部情绪的表达、识别及其神经机制等方面，对声音、躯体等其他情绪载体的研究相对较少(de Gelder, 2009; Hassin, Aviezer, &amp; Bentin, 2013; Zieber, Kangas, Hock, &amp; Bhatt, 2014)。然而，对声音、躯体等其他情绪载体进行研究会突破只依赖于面部情绪研究的传统局面，极大地提高情绪加工研究领域的现实意义(方平，李洋，姜媛，2009；de Gelder, 2009)。</p><sec id="s6_1"><title>2.1. 面部情绪识别中的群内优势效应</title><p>面部表情是个体获得社会信息并做出恰当反应的最重要来源，面部情绪识别是情绪识别中的核心领域(徐胜三，鲁朝权，张福建，1990；Zhang, Wang, &amp; Lou, 2012)。1971年，Izard虽然发现了美国人、欧洲人、日本人和非洲人识别面部表情图片的正确率都大于随机水平，却忽视了东、西方文化背景下被试识别面部表情图片正确率具有差异性的现象。随后，Elfenbein和Ambady (2002b)对87篇情绪跨文化识别的相关文献进行元分析，结果发现情绪跨文化识别中存在一种群内优势效应，即当情绪表达者与情绪识别者来自相同文化时，他们之间的情绪理解与交流更为准确。群内优势效应的提出引起了心理学家的广泛关注，许多研究者从不同的角度验证其存在。Beaupr&#233;和Hess (2006)发现非裔、华裔和法裔的加拿大人判断同种文化背景的面部情绪图片所表现出来的自信程度要显著大于判断其他文化背景的面部情绪图片所表现的自信，这在一定程度上支持了群内优势效应。Wickline，Bailey和Nowicki (2009)要求非裔美国学生、欧洲裔美国学生、非洲留学生和欧洲留学生通过面部表情判断非裔美国人和欧裔美国人的面部情绪，结果发现非洲留学生的识别正确率最低，欧洲裔美国学生的识别正确率最高。相似地，Sharma，Sharma和Naz (2017)要求尼日利亚人、印度人和中国人识别这三个文化群体的面部情绪，结果发现，尼日利亚人和印度人识别具有相同文化背景的面部情绪的准确率更高，但有趣地是中国被试未能体现该优势，研究者们认为可能由于中国扁平的面部结构使得面部表情表现不佳，进而无法进行正确识别。</p><p>此外，大量研究者考察了面部情绪群内优势效应的神经生理机制。研究发现，人们在识别本族和其他种族人的面部表情时会产生不同的脑区活动。当被试识别与自己相同种族人的面部表情时会激活大脑中的杏仁核和梭状回等部位；当被试识别其他种族人的面部表情时激活了大脑的额叶、枕叶和顶叶区域(Kim, Yoon, Kim, Jeun, Jung, &amp; Choe, 2006; Lee et al., 2008; Van Bavel, Packer, &amp; Cunningham, 2008)。Lidaka，Nogawa，Kansaku和Sadato (2008)进一步研究了日本人在识别本族人和非本族人的快乐和中性面部情绪时的大脑活动特点，结果发现，相较于判断非本族人的快乐情绪，被试在判断本族人的快乐情绪时后扣带皮层会产生更大的激活，在判断与本族相似的面部情绪时会激活后扣带皮层和颞上回，而左侧杏仁核会在被试判断不同种族的情绪时产生不同的活动。</p></sec><sec id="s6_2"><title>2.2. 声音情绪识别的群内优势效应</title><p>声音情绪识别的群内优势效应研究也引发了很多研究者的兴趣。Albas，McCluskey和Albas (1976)发现印第安人和白人在识别自己文化下的方言语言情绪的正确率更高。相似地，Pell，Monetta，Paulmann和Kotz (2009)发现阿根廷西班牙被试识别本族语言的准确度更高，而识别本国其他与之相似度极低的语言情绪时具有较低的正确率。此外，Wickline，Bailey和Nowicki (2009)要求非裔美国学生、欧洲裔美国学生、非洲留学生和欧洲留学生四组被试通过声音来判断非裔美国人和欧裔美国人的面部情绪，结果与面部情绪识别的群内优势效应一致，非洲留学生的识别正确率最低，欧洲裔美国人的识别正确率最高。对于声音情绪识别中出现群内优势效应，有研究者认为可能是本土文化下声音情绪的表达与解读习惯对非本土文化的声音情绪加工产生了影响，进而导致识别本土文化下声音情绪的正确率要显著高于识别非本土文化下声音情绪的正确率(Elfenbein, Beaupr&#233;, Levesque, &amp; Hess, 2007; Mesquita &amp; Frijda, 1992; Pell &amp; Skorup, 2008; Scherer, Banse, &amp; Wallbott, 2001)。</p></sec><sec id="s6_3"><title>2.3. 躯体情绪识别的群内优势效应</title><p>情绪躯体语言(emotional body language)是躯体表现出的情绪信息、协调一致的运动以及有意义行为的统称，也称为躯体表情或姿态表情(de Gelder, 2006)。在远距离的情绪表达中，躯体线索表达和传递的情绪信息更为丰富(Aviezer, Trope, &amp; Todorov, 2012; de Borst &amp; de Gelder, 2016; Martinez, Falvello, Aviezer, &amp; Todorov, 2016)。情绪识别中的群内优势效应在以面部情绪和声音情绪为材料的研究中得到了广泛证实，同样，躯体情绪的群内优势效应也积累了一定的证据(Tuminello &amp; Davidson, 2011)。Roberts和Levenson (2006)要求非裔美国人、华裔美国人、欧洲裔美国人和墨西哥裔美国人观看愉快、悲伤和厌恶的电影片段后报告情绪体验并测量他们的面部情绪表情和生理反应，结果发现，当被试与影片中的演员来自相同的种族时会表现出更强烈的情绪体验、面部情绪以及生理激活。Gray，Mendes和Brown (2008)用录像记录了白人被试和黑人被试在与同种族和不同种族人交往时的表现，要求白人观察者和黑人观察者观看录像并报告录像中被试的焦虑程度，结果发现，只有同种族的观察者能够发现并准确地描述被试的焦虑情绪及其变化过程。此外，de Gelder和Huis in’t Veld (2016)的研究发现，中国被试和荷兰被试对不同情景中的躯体表情识别存在差异，当躯体表情刺激出现在非社会情景中时，中国被试识别躯体情绪的正确率好于荷兰被试。这可能因为中国被试会更容易受到集体主义文化的影响，更加关注情景及他人信息。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s7"><title>3. 情绪识别的群内优势效应的解释</title><p>大多数解释情绪识别中群内优势效应的理论都集中在面部情绪识别的文化差异上，但也有人提出过相关模型来解释声音情绪识别中的群内优势效应。群内优势效应的理论主要集中在情绪表达者和识别者的特性上。Ekman (1972)提出了神经文化理论(neurocultural theory)，认为人们具有一个普遍的、先天的“面部情绪系统”(facial affect program)，使得人们在不同文化背景下识别到的情绪与表达的情绪具有一致性。另一方面，Matsumoto (1989)认为，在不同文化中已知的“解码规则”(decoding rules)会因权利、距离、个人主义等社会因素而有所不同。Elfenbein和Ambady (2003b)考虑到了上述理论在解释群内优势效应时存在一些不足，认真研究了情绪表达者和情绪识别者的文化背景的匹配与互动过程，将语言学中的方言现象与早期的神经文化理论融合在一起并提出了“方言理论”(the dialect theory)，即情绪的普遍“语言”是用不同的方言表达的，人们对特定方言的熟悉程度决定了识别出来的速度和正确率。</p><p>Elfenbein和Ambady (2003b)认同Ekman (1972)提出的关于人类具有先天情绪系统的观点，并将其称为普遍情感系统，但Elfenbein和Ambady (2003b)认为人们在识别和表达情绪时也存在一个独特情感系统(specific affect program)，两个系统都会影响个体对不同文化人的情绪识别过程。普遍情感系统就像是一种语言系统，在这个系统中不同文化的群体可以相互识别，具有普遍性；而独特情感系统更像是一种方言，独立地执行相应的功能，受文化、教育等后天环境因素的影响，不同文化的群体以其独特的方式来表达情绪。与神经文化理论相比，方言理论认为情绪识别的文化差异来源有独特情感系统和解码规则，而神经文化理论认为情绪识别的差异仅由解码规则引起，忽视了不同文化个体对情绪理解具有差异性，所以方言理论更具解释力。随后，Elfenbein等人(2007)通过实验对方言理论进行了验证，要求加拿大魁北克和非洲加蓬的被试表现出相同的面部表情并拍照，然后将被试的面部表情图片分解成多个“面部动作单位”进行量化分析。根据方言理论的观点，不同文化的被试同种情绪的面部表情有差异，研究结果发现，两组被试的快乐、生气、悲伤、惊讶等情绪在面部表情特点上存在显著差异，为方言理论提供了有力的实证支持。</p></sec><sec id="s8"><title>4. 现阶段相关研究存在的问题</title><p>虽然现阶段学者从多个视角对情绪识别中群内优势效应进行了大量研究，并取得了有价值的研究成果。但迄今为止，群内优势效应研究中还存在一些困难和不足，对这些困难的突破与解决有望给情绪识别中群内优势效应的研究和干预提供思路及建议。</p><sec id="s8_1"><title>4.1. 发展性研究不足</title><p>不论是行为研究还是神经机制方面的研究，都存在一个很重要的问题，就是发展性研究匮乏。目前大多数研究主要是针对情绪识别的横断研究，欠缺纵向追踪的研究，无法获知人类随着年龄增长而带来的情绪识别特征的变化轨迹，以及不同文化或种族对同一种情绪的识别是否呈现不同发展趋势等相关问题，所以对人们各个年龄段的发展性研究还是有必要的。Brosgole和Weisman (1995)对情绪识别能力的横向评估表明，面部和声音情绪的识别可能在45岁开始下降。Paulmann，Pell和Kotz (2008)发现中年人(38~50岁)在声音情绪识别方面的正确率显著高于年轻人(18~28岁)。此外，McCluskey和Albas (1981)的研究发现，5~65岁的墨西哥和加拿大被试识别愉快、悲伤、爱和愤怒声音情绪的能力随着年龄的增长而增加。由此总结，在情绪的跨文化识别中，随着年龄的上升，对情绪识别的正确率是直线上升还是在一定阶段会平缓或是下降趋势这一问题是不明确的，需要进一步的研究。</p></sec><sec id="s8_2"><title>4.2. 被试的选取和实验材料的异质性</title><p>首先，文化和种族是复杂的、具有巨大异质性的群体，不同文化和种族的内部群体在情绪识别上会表现出很大差异，如何选取、选取哪些群体作为实验被试都是研究者在研究实践中需要仔细斟酌的。其次，部分研究者未选取经过严格取样、科学筛选并具有良好信效度的标准情绪材料进行实验，而选择自制实验材料，但往往难以把握自制实验材料的标准化和信效度等问题，这在一定程度上会影响了实验结果的真实性与科学性。再次，研究者选用基本或复杂的情绪材料也会影响实验结果。如愉快、悲伤等基本面部情绪和声音情绪较易识别，而尴尬、羞愧、爱等复杂的面部情绪和声音情绪难以诱发被试的情绪，从而影响实验结果的科学性与准确性。正是因为多种因素造成了群内优势效应研究具有较低的信效度，使得不同研究成果之间的参照性降低，导致对不同文化和种族的个体对情绪识别的能力争议较大，如在面部情绪识别中有研究指出亚洲人对面部情绪的识别存在困难，但也有研究表面亚洲人对面部情绪的识别与其他文化或种族没有差异。也有研究发现年轻人更倾向于观察上半张脸来识别愤怒情绪，而老年人更倾向于通过下半张脸来识别厌恶情绪(Calder, Young, Kean, &amp; Dean, 2000)。</p></sec><sec id="s8_3"><title>4.3. 实证研究可操作性困难</title><p>从研究设计来看，以往研究主要有平衡设计、非平衡设计和反非平衡设计，其中平衡设计是指制作各文化下所有参与实验的被试的情绪材料，然后全部呈现给所有被试识别(Albas et al., 1976; Kramer, 1964; McCluskey, Albas, Niemi, Cuevas, &amp; Ferrer, 1975; Paulmann &amp; Uskul, 2013; Sauter, Eisner, Ekman, &amp; Scott, 2010; Tracy &amp; Robins, 2008)；非平衡设计是指采用单一文化背景下的情绪材料呈现给多种文化背景下的被试(Beier &amp; Zautra, 1972; J&#252;rgens, Drolet, Pirow, Scheiner, &amp; Fischer, 2013; Scherer et al., 2001)；反非平衡设计是指采用多种文化下的情绪材料呈现给一种文化下的被试识别(Laukka et al., 2013; Pell, Paulmann, Dara, Alasseri, &amp; Kotz, 2009; Thompson &amp; Balkwill, 2006)。每个研究设计各有利弊，需要考虑被试的负荷量以及研究的局限性。此外，实验材料的处理更是体现了对情绪识别研究过程中额外因素的控制。情绪材料不加改动时，是最原始和真实的表现，因此让被试去识别时所得到的也是真实的记录，但又避免不了会怀疑被试是否依据其他额外线索而发生猜测。但若是改动了情绪材料，也许会有效地控制额外变量，消除被试对额外变量的特别猜测和顾忌，却又会考虑其真实性。如自发的非语言发生，被试进行情绪识别时更多地侧重生物特征而忽略文化作用。可见，情绪材料的选择对研究目的和结论起到不可小觑的影响。因此，情绪的跨文化识别研究中的实验设计和材料制作将成为未来完善实验研究的重点。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s9"><title>5. 情绪识别的群内优势效应研究的展望</title><p>分析情绪识别群内优势效应的相关研究，可见，情绪识别的群内优势效应研究目前尚无完整的定论。由于受文化差异性、被试广泛性以及实验材料难易性等因素的影响，国内外研究者还没有得出完整而确切的结论。此外，基础性研究理应服务于教育干预实践。因此，情绪识别的群内优势效应有待进一步深入。</p><sec id="s9_1"><title>5.1. 进一步完善情绪识别群内优势效应的发展研究</title><p>通过研究发现，情绪识别中的群内优势效应是不同文化或种族之间情绪交流障碍的一种表现形式，因此进一步探讨情绪识别中的群内优势效应与跨文化交流之间的关系显得尤为重要。跨文化交流存在障碍是否由某种具体情绪加工或情绪识别不足而导致？情绪识别的群内优势效应是否能对跨文化情绪交流障碍进行干预并提出借鉴？这已经引起研究者的高度重视。但目前还有几个问题值得进一步讨论：首先，确保实验材料的有效性。影响情绪识别群内优势效应的因素是多方面的，但大多数研究选取的是图片、声音、视频等，这些实验材料能否诱发真实的情绪？其研究成果能否精确地预测个体在真实情境中的表现？为了避免受到实验材料的干扰，今后研究应着眼于真实的社交情境中探究跨文化群体进行情绪识别的特点。其次，群内优势效应的研究方法有待进一步完善。正如Matsumoto (2002)所指出的，为了提高情绪跨文化识别研究的信效度，未来的研究应该创造和使用方法上合理的情绪刺激材料，如使用等价的情绪刺激、平衡设计以及纵向追踪的研究设计等。对“群内”的界定不仅要考虑情绪识别者与情绪表达者在文化或种族上的匹配，也要包含个体的社会心理特点(Tajfel, 1982)。最后，多种研究技术的融合。多学科交叉研究是情绪跨文化识别研究发展的必然趋势，特别是行为学和认知神经科学的结合。行为研究能描述个体进行情绪跨文化识别的特点，认知神经科学研究能阐述个体进行情绪跨文化识别的神经生理机制问题。只有多学科结合、多技术融合，才能更全面地探究情绪识别群内优势效应的特征和产生原因。</p></sec><sec id="s9_2"><title>5.2. 建构以情绪跨文化识别为主的标准化干预方案</title><p>虽然关于情绪识别群内优势效应已经取得了很多基础性研究成果，但如何消除群内优势效应，提高跨文化情绪交流效果的教育干预措施却很欠缺。研究人员对情绪跨文化识别的教育干预既要基于自身的经验，也要基于心理学和神经科学的研究成果。研究表明，中年人对声音情绪识别的正确率要好于年轻人(Paulmann, Pell, &amp; Kotz, 2008; McCluskey &amp; Albas, 1981)，因此在教育干预中，对年轻人进行跨文化情绪交流训练的效果要好于中年人。此外，干预的主要目的是提高个体进行情绪跨文化识别的准确率，促进跨文化交流效果。传统的干预训练通常是在特定的教育场所进行，人际交往范围狭窄可能在一定程度上会限制训练效果的发挥。因此，个体可多参加跨文化类的团体活动，自发性地进行交友、沟通，有助于其在日常生活中将学到的社会技能泛化。在我国，情绪跨文化识别的干预研究仍处于起步阶段，鉴于其对跨文化交流领域的深远影响，在未来研究中，需要基于我国文化背景和社会现状，结合质性研究与量化分析，着力构建符合我国情绪跨文化识别的标准化方案，促进情绪跨文化识别的早期干预与教学实践进展。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s10"><title>基金项目</title><p>本研究得到2019年度内蒙古师范大学研究生科研创新基金资助项目(CXJJS19011)的资助。</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>文章引用</title><p>杨 宏. 情绪识别中群内优势效应研究的回顾与展望The Review and Prospect of In-Group Advantage Effect in Emotion Recognition[J]. 心理学进展, 2021, 11(01): 39-47. https://doi.org/10.12677/AP.2021.111005</p></sec><sec id="s12"><title>参考文献</title></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">方平, 李洋, 姜媛(2009). 情绪躯体语言研究进展. 心理科学, 32(5), 1155-1158.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">彭聃龄(2004). 心理学(pp. 352-353). 北京: 北京师范大学出版社.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">徐胜三, 权朝鲁, 张福建(1990). 关于儿童表情认知发展水平的研究. 心理发展与教育, (1), 24-27.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Albas, D. C., McCluskey, K. W., &amp; Albas, C. A. (1976). Perception of the Emotional Content of Speech: A Comparison of Two Canadian Groups. Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology, 7, 481-489. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/002202217674009</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Aviezer, H., Trope, Y., &amp; Todorov, A. (2012). Body Cues, Not Facial Expressions, Discriminate between Intense Positive and Negative Emotions. Science, 338, 1225-1229. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1224313</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Beaupré, M. G., &amp; Hess, U. (2006). An In-Group Advantage for Confidence in Emotion Recognition Judgments: The Moderating Effect of Familiarity with the Expression of Out Group Members. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 32, 16-26. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167205277097</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Beier, E., &amp; Zautra, A. J. (1972). Identification of Vocal Communication of Emotion across Cultures. Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology, 39, 166-188. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/h0033170</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Biehl, M., Matsumoto, D., Ekman, P., Hearn, V., Heider, K., Kudoh, T., &amp; Ton, V. (1997). Matsumoto and Ekman’s Japanese and Caucasian Facial Expressions of Emotion (JACFEE): Reliability Data and Cross-National Differences. Journal of Nonverbal Behavior, 21, 3-21. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1024902500935</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Brooks, C. (1994). The Sounds of Silence. English Journal, 83, 84-86. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.2307/820559</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Brosgole, L., &amp; Weisman, J. (1995). Mood Recognition across the Ages. International Journal of Neuroscience, 82, 169-189.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.3109/00207459508999800</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Calder, A. J., Young, A. W., Keane, J., &amp; Dean, M. (2000). Configural Information in Facial Expression Perception. Journal of Experimental Psychology: Human Perception and Performance, 26, 527-551.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0096-1523.26.2.527</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Darwin, C. (1872). The Expression of Emotion in Man and Animals. London: Murray. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/10001-000</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">de Borst, A. W., &amp; de Gelder, B. (2016). Clear Signals or Mixed Messages: Inter-Individual Emotion Congruency Modulates Brain Activity Underlying Affective Body Perception. Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience, 11, 1299-1309.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/scan/nsw039</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">de Gelder, B. (2006). Towards the Neurobiology of Emotional Body Language. Nature Review Neuroscience, 7, 242-249.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1038/nrn1872</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">de Gelder, B. (2009). Why Bodies? Twelve Reasons for Including Bodily Expressions in Affective Neuroscience. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London, 364, 3475-3484. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2009.0190</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">de Gelder, B., &amp; Huis in‘t Veld, E. M. J. (2016). Cultural Differences in Emotional Expressions and Body Language (pp. 223-234). Oxford: Oxford University Press. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199357376.013.16</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ekman, P. (1972). Universals and Cultural Differences in Facial Expressions of Emotion. Nebraska Symposium on Motivation, 19, 207-283.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Elfenbein, H. A., &amp; Ambady, N. (2002a). Is There an In-Group Advantage in Emotion Recognition? Psychological Bulletin, 128, 243-249. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.128.2.243</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Elfenbein, H. A., &amp; Ambady, N. (2002b). On the Universality and Cultural Specificity of Emotion Recognition: A Meta-Analysis. Psychological Bulletin, 128, 203-235. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.128.2.203</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Elfenbein, H. A., &amp; Ambady, N. (2003a). When Familiarity Breeds Accuracy: Cultural Exposure and Facial Recognition. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 85, 276-290. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.85.2.276</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Elfenbein, H. A., &amp; Ambady, N. (2003b). Universals and Cultural Differences in Recognizing Emotions (pp.159-164). New York: Spearson Education. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-8721.01252</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Elfenbein, H. A., Beaupré, M., Lévesque, M., &amp; Hess, U. (2007). Toward a Dialect Theory: Cultural Differences in the Expression and Recognition of Posed Facial Expressions. Emotion, 7, 131-146. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/1528-3542.7.1.131</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gray, H. M., Mendes, W. B., &amp; Brown, C. D. (2008). An In-Group Advantage in Detecting Intergroup Anxiety. Psychological Science, 1, 1233. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.2008.02230.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hassin, R. R., Aviezer, H., &amp; Bentin, S. (2013). Inherently Ambiguous: Facial Expressions of Emotions, in Context. Emotion Review, 5, 60-65. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/1754073912451331</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Izard, C. E. (1971). The Face of Emotion. New York: Apple-ton-Century-Crofts.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Jürgens, R., Drolet, M., Pirow, R., Scheiner, E., &amp; Fischer, J. (2013). Encoding Conditions Affect Recognition of Vocally Expressed Emotions across Cultures. Frontiers in Psychology, 4, 111. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2013.00111</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kim, J. S., Yoon, H. W., Kim, B. S., Jeun, S. S., Jung, S. L., &amp; Choe, B. Y. (2006). Racial Distinction of the Unknown Facial Identity Recognition Mechanism by Event-Related fMRI. Neuroscience Letters, 397, 279-284.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neulet.2005.12.061</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kramer, E. (1964). Elimination of Verbal Cues in Judgments of Emotion from Voice. The Journal of Abnormal and Social Psychology, 68, 390-396. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/h0042473</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Laukka, P., Elfenbein, H. A., Söder, N., Nordström, H., Althoff, J., Chui, W., &amp; Thingujam, N. S. (2013). Cross-Cultural Decoding of Positive and Negative Non-Linguistic Emotion Vocalizations. Frontiers in Psychology, 4, 353.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2013.00353</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lee, K. U., Khang, H. S., Kim, K. T., Kim, Y. J., Kweon, Y. S., Shin, Y. W. et al. (2008). Distinct Processing of Facial Emotion of Own-Race versus Other-Race. Neuro Report: For Rapid Communication of Neuroscience Research, 19, 1021-1025. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/WNR.0b013e3283052df2</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lidaka, T., Nogawa, J., Kansaku, K., &amp; Sadato, N. (2008). Neural Correlates Involved in Processing Happy Affect on Same-Race Face. Journal of Psychophysiology, 22, 91-99. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1027/0269-8803.22.2.91</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Martinez, L., Falvello, V. B., Aviezer, H., &amp; Todorov, A. (2016). Contributions of Facial Expressions and Body Language to the Rapid Perception of Dynamic Emotions. Cognition and Emotion, 30, 939-952.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/02699931.2015.1035229</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Masuda, T., Ellsworth, P. C., Mesquita, B., Leu, J., Tanida, S., &amp; Veerdonk, E. V. (2008). Placing the Face in Context: Cultural Differences in the Perception of Facial Emotion. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 94, 365-381.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.94.3.365</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Matsumoto, D. (1989). Cultural Influences on the Perception of Emotion. Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology, 20, 92-105.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/0022022189201006</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Matsumoto, D. (1992). American-Japanese Cultural Differences in the Recognition of Universal Facial Expressions. Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology, 23, 72-84. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/0022022192231005</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Matsumoto, D. (2002). Methodological Requirements to Test a Possible in Group Advantage in Judging Emotions across Cultures: Comments on Elfenbein and Ambady and Evidence. Psychological Bulletin, 128, 236-242.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.128.2.236</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Matsumoto, D., &amp; Assar, M. (1992). The Effects of Language on Judgments of Universal Facial Expressions of Emotion. Journal of Nonverbal Behavior, 16, 85-99. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00990324</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCluskey, K. W., &amp; Albas, D. C. (1981). Perception of the Emotional Content of Speech by Canadian and Mexican Children, Adolescents, and Adults. International Journal of Psychology, 16, 119-132.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/00207598108247409</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McCluskey, K. W., Albas, D. C., Niemi, R. R., Cuevas, C., &amp; Ferrer, C. A. (1975). Cross-Cultural Differences in the Perception of the Emotional Content of Speech: A Study of the Development of Sensitivity in Canadian and Mexican Children. Developmental Psychology, 11, 551-555. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0012-1649.11.5.551</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mesquita, B., &amp; Frijda, N. H. (1992). Cultural Variations in Emotions: A Review. Psychological Bulletin, 112, 179-204.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.112.2.179</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mesquita, B., Frijda, N. H., &amp; Scherer, K. R. (1997). Culture and Emotion (pp. 255-297). Boston, MA: Allyn &amp; Bacon.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Paulmann, S., &amp; Uskul, A. K. (2013). Cross-Cultural Emotional Prosody Recognition: Evidence from Chinese and British Listeners. Cognition &amp; Emotion, 28, 230-244. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/02699931.2013.812033</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Paulmann, S., Pell, M. D., &amp; Kotz, S. A. (2008). How Aging Affects the Recognition of Emotional Speech. Brain and Language, 104, 262-269. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bandl.2007.03.002</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pell, M. D., &amp; Skorup, V. (2008). Implicit Processing of Emotional Prosody in a Foreign versus Native Language. Speech Communication, 50, 519-530. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.specom.2008.03.006</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pell, M. D., Monetta, L., Paulmann, S., &amp; Kotz, S. A. (2009). Recognizing Emotions in a Foreign Language. Journal of Nonverbal Behavior, 33, 107-120. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10919-008-0065-7</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pell, M. D., Paulmann, S., Dara, C., Alasseri, A., &amp; Kotz, S. A. (2009). Factors in the Recognition of Vocally Expressed Emotions: A Comparison of Four Languages. Journal of Phonetics, 37, 417-435.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wocn.2009.07.005</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Roberts, N. A., &amp; Levenson, R. W. (2006). Subjective, Behavioral, and Physiological Reactivity to Ethnically Matched and Ethnically Mismatched Film Clips. Emotion, 6, 635-646. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/1528-3542.6.4.635</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Romney, A. K., Moore, C. C., &amp; Rusch, C. D. (1997). Cultural Universals: Measuring the Semantic Structure of Emotion Terms in English and Japanese. Proceedings from the National Academy of Sciences, 94, 5489-5494.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.94.10.5489</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Russell, J. A. (1994). Is There Universal Recognition of Emotion from Facial Expressions? A Review of the Cross-Cultural Studies. Psychological Bulletin, 115, 102-141. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.115.1.102</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sauter, D. A., Eisner, F., Ekman, P., &amp; Scott, S. K. (2010). Cross-Cultural Recognition of Basic Emotions through Nonverbal Emotional Vocalizations. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 107, 2408-2412. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0908239106</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Scherer, K. R., &amp; Walbott, H. G. (1994). Evidence for Universality and Cultural Variation of Differential Emotion Response Patterning. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 66, 310-328. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.66.2.310</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Scherer, K. R., Banse, R., &amp; Wallbott, H. G. (2001). Emotion Inferences from Vocal Expression Correlate across Languages and Cultures. Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology, 32, 76-92. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/0022022101032001009</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sharma, K., Sharma, H., &amp; Naz, S. (2017). In-Group Advantage in Recognition of Facial Emotional Expressions in Cross-Cultural Societies. International Journal of Economic Research, 14, 715-726.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tajfel, H. (1982). Social Psychology of Intergroup Relations. Annual Review of Psychology, 33, 1-39.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.ps.33.020182.000245</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Thompson, W. F., &amp; Balkwill, L. L. (2006). Decoding Speech Prosody in Five Languages. Semiotica, 2006, 407-424.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1515/SEM.2006.017</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tracy, J. L., &amp; Robins, R. W. (2008). The Nonverbal Expression of Pride: Evidence for Cross-Cultural Recognition. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 94, 516-530. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.94.3.516</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tuminello, R., &amp; Davidson, D. (2011). What the Face and Body Reveal: In-Group Emotion Effects and Stereotyping of Emotion in African-American and European-American Children. Experimental Child Psychology, 110, 258-274.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jecp.2011.02.016</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Van Bavel, J. J., Packer, D. J., &amp; Cunningham, W. A. (2008). The Neural Substrates of In-Group Bias: A Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging Investigation. Psychological Science, 19, 1131-1139.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.2008.02214.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wickline, V. B., Bailey, W., &amp; Nowicki, S. (2009). Cultural In-Group Advantage: Emotion Recognition in African American and European American Faces and Voices. The Journal of Genetic Psychology, 170, 5-30.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.3200/GNTP.170.1.5-30</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zhang, D., Wang, L., &amp; Luo, Y. (2012). Individual Differences in Detecting Rapidly Presented Fearful Faces. PLoS ONE, 7, e49517. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0049517</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.39786-ref61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zieber, N., Kangas, A., Hock, A., &amp; Bhatt, R. S. (2014). The Development of Intermodal Emotion Perception from Bodies and Voices. Journal of Experimental Child Psychology, 126C, 68-79. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jecp.2014.03.005</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>