<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" article-type="research article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Advances in Psychology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2160-7273</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Scientific Research Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12677/AP.2021.112043</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AP-40346</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>AP20210200000_76911139.pdf</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>人文社科</subject><subject> 合作期刊</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
 
 
  奖励还是安慰？情绪对进食量的影响研究概述
  Award or Comfort? The Review of the Moods Influence on Food Consumption
 
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>边</surname><given-names>子茗</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><addr-line>null</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>1</label><addr-line>西南大学心理学部，重庆</addr-line></aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>02</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>02</issue><fpage>374</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Copyright  2014 by authors and Scientific Research Publishing Inc. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY). http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
 
 
   
   情绪是否会影响进食量，以及会如何影响饮食目前还不清楚。通过对情绪与进食量研究的文献进行整理，从积极情绪、消极情绪对不同人群(限制性饮食者、进食障碍患者、肥胖和超重患者)进食量的影响分别进行梳理，评估了不同情绪效价对饮食亚群体的进食量的影响，从而发现该领域尚未解决的问题，并提出对未来研究方向的展望，进一步扩充情绪与进食量的相关研究。&lt;br/&gt;Whether emotions affect food intake and in whom remains unclear. This review analyzed the in-fluence of negative and positive moods on food intake among different groups (restrained eaters, people with eating disorders, obese and overweight eaters), and evaluated the effects of different emotional valence on food intake of dietary subgroups. As found the unsolved problem in this field, this review gives an integrated perspective for future research. 
  
 
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>情绪，进食量，限制性饮食，进食障碍，肥胖/超重, Moods</kwd><kwd> Food Consumption</kwd><kwd> Restrained Eater</kwd><kwd> Eating Disorder</kwd><kwd> Obese/Overweight</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>摘要</title><p>情绪是否会影响进食量，以及会如何影响饮食目前还不清楚。通过对情绪与进食量研究的文献进行整理，从积极情绪、消极情绪对不同人群(限制性饮食者、进食障碍患者、肥胖和超重患者)进食量的影响分别进行梳理，评估了不同情绪效价对饮食亚群体的进食量的影响，从而发现该领域尚未解决的问题，并提出对未来研究方向的展望，进一步扩充情绪与进食量的相关研究。</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>关键词</title><p>情绪，进食量，限制性饮食，进食障碍，肥胖/超重</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Award or Comfort? The Review of the Moods Influence on Food Consumption</title><p>Ziming Bian</p><p>Faculty of Psychology, Southwest University, Chongqing</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/9-1132162x4_hanspub.png" /></p><p>Received: Jan. 6<sup>th</sup>, 2021; accepted: Jan. 27<sup>th</sup>, 2021; published: Feb. 9<sup>th</sup>, 2021</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/9-1132162x5_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Whether emotions affect food intake and in whom remains unclear. This review analyzed the influence of negative and positive moods on food intake among different groups (restrained eaters, people with eating disorders, obese and overweight eaters), and evaluated the effects of different emotional valence on food intake of dietary subgroups. As found the unsolved problem in this field, this review gives an integrated perspective for future research.</p><p>Keywords:Moods, Food Consumption, Restrained Eater, Eating Disorder, Obese/Overweight</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.40346-formula34"><graphic xlink:href="//html.hanspub.org/file/9-1132162x6_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><p>Copyright &#169; 2021 by author(s) and Hans Publishers Inc.</p><p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/9-1132162x7_hanspub.png" /> <img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/9-1132162x8_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>1. 引言</title><p>进食问题会导致许多健康问题，比如超重/肥胖，心血管疾病，糖尿病以及一些癌症，这些疾病与全球高发病率和高死亡率有关(World Health Organization, 2020)。过度进食(overeating)现象已严重威胁人类健康，因此越来越多的研究开始研究过度进食的机制。其中，消极的情绪体验是过度进食的一种方式，人们通过过度进食的方式来应对抑郁、焦虑或愤怒等情绪(Nightingale &amp; Cassin, 2019)。这种现象通常被称作“情绪性进食”，也称为“安慰性进食”(comfort eating) (Gibson, 2012)或“压力诱导饮食”(stress-induced eating) (Greeno &amp; Wing, 1994)。最近几年的研究中，自我报告的情绪性进食的发生率越来越高(Gibson, 2012)。虽然之前的大多数研究报告了消极情绪对情绪化进食对负面情绪的反应，如悲伤或愤怒，但最近的一项系统性研究表明，当个体经历积极情绪时，如喜悦或兴奋时，他们也可能参与情绪化进食(Devonport, Nicholls, &amp; Fullerton, 2017; Evers, Marijn Stok, &amp; de Ridder, 2010)。情绪性进食不仅与导致肥胖风险增加的行为有关，例如暴饮暴食(binge eating)和饮食失控(lose control over eating) (Goossens, Braet, Van Vlierberghe, &amp; Mels, 2009; Kattermana, Kleinmanb, Hooda, Nackersa, &amp; Corsica, 2014)，同时也被认为是肥胖与抑郁之间的关键中介(van Strien, Konttinen, Homberg, Engels, &amp; Winkens, 2016)。无论个人对哪种类型的影响做出反应，情绪化饮食都与更大的肥胖和更高的体重指数(BMI)有关(van Strien et al., 2016)。此外，情绪化饮食也与不良的饮食摄入密切相关。情绪性进食者在对情绪的反应中往往会转向高能量和低营养密度的食物(Banos et al., 2014; Michels et al., 2012; Nguyen-Michel, Unger, &amp; Spruijt-Metz, 2007)，例如应激后糖和脂肪的摄入增加(Oliver, Wardle, &amp; Gibson, 2000)。</p><p>情感是人们日常生活中不可或缺的一部分。然而对于为什么情绪会影响饮食行为，什么样的情绪会影响饮食行为，什么群体会受到情绪的影响进而增大或减少进食量，目前仍然有很多争论。Macht (2008)在情绪影响进食的五因素模型中，将个体差异和情绪类型纳入模型的分析中来探讨情绪对进食量的影响(Macht, 2008)。一方面，之前的研究认为高唤醒或强烈的情绪会抑制进食。基于这样的想法，即这些情绪激活自主神经系统，从而引起一系列生理变化，可能会导致饱腹感，如胃排空减慢，血液从胃肠道分流到肌肉，以及释放抑制食欲的激素(Wing, Blair, Epstein, &amp; McDermott, 1990)。另一方面，中度的情绪唤醒会导致认知控制的能力下降。例如，限制饮食者是指为了减肥而有意识的控制自己的进食行为的人(Herman &amp; Mack, 1975)，他们在经历一些积极或消极情绪时，由于处理情绪问题比控制饮食问题更加紧迫，因此对进食行为的控制会降低，当抑制难以维持时，抑制解除后的过度进食可能随之而来(Polivy, Herman, &amp; Deo, 2010; Polivy, Herman, &amp; Mcfarlane, 1994)。总之，有人假设，不同种类的情绪变化会导致进食量的增加和减少。尽管情绪会影响人们的进食行为，但这一影响在不同人群中是否都会引发过度进食这一最基本的问题仍然不清楚。因此本文梳理了不同人群中(包括限制性饮食者，饮食障碍患者，肥胖和超重群体)情绪对进食量影响的实证研究，总结了现有研究结果，并对未来的研究进行展望。</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>2. 消极情绪对进食量的影响</title><sec id="s6_1"><title>2.1. 限制性饮食者</title><p>在限制性饮食者中，情绪对进食量的影响比较一致。一系列实验表明，在消极情绪状态下，限制性进食者比非限制进食者进食了更多的食物(有关综述，见Cardi, Leppanen, &amp; Treasure, 2015; Evers, Dingemans, Junghans, &amp; Boeve, 2018; Greeno &amp; Wing, 1994; Heatherton, Striepe, &amp; Wittenberg, 1998)。限制性饮食是指为了减轻或保持体重而控制自己的关于饮食的认知和行为模式(Herman &amp; Mack, 1975)，前人的研究中多用自我损耗(self-depletion)来解释限制性饮食者在消极情绪后的进食行为。控制自己的情绪需要消耗自己有限的内在认知资源。当一种情景需要两种自我控制行为时，第二项任务的执行可能会因为能量消耗而受损(Muraven &amp; Baumeister, 2000)，例如，当限制性饮食者需要调节自己的负面情绪并抑制进食行为时，他们对进食行为的控制往往会降低。越来越多的研究支持消极情绪可能会损害对食物抑制反应的能力(Padmala, Bauer, &amp; Pessoa, 2011; Rebetez, Rochat, Billieux, Gay, &amp; Van der Linden, 2015)。一项使用功能磁共振成像的研究发现，相比于中性条件，在经历消极情绪时，高度负性紧迫感的参与者激活了更多与抑制控制相关的脑区，这表明大脑调节资源的过度反应性可能是解除抑制的罪魁祸首(Chester et al., 2016)。限制性饮食者也会在自我耗尽后解除抑制。Vohs和Heatherton (2000)对比了慢性应激条件下和中等应激状态下的女性节食，让她们观看令人不安的电影并用应用抑制情绪的策略来调节自己的情绪反应，结果发现处在慢性应激中的女性节食者在后续的味觉任务中吃了更多的冰淇淋(Vohs &amp; Heatherton, 2000)。</p></sec><sec id="s6_2"><title>2.2. 进食障碍患者</title><p>过往的一些证据表明，消极情绪是暴饮暴食(binge eating)发生的诱因，抑郁情绪(即悲伤)是这种疾病中最常见的负性情绪(Nicholls, Devonport, &amp; Blake, 2016)。一些横断面、实验和治疗结果研究表明，抑郁症状，急性悲伤情绪和暴饮暴食行为之间存在关联，并表明更高水平的抑郁与更严重的暴饮暴食有关 (Antony, Johnson, Carr-Nangle, &amp; Abel, 1994; Dingemans, Martijn, Jansen, &amp; van Furth, 2009; Telch &amp; Agras, 1996)。此外，一项综述(Dingemans, Danner, &amp; Parks, 2017)以及一项元分析(Cardi, Leppanen, &amp; Treasure, 2015)也发现，负面情绪会引发暴饮暴食者的进食增加。然而，近期的一项元分析发现消极情绪对饮食障碍患者的进食行为并没有显著的影响(Evers et al., 2018)。这可能是因为Cardi, Leppanen, &amp; Treasure (2015)的研究仅分析了三项涉及暴饮暴食症状的患者，而Evers等人(2018)整理并分析了八项相关的研究。这一异质性在一定程度上可以解释为情绪诱导和食物类型的多样性，这表明研究临床样本中情绪相关饮食的研究者在选择情绪诱导和食物类型时应注意。此外，在有暴饮暴食的患者中，有一些亚型可能在情绪-饮食关系中有很大差异。例如，一些暴食症患者可能具有抑郁症的共病，而暴饮暴食行为和研究显示，抑郁程度越高，暴饮暴食越严重(Dingemans et al., 2017)。</p></sec><sec id="s6_3"><title>2.3. 肥胖/超重群体</title><p>肥胖者通常被认为是典型的情绪化进食者(Schachter, Goldman, &amp; Gordon, 1968)，然而一项综述(Greeno &amp; Wing, 1994)以及近期的两项元分析(Cardi, Leppanen, et al., 2015; Evers et al., 2018)发现超重或肥胖人群的消极情绪变化与饮食行为的变化无关。一项应用生态瞬时评估法记录超重和健康体重人群进食行为的研究发现，消极情绪并不是超重/肥胖群体过度进食的原因(Boh et al., 2016)。最近的一项研究通过启动体重正常和超重的女性的负性和中性情绪，并比较他们在接下来实验中的甜、咸和健康食物进食量和食物选择，研究人员发现负性情绪暴露下，两组的进食量均增加了，出乎意料的是正常体重组的增加幅度高于超重组。然而，在食物选择方面存在差异。体重正常的女性只增加了甜食的摄入量，而体重超重的女性则显著增加了甜食和咸食的摄入量(Aguiar-Bloemer &amp; Diez-Garcia, 2018)。这表明，消极情绪下不同类型食物的选择或许是导致他们后续体重增长以及其他健康问题的原因，同时表明，未来针对超重/肥胖人群研究应更加细致，关注消极情绪对这一群体更细致层面(如甜食等高热量食物或蔬菜等健康食物)的进食量的影响。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s7"><title>3. 积极情绪对进食量的影响</title><p>Cardi, Leppanen, &amp; Treasure (2015)和Evers等人(2018)的研究均发现，积极情绪会导致进食量增加，但是仅发现了非常小的这一效应。一些研究表明，积极影响与健康食品的消费量增加呈正相关(Fedorikhin &amp; Patrick, 2010; Gardner, Wansink, Kim, &amp; Park, 2014; Garg, Wansink, &amp; Inman, 2007)。然而，与消极情绪相比，积极情绪对饮食行为的影响很少被研究。未来的研究还需要进一步评估潜在的机制，并评估某些个体，如过度紧张的进食者，在多大程度上特别容易因积极情绪而增加进食。</p><sec id="s7_1"><title>3.1. 限制性饮食者</title><p>对积极情绪的研究不如对消极情绪的研究那么普遍，关于积极情绪是否会导致限制性饮食者进食量的增加，目前仍未得出一致的结论。Cools等人(1992)通过诱导3种情绪(中性、积极和消极)对女性限制性饮食者的食物摄入量进行研究，结果发现，中性情绪下，限制性程度越高，食物的摄入量越小(Cools, Schotte, &amp; McNally, 1992)。然而在消极情绪和积极情绪下，食物摄入量随着限制程度的增加而增加，而消极情绪下进食更多。随后Cavallo和Pinto (2001)通过比较吸烟和不吸烟的限制性饮食者在消极情绪和积极情绪下的进食量，结果发现，两种情绪下，限制性饮食者的进食量并没有显著差异(Cavallo &amp; Pinto, 2001)。Yeomans和Coughlan (2009)通过区分限制性和去抑制分别研究了限制性饮食者的在积极、消极、中性情绪下的不同表现，结果发现高限制性高去抑制的人群在消极情绪条件下吃得最多，而低限制性高去抑制的人群在积极情绪条件下吃得最多，在消极情绪条件下最少(Yeomans &amp; Coughlan, 2009)。而低去抑制低限制性的女性在三种情绪下都进食了相似的量。这可能表明，限制性饮食者的限制性和去抑制性程度与不同情绪效价共同作用会导致不同的进食行为。</p></sec><sec id="s7_2"><title>3.2. 进食障碍患者</title><p>仅有几项研究探究了不同情绪效价对饮食障碍患者进食行为的影响，并发现积极情绪与厌食症患者中卡路里消耗增加有关，并且在暴食症患者中与高美味度零食的进食量减少相关(Cardi, Esposito, Clarke, Schifano, &amp; Treasure, 2015; Cardi, Lounes, Kan, &amp; Treasure, 2013)。说明积极情绪对饮食障碍患者的不健康进食症状又一定的改善。</p></sec><sec id="s7_3"><title>3.3. 健康人群</title><p>健康人群中积极的情绪往往与更高的进食量相关，其中健康人群在快乐和幸福的时候往往会产生快乐进食(Macht, 1999)。此外，在实验室环境中，实验诱导的积极情绪可以增加巧克力的愉悦感和口感(Macht, Roth, &amp; Ellgring, 2002)。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s8"><title>4. 总结与展望</title><p>本文总结了消极情绪和积极情绪对分症状饮食行为人群进食量的影响。通过综述可以发现，对于消极情绪对限制性饮食者的影响，前人的研究得到了一致的结论，消极情绪与限制性饮食者的进食量增加有关(详见，Cardi, Leppanen, &amp; Treasure, 2015; Evers, Dingemans, Junghans, &amp; Boeve, 2018)。而在饮食障碍患者以及肥胖/超重人群中，消极情绪与进食量的关系并没有得出显著的结论。对于积极情绪，由于前人研究较少，目前的研究并没有得出一致的结论，积极情绪对饮食亚群体的影响是有益的还是有害的目前还不明确。</p><p>未来的研究中应扩充积极情绪对进食量的影响。因为消极情绪是许多饮食障碍发病的诱发因素(Nicholls et al., 2016)，因此前人的研究更多的集中在消极情绪对进食量的影响，而对于积极情绪是诱发更严重的不健康进食症状还是改善已有的症状仍没有一致的结论。前人的研究没有得到一致结论的原因可能是不同诱导积极情绪的实验材料导致诱发了不同程度的积极情绪，近期的一项研究表明，当消极情绪或积极情绪的程度不同时，可能会导致不同的食物选择和进食行为，进而导致进食量的差异(Barnhart, Braden, &amp; Jordan, 2020)。因此，未来对积极情绪和消极情绪的研究中，应使消极情绪和积极情绪的诱发达到同一唤醒程度，进而比较两种情绪效价对进食量的影响。</p><p>前人的研究更多的是集中于实验室诱发消极或积极情绪以及随后测量的进食量的变化，但是一项对进食障碍患者的日常生活研究进行的荟萃分析发现，与平均的负面情绪水平和正常饮食前的负面情绪水平相比，进食障碍患者在暴饮暴食前的负面情绪水平明显更高(Haedt-Matt &amp; Keel, 2011)。因此对日常生活研究进行类似的荟萃分析对未来的研究很重要，并且目前对于健康的非临床群体的研究较少，因此未来应多扩充这一部分的研究，以便弄清楚这些发现在多大程度上与目前实验室研究的结果相一致。</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>文章引用</title><p>边子茗. 奖励还是安慰？情绪对进食量的影响研究概述Award or Comfort? The Review of the Moods Influence on Food Consumption[J]. 心理学进展, 2021, 11(02): 374-380. https://doi.org/10.12677/AP.2021.112043</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>参考文献</title></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Aguiar-Bloemer, A. C., &amp; Diez-Garcia, R. W. (2018). Influence of Emotions Evoked by Life Events on Food Choice. Eating and Weight Disorders, 23, 45-53. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s40519-017-0468-8</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Antony, M. M., Johnson, W. G., Carr-Nangle, R. E., &amp; Abel, J. L. (1994). Psychopathology Correlates of Binge Eating and Binge Eating Disorder. Comprehensive Psychiatry, 35, 386-392. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/0010-440X(94)90280-1</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Banos, R. M., Cebolla, A., Moragrega, I., Van Strien, T., Fernandez-Aranda, F., Aguera, Z. et al. (2014). Relationship between Eating Styles and Temperament in an Anorexia Nervosa, Healthy Control, and Morbid Obesity Female Sample. Appetite, 76, 76-83. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2014.01.012</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Barnhart, W. R., Braden, A. L., &amp; Jordan, A. K. (2020). Negative and Positive Emotional Eating Uniquely Interact with Ease of Activation, Intensity, and Duration of Emotional Reactivity to Predict Increased Binge Eating. Appetite, 151, Article ID: 104688. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2020.104688</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Boh, B., Jansen, A., Clijsters, I., Nederkoorn, C., Lemmens, L., Spanakis, G., &amp; Roefs, A. (2016). Indulgent Thinking? Ecological Momentary Assessment of Overweight and Healthy-Weight Participants’ Cognitions and Emotions. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 87, 196-206. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brat.2016.10.001</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cardi, V., Esposito, M., Clarke, A., Schifano, S., &amp; Treasure, J. (2015). The Impact of Induced Positive Mood on Symptomatic Behaviour in Eating Disorders. An Experimental, AB/BA Crossover Design Testing a Multimodal Presentation during a Test-Meal. Appetite, 87, 192-198. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2014.12.224</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cardi, V., Leppanen, J., &amp; Treasure, J. (2015). The Effects of Negative and Positive Mood Induction on Eating Behaviour: A Meta-Analysis of Laboratory Studies in the Healthy Population and Eating and Weight Disorders. Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews, 57, 299-309. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2015.08.011</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cardi, V., Lounes, N., Kan, C., &amp; Treasure, J. (2013). Meal Support Using Mobile Technology in Anorexia Nervosa. Contextual Differences between Inpatient and Outpatient Settings. Appetite, 60, 33-39.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2012.10.004</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cavallo, D. A., &amp; Pinto, A. (2001). Effects of Mood Induction on Eating Behavior and Cigarette Craving in Dietary Restrainers. Eating Behaviors, 2, 113-127. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/S1471-0153(01)00023-X</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chester, D. S., Lynam, D. R., Milich, R., Powell, D. K., Andersen, A. H., &amp; DeWall, C. N. (2016). How Do Negative Emotions Impair Self-Control? A Neural Model of Negative Urgency. NeuroImage, 132, 43-50.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2016.02.024</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cools, J., Schotte, D. E., &amp; McNally, R. J. (1992). Emotional Arousal and Overeating in Restrained Eaters. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 101, 348-351. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0021-843X.101.2.348</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Devonport, T. J., Nicholls, W., &amp; Fullerton, C. (2017). A Systematic Review of the Association between Emotions and Eating Behaviour in Normal and Overweight Adult Populations. Journal of Health Psychology, 24, 3-24.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/1359105317697813</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Dingemans, A. E., Martijn, C., Jansen, A. T., &amp; van Furth, E. F. (2009). The Effect of Suppressing Negative Emotions on Eating Behavior in Binge Eating Disorder. Appetite, 52, 51-57. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2008.08.004</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Dingemans, A., Danner, U., &amp; Parks, M. (2017). Emotion Regulation in Binge Eating Disorder: A Review. Nutrients, 9, 1274. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.3390/nu9111274</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Evers, C., Dingemans, A., Junghans, A. F., &amp; Boeve, A. (2018). Feeling Bad or Feeling Good, Does Emotion Affect Your Consumption of Food? A Meta-Analysis of the Experimental Evidence. Neuroscience &amp; Biobehavioral Reviews, 92, 195-208. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neubiorev.2018.05.028</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Evers, C., Marijn Stok, F., &amp; de Ridder, D. T. (2010). Feeding Your Feelings: Emotion Regulation Strategies and Emotional Eating. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 36, 792-804. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167210371383</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fedorikhin, A., &amp; Patrick, V. M. (2010). Positive Mood and Resistance to Temptation: The Interfering Influence of Elevated Arousal. Journal of Consumer Research, 37, 698-711. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1086/655665</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gardner, M. P., Wansink, B., Kim, J., &amp; Park, S. B. (2014). Better Moods for Better Eating?: How Mood Influences Food Choice. Journal of Consumer Psychology, 24, 320-335. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcps.2014.01.002</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Garg, N., Wansink, B., &amp; Inman, J. J. (2007). The Influence of Incidental Affect on Consumers’ Food Intake. Journal of Marketing, 71, 194-206. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1509/jmkg.71.1.194</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gibson, E. L. (2012). The Psychobiology of Comfort Eating: Implications for Neuropharmacological Interventions. Behavioural Pharmacology, 23, 442-460. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/FBP.0b013e328357bd4e</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Goossens, L., Braet, C., Van Vlierberghe, L., &amp; Mels, S. (2009). Loss of Control over Eating in Overweight Youngsters: The Role of Anxiety, Depression and Emotional Eating. European Eating Disorders Review, 17, 68-78.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/erv.892</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Greeno, C. G., &amp; Wing, R. R. (1994). Stress-Induced Eating. Psychological Bulletin, 115, 444-464.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.115.3.444</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Haedt-Matt, A. A., &amp; Keel, P. K. (2011). Revisiting the Affect Regulation Model of Binge Eating: A Meta-Analysis of Studies Using Ecological Momentary Assessment. Psychological Bulletin, 137, 660-681.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/a0023660</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Heatherton, T. E., Striepe, M., &amp; Wittenberg, L. (1998). Emotional Distress and Disinhibited Eating: The Role of Self. Personality &amp; Social Psychology Bulletin, 24, 301-313. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/0146167298243007</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Herman, C. P., &amp; Mack, D. (1975). Restrained and Unrestrained Eating. Journal of Personality, 43, 647-660.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-6494.1975.tb00727.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kattermana, S. N., Kleinmanb, B. M., Hooda, M. M., Nackersa, L. M., &amp; Corsica, J. A. (2014). Mindfulness Meditation as an Intervention for Binge Eating, Emotional Eating, and Weight Loss: A Systematic Review. Eating Behaviors, 15, 197-204. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eatbeh.2014.01.005</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Macht, M. (1999). Characteristics of Eating in Anger, Fear, Sadness and Joy. Appetite, 33, 129-139.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1006/appe.1999.0236</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Macht, M. (2008). How Emotions Affect Eating: A Five-Way Model. Appetite, 50, 1-11.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2007.07.002</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Macht, M., Roth, S., &amp; Ellgring, H. (2002). Chocolate Eating in Healthy Men during Experimentally Induced Sadness and Joy. Appetite, 39, 147-158. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1006/appe.2002.0499</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Michels, N., Sioen, I., Braet, C., Eiben, G., Hebestreit, A., Huybrechts, I. et al. (2012). Stress, Emotional Eating Behaviour and Dietary Patterns in Children. Appetite, 59, 762-769. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2012.08.010</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Muraven, M., &amp; Baumeister, R. F. (2000). Self-Regulation and Depletion of Limited Resources: Does Self-Control Resemble a Muscle? Psychological Bulletin, 126, 247-259. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.126.2.247</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nguyen-Michel, S. T., Unger, J. B., &amp; Spruijt-Metz, D. (2007). Dietary Correlates of Emotional Eating in Adolescence. Appetite, 49, 494-499. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2007.03.005</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nicholls, W., Devonport, T. J., &amp; Blake, M. (2016). The Association between Emotions and Eating Behaviour in an Obese Population with Binge Eating Disorder. Obesity Reviews, 17, 30-42. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/obr.12329</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nightingale, B. A., &amp; Cassin, S. E. (2019). Disordered Eating among Individuals with Excess Weight: A Review of Recent Research. Current Obesity Reports, 8, 112-127. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s13679-019-00333-5</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Oliver, G., Wardle, J., &amp; Gibson, E. L. (2000). Stress and Food Choice: A Laboratory Study. Psychosomatic Medicine, 62, 853-865. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/00006842-200011000-00016</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Padmala, S., Bauer, A., &amp; Pessoa, L. (2011). Negative Emotion Impairs Conflict-Driven Executive Control. Frontiers in Psychology, 2, 192. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2011.00192</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Polivy, J., Herman, C. P., &amp; Deo, R. (2010). Getting a Bigger Slice of the Pie. Effects on Eating and Emotion in Restrained and Unrestrained Eaters. Appetite, 55, 426-430. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2010.07.015</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Polivy, J., Herman, C. P., &amp; Mcfarlane, T. (1994). Effects of Anxiety on Eating—Does Palatability Moderate Distress-Induced Overeating in Dieters. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 103, 505-510.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0021-843X.103.3.505</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rebetez, M. M. L., Rochat, L., Billieux, J., Gay, P., &amp; Van der Linden, M. (2015). Do Emotional Stimuli Interfere with Two Distinct Components of Inhibition? Cognition &amp; Emotion, 29, 559-567. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/02699931.2014.922054</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Schachter, S., Goldman, R., &amp; Gordon, A. (1968). Effects of Fear, Food Deprivation, and Obesity on Eating. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 10, 91-97. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/h0026284</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Telch, C. F., &amp; Agras, W. S. (1996). The Effects of Short-Term Food Deprivation on Caloric Intake in Eating-Disordered Subjects. Appetite, 26, 221-233. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1006/appe.1996.0017</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">van Strien, T., Konttinen, H., Homberg, J. R., Engels, R. C. M. E., &amp; Winkens, L. H. H. (2016). Emotional Eating as a Mediator between Depression and Weight Gain. Appetite, 100, 216-224. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2016.02.034</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Vohs, K. D., &amp; Heatherton, T. F. (2000). Self-Regulatory Failure: A Resource-Depletion Approach. Psychological Science, 11, 249-254. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-9280.00250</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">World Health Organization (2020). Obesity and Overweight.  
https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/obesity-and-overweight</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wing, R. R., Blair, E. H., Epstein, L. H., &amp; McDermott, M. D. (1990). Psychological Stress and Glucose Metabolism in Obese and Normal-Weight Subjects: A Possible Mechanism for Differences in Stress-Induced Eating. Health Psychology, 9, 693-700. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0278-6133.9.6.693</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.40346-ref46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Yeomans, M. R., &amp; Coughlan, E. (2009). Mood-Induced Eating. Interactive Effects of Restraint and Tendency to Overeat. Appetite, 52, 290-298. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.appet.2008.10.006</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>