<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" article-type="research article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ACM</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Advances in Clinical Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2161-8712</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Scientific Research Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12677/ACM.2021.115317</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ACM-42464</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>ACM20210500000_24047010.pdf</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>医药卫生</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
 
 
  种植导向的血管化腓骨肌皮瓣移植在颌面部骨缺损重建修复中的临床应用
  Clinical Application of Vascularized Fibula Free Flap Transplantation Combined with Implantation in Reconstruction and Repair of Maxillofacial Bone Defect
 
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>孙</surname><given-names>一航</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>刘</surname><given-names>雁鸣</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff2"><addr-line>浙江大学医学院附属第二医院口腔颌面外科，浙江 杭州</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>null</addr-line></aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>05</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>05</issue><fpage>2204</fpage><lpage>2213</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Copyright  2014 by authors and Scientific Research Publishing Inc. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY). http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
 
 
  外伤、肿瘤、手术等一系列的原因，可能会导致患者出现颌面部的骨缺损，往往伴随大面积的牙列缺损，相对应的咀嚼及发音功能也受到较大影响。而随着种植外科的不断发展，关注点也不再只局限于颜面外形上的恢复，更多转移至口腔功能上的重建修复。为了同时覆盖这两种需求，目前临床上应用较多的方式主要是通过游离骨组织瓣(包括腓骨肌皮瓣、髂骨肌皮瓣、肩胛骨肌皮瓣等)来修复相应大面积软硬组织复合缺损，而后修复牙列缺损。本文主要讨论其中的游离血管化腓骨肌皮瓣移植结合日益成熟的种植外科技术，修复伴牙列缺损的颌面部骨组织缺损，以达到最大程度恢复患者术后美观及功能需求的相关临床进展。
   A series of reasons such as trauma, tumor, surgery, etc. may cause the patient to have maxillofacial bone defect, which is often accompanied by large area of dentition defect, and the corresponding chewing and pronunciation functions are also greatly affected. With the continuous development of implant surgery, the focus is no longer limited to the restoration of facial appearance, but more to the reconstruction and restoration of oral function. In order to cover these two needs at the same time, the current clinical application is mainly to use free bone tissue flaps (including fibula free flap, iliac crest free flap, scapula free flap, etc.) to repair the complex maxillofacial defect, and then the dentition defect. This article mainly discusses the related clinical progress of vascularized fibula free flap transplantation combined with increasingly mature implant surgery techniques to repair maxillofacial bone tissue defects and dentition defects in order to maximize the recovery of postoperative aesthetic and functional needs of patients.
 
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>骨缺损，牙列缺损，血管化腓骨瓣移植，种植修复，数字化外科, Bone Defect</kwd><kwd> Dentition Defect</kwd><kwd> Vascularized Fibula Free Flap</kwd><kwd> Implant</kwd><kwd> Digital Surgery</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>摘要</title><p>外伤、肿瘤、手术等一系列的原因，可能会导致患者出现颌面部的骨缺损，往往伴随大面积的牙列缺损，相对应的咀嚼及发音功能也受到较大影响。而随着种植外科的不断发展，关注点也不再只局限于颜面外形上的恢复，更多转移至口腔功能上的重建修复。为了同时覆盖这两种需求，目前临床上应用较多的方式主要是通过游离骨组织瓣(包括腓骨肌皮瓣、髂骨肌皮瓣、肩胛骨肌皮瓣等)来修复相应大面积软硬组织复合缺损，而后修复牙列缺损。本文主要讨论其中的游离血管化腓骨肌皮瓣移植结合日益成熟的种植外科技术，修复伴牙列缺损的颌面部骨组织缺损，以达到最大程度恢复患者术后美观及功能需求的相关临床进展。</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>关键词</title><p>骨缺损，牙列缺损，血管化腓骨瓣移植，种植修复，数字化外科</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Clinical Application of Vascularized Fibula Free Flap Transplantation Combined with Implantation in Reconstruction and Repair of Maxillofacial Bone Defect</title><p>Yihang Sun<sup>*</sup>, Yanming Liu<sup>#</sup></p><p>Maxillofacial Surgery of the Second Affiliated Hospital of Zhejiang University, Hangzhou Zhejiang</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/26-1572199x5_hanspub.png" /></p><p>Received: Apr. 17<sup>th</sup>, 2021; accepted: May 2<sup>nd</sup>, 2021; published: May 21<sup>st</sup>, 2021</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/26-1572199x6_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>A series of reasons such as trauma, tumor, surgery, etc. may cause the patient to have maxillofacial bone defect, which is often accompanied by large area of dentition defect, and the corresponding chewing and pronunciation functions are also greatly affected. With the continuous development of implant surgery, the focus is no longer limited to the restoration of facial appearance, but more to the reconstruction and restoration of oral function. In order to cover these two needs at the same time, the current clinical application is mainly to use free bone tissue flaps (including fibula free flap, iliac crest free flap, scapula free flap, etc.) to repair the complex maxillofacial defect, and then the dentition defect. This article mainly discusses the related clinical progress of vascularized fibula free flap transplantation combined with increasingly mature implant surgery techniques to repair maxillofacial bone tissue defects and dentition defects in order to maximize the recovery of postoperative aesthetic and functional needs of patients.</p><p>Keywords:Bone Defect, Dentition Defect, Vascularized Fibula Free Flap, Implant, Digital Surgery</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.42464-formula22"><graphic xlink:href="//html.hanspub.org/file/26-1572199x7_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><p>Copyright &#169; 2021 by author(s) and Hans Publishers Inc.</p><p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/26-1572199x8_hanspub.png" /> <img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/26-1572199x9_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>1. 引言</title><p>上下颌骨作为颌面部的重要组成部分，不仅影响颜面部外形，同时承担咀嚼、呼吸、吞咽、语言能力等多种功能。临床工作中，各种原因导致的颌面部骨缺损患者往往伴随大面积的牙列缺损。随着血管外科及种植外科的发展，颌骨重建及牙列缺损的修复被更多人重视。如何选择合适的重建修复方案一直尚无定论，本文主要对其中近年来血管化腓骨肌皮瓣结合种植支持的义齿修复骨及牙列缺损在临床工作中的探索应用作一综述。</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>2. 血管化组织瓣修复骨缺损</title><p>对于临床上颌面部骨缺损重建的方法较多，包括自体及异体骨移植、牵张成骨、非生物材料植入及单纯重建钛板植入替代骨缺损等。自体骨移植又包含了骨组织及软骨组织移植，联合种植外科共同修复颌面部骨缺损的主要方式仍需骨组织移植。自体骨组织又包含血管化及非血管化自体骨，以及自体冷冻骨移植。随着当前显微外科的不断发展与应用，血管化自体骨移植无论是成功率还是对于可能伴随的牙列缺损的后期修复，都有着极其巨大的临床优势，已成为颌骨缺损重建中应用最多的修复方式之一。</p><p>血管化自体骨组织瓣供区主要包括桡骨、肩胛骨、肋骨、髂骨、股骨、腓骨及跖骨 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref1">1</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref2">2</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref3">3</xref>]。结合对供区及受区的影响、术后恢复效果、手术成功率、以及骨内种植修复等多方面因素综合考虑，最广泛应用于临床的是旋髂深动脉供血的髂骨移植和腓动脉供血的腓骨移植 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref4">4</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref5">5</xref>]。</p><sec id="s6_1"><title>2.1. 游离腓骨肌皮瓣 Fibula Free Flap (FFF)</title><p>历史上最早的一例成功通过游离腓骨瓣修复下颌骨缺损的病例是由Hidalgo于1989年首次报道。FFF具有以下优点：1) 供血血管腓动脉相对解剖位置恒定(90%起自于胫后动脉)，且其血管外径较大(2.93 &#177; 0.47 mm)，易于吻合及提高手术成功率；2) 腓骨骨量充足，有足够的长度(全长32.58 &#177; 2.26 cm，其中可移植部分平均可达25 cm) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref4">4</xref>]；3) 腓骨骨髓及骨膜具有双重血管系统，即使只保留弓状动脉的骨膜支血供来源，腓骨也可以成活 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref6">6</xref>]；4) 腓骨具有较坚实的皮质骨，利于后续种植外科的进一步修复以恢复咀嚼功能。但同时，FFF也仍存在一定的缺陷，比如：1) 腓骨平均直径约10.4~16 mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref7">7</xref>]，约为下颌骨平均高度的一半，重建下颌骨时无法恢复令人满意的垂直高度；2) 国内外偶有腓深神经损伤及截取腓骨过多后术后踝关节不稳定的病例报道；3) 且由于术后的腿部制动，存在下肢深静脉血栓的潜在风险。近30年来，随着这一技术的不断应用与发展，已经日益成熟，Wei等学者于2018年已就此类皮瓣的制取作出了完善的总结与分享 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref8">8</xref>]。Ide等学者也通过CT辅助下的腓骨解剖形态分析确定了腓骨中最适合植入植体的节段以利于腓骨瓣的制备 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref9">9</xref>]。</p></sec><sec id="s6_2"><title>2.2. 游离腓骨肌皮瓣及其他常见临床游离骨组织瓣比较</title><p>除去FFF外，临床上常用的或常见于国内外文献报道的骨组织瓣主要包括游离髂骨肌皮瓣Iliac Crest Free Flap (ICFF)、游离肩胛骨肌皮瓣Scapula Free Flap (SFF)及游离桡骨肌皮瓣Osteocutaneous Radial Forearm Free Flap (RFFF) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref1">1</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref3">3</xref>]。</p><p>除外前述优点，相对于几种常见的骨组织瓣，FFF在多项研究中表现出了更少的术后骨吸收及更好的稳定性，其次是ICFF及SFF。而在上述几种常见骨组织瓣中，ICFF在重建下颌骨时存在更高的失败率，Brown及其团队认为这可能与其血管蒂长度更短及吻合技术要求更高密切相关 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref10">10</xref>]。而对于种植外科来说，FFF和ICFF在解剖形态上更适合后期种植修复 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref9">9</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref11">11</xref>]，其次是SFF，而RFFF由于其骨量及高度，密度等因素，最不适合植体的植入。</p><p>相较于其他骨组织瓣，腓骨内植体已被广泛证实可以拥有更好的初期稳定性，可以更好的提供早期负载能力，此外，血管化游离腓骨肌瓣有着更好的骨整合率，发生种植体周围炎的概率显著小于其他血管化游离组织瓣及非血管化自体骨组织移植 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref12">12</xref>]。SFF与ICFF相比拥有类似的骨密度及皮质骨厚度，但由于亚洲人种肩胛岗菲薄，不利于后期的牙列缺损修复 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref1">1</xref>]，故国内较少报道通过SFF与种植修复颌面部骨缺损，国外学者则认为，SFF拥有较低的供区影响及较薄的皮岛组织，适合作为老年人的理想修复选择方式，但由于老年患者SFF缺乏根尖区骨宽度，也无法联用种植手段修复牙列缺损 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref11">11</xref>]。</p><p>而作为最适合种植的两种骨组织瓣，FFF与ICFF无论在供区发病率、疼痛评分、术后愈合、语言能力、生活质量等方面都有类似的表现 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref11">11</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref13">13</xref>]，但综合考虑，对于颌面部不伴牙列缺损的骨缺损(如下颌角处)的患者，ICFF可能可以作为首选的骨组织瓣，而对于无牙合患者及需要修复长段下颌骨缺损(如下颌骨次全切及全切术)的患者，或需要髁状突重建的患者，首选则必然是血管化FFF [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref10">10</xref>]。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s7"><title>3. 种植修复牙列缺损</title><sec id="s7_1"><title>3.1. 重建修复方案设计</title><p>术前修复方案的设计对于手术的整体成功率以及预后无疑是至关重要的。相关辅助检查及设计例如术前患区常规行计算机断层扫描(CT)确定骨缺损范围及围手术区重要血管神经结构，常规行供区腓动、静脉多普勒超声检查排除血管变异情况并指导骨肌皮瓣的设计。</p><p>无论是颌骨的重建还是种植修复中植体的植入，都离不开各种辅助手段，如锥形束CT (Cone Beam CT, CBCT)技术及计算机辅助设计和制造(CAD/CAM)技术。数字化外科的发展与应用 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref14">14</xref>] - [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref19">19</xref>]，无论对于重建钛板的制作，抑或是对于后续种植体的位置及方向，以及远期修复体的成功率，都有着极其重要的指导意义，不但能使修复后的颌骨在功能性和美观性上更贴近健侧形态，也能有效规避可能存在的植体与重建钛板相互影响的潜在危害，同时可以极大程度上缩短手术时间，减少腓骨瓣缺血时间，更能有效减少其他潜在的术后并发症。</p></sec><sec id="s7_2"><title>3.2. 种植植入及负载时机的选择</title><p>对于植体植入时机的选择，目前尚未形成共识，不同的学者持有不同的看法，相关研究对同期植入与延期植入植体的FFF移植术后患者进行对比后发现，两者间的植体稳定性相似，并无明显的统计学差异 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref20">20</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref21">21</xref>]。重建手术中同期植入植体的安全性已被广泛证实 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref22">22</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref23">23</xref>]，其好处也显而易见，不但可以减少手术次数，而且可以更早的开始植体的骨整合过程，更早进行负载恢复患者的口腔咀嚼功能，整体上减少达到功能性修复所需的时间。但同时，同期手术的整体手术时间会延长，对于术者的熟练度要求也会相应增高，且对于颌面部恶性肿瘤患者，由于复发的可能性，也应更严格把握手术适应证，但相对的，恶性肿瘤患者由于术后预期寿命明显减短，尽快完成最终的修复对他们生活质量的改善也有较大意义 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref24">24</xref>]。同期植入手术细分也可分为先完成腓骨段的塑形及固定，再根据上下颌骨及咬合关系手术根据术者经验植入植体或在术前设计的种植导板引导下植入。或先行在导板辅助设计下于腓骨段内植入植体并切割塑形，再根据最终修复所需植体轴向在转移杆卡引导下将腓骨段定位及固定，后者可以有效地避免在后续修复过程中由于植体的轴向或位置不良产生无效植体 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref25">25</xref>]。</p><p>另一些支持延期种植的学者认为，同期植入植体可能存在植体位置及方向不正确，且移植骨组织瓣的血供不足可能影响植体的骨整合程度，也可能存在植体植入后导致血供受影响而影响骨组织瓣预后。有文献报道骨组织瓣移植后前6个月对于长远的治疗效果尤为重要，建议于重建术后6~18个月，确认FFF软硬组织整合完善且稳定并排除恶性肿瘤复发可能后，二次手术行种植修复 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref26">26</xref>]。</p><p>更有甚者，Pauchet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref27">27</xref>] 及Richelle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref17">17</xref>] 等提出了先将植体植入患者腓骨段内，待植体与骨组织形成完善的骨整合后，再将患者腓骨段组织截取植入颌面部以修复缺损。Pauchet等认为这种手术方案的设计可以使植体在血供充分的情况下完成骨整合，且可以在不增加血管风险的情况下植入更多植体。但这种技术受限于高精度的CT扫描及三维重建，以及一期手术的种植导板设计和二期手术所需的腓骨段切割导轨设计。也无法适用于大多数容易导致骨缺损的肿瘤患者，故离进一步推广仍需技术的发展以及进一步的病例数据论证。Richelle等学者的SDS技术(Three-dimensional digital surgical design and simulation)中，认可了Rohner等学者 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref28">28</xref>] 在恶性肿瘤患者切除原发肿瘤时，在计算机设计导板的指导下，同期于腓骨段中预先植入植体，观察肿瘤是否复发的过程中植体可以与腓骨先行产生良好的骨结合，排除肿瘤复发可能后二次手术再次在导板指引下行腓骨段移植，可以极大的减少修复所需的时间，也规避了肿瘤复发的相关因素。Freudlsperger等也报道了类似的病例 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref29">29</xref>]。</p><p>此外，对于需要术后辅助放疗治疗的患者，学者也抱有不同观点，大多数学者认为延期种植能降低放射性颌骨骨髓炎的发生率及种植失败率，一般认为放疗后6个月相对安全 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref30">30</xref>]，若时间允许，可将种植手术延期至放疗后12~18个月 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref31">31</xref>]。但Maria等在2019年报道的一项短期回顾性研究表明FFF移植时同期种植不会延迟术后放疗计划，也不会增加放疗毒性及并发症风险，对于辐射剂量范围也无确切要求，但可以显著利于患者术后早期生活质量的改善 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref23">23</xref>]，多篇文献也均得出类似的结论。也有学者认为同期种植手术能在放疗治疗前提供植体初步骨整合的时间，潜在降低种植失败率及减少腓骨的术后吸收 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref12">12</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref32">32</xref>]。</p><p>至于负载时机，多数学者认为，植体植入后3~6个月进行负载是相对比较合适的，但也有学者认为植体在腓骨上有较好的初期稳定性，可以在高精度的计算机辅助设计下进行即刻负载，达到颌骨重建、腓骨内种植及义齿修复一步到位 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref33">33</xref>]。但这种技术适应证范围较窄，且报告的病例数量及后续随访数据不足，仍需进一步验证。</p></sec><sec id="s7_3"><title>3.3. 植体的选择</title><p>在既往的研究中，7~10 mm的垂直骨高度被认为是种植体植入的最低标准 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref34">34</xref>]，且在大量的研究中认可超过10 mm的骨厚度可以安全地进行后续种植修复手术，相关文献报道成年人腓骨宽度平均为10.4~16 mm，因此10~12 mm范围内的植体均适用于FFF。而对于植体直径的选择，国外学者研究后报道认为安全范围为3.75~4.8 mm。在另一项相关研究中，研究人员发现对于术后需放疗治疗患者，短种植体较10 mm及以上的植体有更高的种植失败率 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref26">26</xref>]。此外，Ramin等学者对临床常见的5个商用种植系统(Biomet 3i, Nobel Biocare, Astra tech, Straumann及Ankylos)在FFF中行种植修复的安全性及相容性进行了研究分析 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref34">34</xref>]，各种植系统均有令人满意的表现，未提示显著疗效差异，而相对来说更粗糙化的表面处理可能会获得更好的初期稳定性 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref26">26</xref>]。而近期Edoardo等进行研究发现在传统钛种植体基础上，使用仿骨小梁多孔结构钽涂层表面处理的种植系统(porous tantalum trabecular metal (PTTM)-enhanced titanium dental implants)较常规种植系统有助于增强植体稳定性，减少术后骨吸收 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref35">35</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref36">36</xref>]。</p><p>因此，根据患者个体差异，选择安全范围内的植体直径及长度，合理的表面处理方式，在FFF联合种植治疗修复过程中均可获得不错的疗效。</p></sec><sec id="s7_4"><title>3.4. 植体数量与位置的选择</title><p>Kumar等人在一系列的研究中发现，2个植体支持的覆盖义齿较4个植体支持的覆盖义齿具有更多的边缘骨吸收，但均处于可以接受的范围内，而两者间植体周围软组织及患者自身满意度则均无明显统计学差异。而当出现术后种植失败时，拆除失败种植体后4个植体支持的覆盖义齿修复仍可继续行使相应功能 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref37">37</xref>]。</p><p>Stavan等提出，每2 cm的腓骨段中最多可植入2枚种植体，而植体具体植入位置的要求与正常牙槽骨基本相同，植体之间至少相距3 mm，与腓骨段连接点之间距离应不少于3 mm，颊舌侧距离腓骨皮质板应不少于0.5 mm，且即使使用角度基台，植体的长轴角度偏差也应控制在15˚以内 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref11">11</xref>]。腓骨的种植最小及最大扭矩分别为20 Ncm和45 Ncm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref38">38</xref>]。</p></sec><sec id="s7_5"><title>3.5. 植体周围组织管理</title><p>种植体周围组织是影响种植成功率的主要因素之一。种植体的稳定性与植体体部周围硬组织密切相关，而术后患者口腔功能的改善及术后种植体周围炎的预防，则与植体颈部软组织密不可分。</p><p>相较于正常牙槽骨组织，腓骨组织具有更多的皮质骨部分，在可以获得更好初期稳定性的同时，也缺乏正常牙槽骨的弹性，故偶有报道在植体植入过程中，腓骨组织出现骨开裂现象。Fatih Cabbar等建议在常规种植终末钻完成扩孔后二次钻入，并且尽可能通过穿双层皮质骨甚至三层皮质骨以减少应力延伸来降低骨开裂风险并增大植体稳定性，不过该观点仍需进一步实验来证实 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref20">20</xref>]。</p><p>与FFF相连的皮瓣，通常用来修复颌面部软组织缺损部分，不但可以更好保护移植腓骨组织，也可以有效恢复颊部、前庭沟及口底形态与功能。行同期种植手术时，应尽可能通过皮岛修复其他软组织缺损而保留原有牙龈组织，若延期手术或无法保留牙龈组织，皮瓣也可作为植体周围软组织使用。同时，在延期种植手术中，需注意切口的设计要避开皮瓣的穿支血管，在腓骨暴露后，也应该尽可能少的进行骨膜的剥离保证FFF的充足血供。</p><p>但迄今为止已有多篇报道提示FFF带有的游离皮瓣组织作为植体周围软组织时，由于皮下组织较多，质地松散，术后更容易发生种植体周围粘膜炎 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref31">31</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref39">39</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref40">40</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref41">41</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref42">42</xref>]。由于腭结缔组织瓣移植可以提供类似于牙龈组织的角化粘膜组织，能有效减少植体周围的边缘骨吸收和种植体周围炎的发生率，此技术已逐渐被常规应用于临床 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref40">40</xref>]。Chang等在研究中发现功能性负载后，腭结缔组织瓣瓣移植患者的植体边缘骨吸收平均值约为0.5 mm，明显少于未行或行其他软组织管理治疗的患者 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref40">40</xref>]。而Sozzi等学者则不推荐常规行腭结缔组织瓣移植，更多应采用修整薄化皮瓣皮下组织，并行前庭沟成形术 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref43">43</xref>]。而为了形成足够的前庭沟空间，使后续义齿修复不受干扰，移植腓骨上缘距重建板上缘应有至少5 mm的距离 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref11">11</xref>]，Kumar等人也于近年提出一种新的骨膜下剥离后义齿引导上皮再生技术(Sub-periosteal dissection and Denture Guided Epithelial Regeneration, SD-DGER) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref41">41</xref>]，可以有效促进植体周围软组织产生角化上皮，减少植体周围炎的发生，并且Koch等基于CAD/CAM技术，使用杆卡式覆盖义齿辅助确定腓骨段重建形态及位置，且确保前庭深度得以保留，能获得更好的软组织形态恢复 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref25">25</xref>]。</p></sec><sec id="s7_6"><title>3.6. 上部修复方式选择</title><p>种植修复时常见的修复方式包括覆盖义齿修复及固定义齿修复，固定义齿又主要分为粘接固位式与螺丝固位式。</p><p>Bodard等认为从美学改善角度来看，种植支持的覆盖义齿要优于螺丝固位或粘接固位的固定义齿 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref7">7</xref>]。Kumar等也认可球帽状附着体可以明显减少传递给植体的咬合力，需要的植体更少，也可以更方便的进行术后的口腔软硬组织检查 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref39">39</xref>]。而对于术后行放疗治疗的患者，Ernst认为由于球帽状附着体连接的种植覆盖义齿在设计时需要更多的粘膜支持，更容易出现放疗后的严重粘膜炎症等并发症，不应作为首选修复方式，可适当选择如杆卡式附着体连接减少义齿在使用过程中的微动并克服植体植入轴向上的误差 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref42">42</xref>]。固定义齿修复在远期自洁及维护上要求更高，但在修复戴牙时可通过螺丝就位孔道设计补偿植体间共同就位道角度的偏差 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref11">11</xref>]。</p></sec></sec><sec id="s8"><title>4. 修复成功率及临床实际应用</title><p>血管化FFF移植联合种植修复伴有牙列缺损的大面积颌面部骨缺损的成功率已被广泛证实。相关文献报道的FFF术后5年存活率在92%~97%之间，而10年存活率也有79.9% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref2">2</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref7">7</xref>]。而骨组织瓣中的植体存活率可达到84%~99%，最终修复成功率也从42.9%~98%不等 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref7">7</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref21">21</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref38">38</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref44">44</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref45">45</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref46">46</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref47">47</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref48">48</xref>]。影响最终种植修复成功的因素除去前述因素外仍有很多，比如不同性别，不同个体之间腓骨的质与量存在显著差异 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref9">9</xref>]，腓骨瓣修复骨缺损的位置 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref42">42</xref>]，患者自身咬合关系及卫生习惯等密切相关。</p><p>而在临床实际应用中，为了修复下颌骨缺损患者颌面部的外形，往往腓骨段需要与患者下颌骨的底端对齐，而腓骨的解剖特点导致了往往重建后牙槽嵴的垂直高度无法恢复，往往仍需要通过如重叠双管移植、牵张成骨、长基台修复体等手段弥补。而对于长段的下颌骨缺损，双管移植往往受限于腓骨的可取长度而无法实施，牵张成骨也由于腓骨的骨髓解剖特性并非是最佳选项，Shen等学者提出根据植体修复需要于高位固定单管式腓骨，而通过一块平齐下颌骨下缘的低位重建钛板恢复面部外形 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref49">49</xref>]，但由于放疗后容易出现钛板暴露等并发症，该方法仅适用于无需放疗患者。也有学者倾向于FFF成活并愈合良好后于种植位点处再次手术行非血管化髂骨移植 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref50">50</xref>]，髂骨移植可以更好的提供种植所需的垂直骨高度，也可以减少单管式腓骨中植体植入潜在的骨折风险，但非血管化的髂骨术后吸收较多，且完成整体修复的时间将明显延长，均需在手术方案设计时纳入考量。</p><p>此外，恶性肿瘤并不是骨组织瓣移植合并种植修复牙列缺损的绝对禁忌证 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref43">43</xref>]，FFF重建及种植修复后患者的生活质量会有明显的提高 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref51">51</xref>]，而且，Sozzi认为对于一些恶性肿瘤的患者来说，往往会因为患者术后的心理创伤及生活质量期待的改变，而拒绝后续额外的手术及其他重建修复手段，因此在设计方案时，重建及修复应该被纳入主要治疗计划中，而且对于非肿瘤患者及预后良好的患者，应该尽可能的同期种植 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref43">43</xref>] (图1)。另外在放射治疗相关患者的种植时机及成功率方面目前仍争议较大，除前述文献提出的放疗后延期种植修复外，多篇文献中报道放疗与否，及放疗与种植修复的时间关系是种植体的存活率及修复的重要影响因素，但无统计学上的显著差异，反而对于植体植入上颌或下颌的位置上存在显著差异 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref42">42</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref52">52</xref>]。这可能是因为上颌骨本身骨质较疏松，血管较丰富，放疗后血供变化较下颌骨改变更明显。且对于放疗后出现并发症的患者，接受高压氧辅助治疗有效，但同样差异不显著，而且常观察到更高的种植失败率，这可能是因为需要高压氧缓解治疗并发症的患者接受的放射剂量更大，对实际临床工作同样指导意义不强，需要更大样本量的研究进一步验证 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref26">26</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref53">53</xref>] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="hanspub.42464-ref54">54</xref>]。</p><p>图1. 手术流程设计及时间参考，仅针对无需术后辅助放射治疗情况讨论</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>5. 总结</title><p>使用游离血管化腓骨瓣(FFF)合并种植修复伴牙列缺损的颌面部骨缺损在临床上的探索，更常见的是回顾性研究，缺少更多更有意义的病例数据对比，更为循证的临床指南的缺失也使得该手段在临床工作中无法被普及推广，但目前来看仍是一个较为可靠且长远的选择，可以有效的改善患者的颜面部外形，咀嚼与发音的功能，术后生活质量及中长期的心理卫生状态。根据实际情况掌握手术的适应证与禁忌证，合理应用日益成熟的计算机辅助技术，缜密的治疗方案设计，优秀的外科及修复团队间的合作，和术后长期的随访及维护，对于最终修复的成功和长期稳定都至关重要。</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>文章引用</title><p>孙一航,刘雁鸣. 种植导向的血管化腓骨肌皮瓣移植在颌面部骨缺损重建修复中的临床应用Clinical Application of Vascularized Fibula Free Flap Transplantation Combined with Implantation in Reconstruction and Repair of Maxillofacial Bone Defect[J]. 临床医学进展, 2021, 11(05): 2204-2213. https://doi.org/10.12677/ACM.2021.115317</p></sec><sec id="s11"><title>参考文献</title></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">胡永杰, 曲行舟, 郑家伟, 等. 游离组织瓣在口腔颌面-头颈肿瘤缺损修复中的应用: 2549例临床分析[J]. 中国口腔颌面外科杂志, 2007, 5(5): 335-359.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">张陈平, 张志愿, 邱蔚六, 等. 口腔颌面部缺损的修复重建——1973例临床分析[J]. 中国修复重建外科杂志, 2005, 19(10): 773-776.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wilkman, T., Apajalahti, S., Wilkman, E., et al. (2017) A Comparison of Bone Resorption over Time: An Analysis of the Free Scapular, Iliac Crest, and Fibular Microvascular Flaps in Mandibular Reconstruction. Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, 75, 616-621. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joms.2016.09.009</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">张志愿, 等. 口腔颌面外科学[M]. 第7版. 北京: 人民卫生出版社, 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">竺涵光, 张陈平, 孙坚, 等. 腓骨肌皮瓣重建下颌骨的方法和经验[J]. 口腔颌面外科杂志, 2003(2): 158-161.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">王卫红, 刘宗良, 邹智荣, 等. 腓骨瓣的解剖学研究[J]. 国际口腔医学杂志, 2011, 38(5): 509-510+14.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bodard, A.G., Salino, S., Desoutter, A., et al. (2015) Assessment of Functional Improvement with Implant-Supported Prosthetic Rehabilitation after Mandibular Reconstruction with a Microvascular Free Fibula Flap: A Study of 25 Patients. Journal of Prosthetic Dentistry, 113, 140-145. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.prosdent.2014.08.005</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Al Deek, N.F., Kao, H.K. and Wei, F.C. (2018) The Fibula Osteoseptocutaneous Flap: Concise Review, Goal-Oriented Surgical Technique, and Tips and Tricks. Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, 142, 913e-923e.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/PRS.0000000000005065</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ide, Y., Matsunaga, S., Harris, J., et al. (2015) Anatomical Examination of the Fibula: Digital Imaging Study for Osseointegrated Implant Installation. Journal of Otolaryngology—Head &amp; Neck Surgery, 44, Article No. 1.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/s40463-015-0055-9</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Brown, J.S., Lowe, D., Kanatas, A., et al. (2017) Mandibular Reconstruction with Vascularised Bone Flaps: A Systematic Review over 25 Years. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, 55, 113-126.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjoms.2016.12.010</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Patel, S.Y., Kim, D.D. and Ghali, G.E. (2019) Maxillofacial Reconstruction Using Vascularized Fibula Free Flaps and Endosseous Implants. Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery Clinics of North America, 31, 259-284.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.coms.2018.12.005</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ch’ng, S., Skoracki, R.J., Selber, J.C., et al. (2016) Osseointegrated Implant-Based Dental Rehabilitation in Head and Neck Reconstruction Patients. Head Neck, 38, E321-E327. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.23993</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kniha, K., Mohlhenrich, S.C., Foldenauer, A.C., et al. (2017) Evaluation of Bone Resorption in Fibula and Deep Circumflex Iliac Artery Flaps Following Dental Implantation: A Three-Year Follow-Up Study. Journal of Cranio-Maxil- lofacial Surgery, 45, 474-478. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcms.2017.01.014</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cebrian-Carretero, J.L., Guinales-Diaz, D.E., Cevallos, J., Sobrino, J.A., et al. (2014) Predictable Dental Rehabilitation in Maxillomandibular Reconstruction with Free Flaps. The Role of Implant Guided Surgery. Medicina Oral, Patologia Oral, Cirugia Bucal, 19, e605-e611. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.4317/medoral.19116</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rana, M., Chin, S.J., Muecke, T., et al. (2017) Increasing the Accuracy of Mandibular Reconstruction with Free Fibula Flaps Using Functionalized Selective Laser-Melted Patient-Specific Implants: A Retrospective Multicenter Analysis. Journal of Cranio-Maxillofacial Surgery, 45, 1212-1219. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcms.2017.04.003</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Schepers, R.H., Raghoebar, G.M., Vissink, A., et al. (2015) Accuracy of Fibula Reconstruction Using Patient-Specific CAD/CAM Reconstruction Plates and Dental Implants: A New Modality for Functional Reconstruction of Mandibular Defects. Journal of Cranio-Maxillofacial Surgery, 43, 649-657. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcms.2015.03.015</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chuka, R., Abdullah, W., Rieger, J., et al. (2017) Implant Utilization and Time to Prosthetic Rehabilitation in Conventional and Advanced Fibular Free Flap Reconstruction of the Maxilla and Mandible. The International Journal of Prosthodontics, 30, 289-294. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.11607/ijp.5161</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">余丹, 黄建瑶, 于长洋, 等. 咬合引导下改良性颌骨功能重建的临床应用及精度分析[J]. 中国修复重建外科杂志, 2020, 34(11): 1410-1416.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">克热木·阿巴司, 王成刚, 尹小朋, 等. 数字化设计联合3D打印技术在下颌骨成釉细胞瘤术后骨缺损修复的应用[J]. 临床口腔医学杂志, 2020, 36(4): 211-214.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Cabbar, F., Durmus, F.N., Sacak, B., et al. (2018) Implant Stability Outcomes after Immediate and Delayed Revascularized Free Fibula Flaps: A Preliminary Comparative Study. The International Journal of Oral &amp; Maxillofacial Implants, 33, 1368-1373. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.11607/jomi.6725</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Menapace, D.C., Van Abel, K.M., Jackson, R.S., et al. (2018) Primary vs Secondary Endosseous Implantation after Fibular Free Tissue Reconstruction of the Mandible for Osteoradionecrosis. JAMA Facial Plastic Surgery, 20, 401-408.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1001/jamafacial.2018.0263</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">李明, 邱憬, 邢树忠, 等. 折叠腓骨肌皮瓣同期牙种植修复下颌骨缺损: 即刻种植延期修复的临床应用[J]. 南京医科大学学报(自然科学版), 2015, 35(9): 1287-1290.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sandoval, M.L., Rosen, E.B., Robert, A.J., et al. (2020) Immediate Dental Implants in Fibula Free Flaps to Reconstruct the Mandible: A Pilot Study of the Short-Term Effects on Radiotherapy for Patients with Head and Neck Cancer. Clinical Implant Dentistry and Related Research, 22, 91-95. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/cid.12870</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Jackson, R.S., Price, D.L., Arce, K., et al. (2016) Evaluation of Clinical Outcomes of Osseointegrated Dental Implantation of Fibula Free Flaps for Mandibular Reconstruction. JAMA Facial Plastic Surgery, 18, 201-206.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1001/jamafacial.2015.2271</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Koch, F.P., Gotze, E., Kumar, V.V., et al. (2015) A Bar-Retained Overdenture as an External Fixator Device in a Three-Dimensional CAD/CAM-Based Surgical Reconstruction of the Mandible. Journal of Cranio-Maxillofacial Surgery, 43, 1447-1451. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcms.2015.06.019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Smith Nobrega, A., Santiago, J.F., De Faria Almeida, D.A., et al. (2016) Irradiated Patients and Survival Rate of Dental Implants: A Systematic Review and Meta-Analysis. Journal of Prosthetic Dentistry, 116, 858-866.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.prosdent.2016.04.025</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pauchet, D., Pigot, J.L., Chabolle, F., et al. (2018) Prefabricated Fibula Free Flap with Dental Implants for Mandibular Reconstruction. European Annals of Oto-Rhino-Laryngology, Head and Neck Diseases, 135, 279-282.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.anorl.2018.02.001</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rohner, D., Bucher, P. and Hammer, B. (2013) Prefabricated Fibular Flaps for Reconstruction of Defects of the Maxillofacial Skeleton: Planning, Technique, and Long-Term Experience. The International Journal of Oral &amp; Maxillofacial Implants, 28, e221-e229. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.11607/jomi.te01</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Freudlsperger, C., Bodem, J.P., Engel, E., et al. (2014) Mandibular Reconstruction with a Prefabricated Free Vascularized Fibula and Implant-Supported Prosthesis Based on Fully Three-Dimensional Virtual Planning. Journal of Craniofacial Surgery, 25, 980-982. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/SCS.0000000000000551</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pompa, G., Saccucci, M., DI Carlo, G., et al. (2015) Survival of Dental Implants in Patients with Oral Cancer Treated by Surgery and Radiotherapy: A Retrospective Study. BMC Oral Health, 15, 5.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/1472-6831-15-5</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sammartino, G., Marenzi, G., Cioffi, I., et al. (2011) Implant Therapy in Irradiated Patients. Journal of Craniofacial Surgery, 22, 443-445. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/SCS.0b013e318207b59b</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Korfage, A., Raghoebar, G.M., Slater, J.J., et al. (2014) Overdentures on Primary Mandibular Implants in Patients with Oral Cancer: A Follow-Up Study over 14 Years. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, 52, 798-805.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjoms.2014.05.013</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Levine, J.P., Bae, J.S., Soares, M., et al. (2013) Jaw in a Day: Total Maxillofacial Reconstruction Using Digital Technology. Plastic and Reconstructive Surgery, 131, 1386-1391. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/PRS.0b013e31828bd8d0</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Carbiner, R., Jerjes, W., Shakib, K., et al. (2012) Analysis of the Compatibility of Dental Implant Systems in Fibula Free Flap Reconstruction. Head &amp; Neck Oncology, 4, 37. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/1758-3284-4-37</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Brauner, E., DI Carlo, S., Ciolfi, A., et al. (2019) Use of Porous Implants for the Prosthetic Rehabilitation of Fibula Free Flap Reconstructed Patients. Journal of Craniofacial Surgery, 30, 1163-1169.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/SCS.0000000000005218</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Brauner, E., Guarino, G., Jamshir, S., et al. (2015) Evaluation of Highly Porous Dental Implants in Postablative Oral and Maxillofacial Cancer Patients: A Prospective Pilot Clinical Case Series Report. Implant Dentistry, 24, 631-637.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/ID.0000000000000295</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kumar, V.V., Ebenezer, S., Kammerer, P.W., et al. (2016) Implants in Free Fibula Flap Supporting Dental Rehabilitation—Implant and Peri-Implant Related Outcomes of a Randomized Clinical Trial. Journal of Cranio-Maxillofacial Surgery, 44, 1849-1858. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcms.2016.08.023</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Maluf, P.S., Ching, A.W., Angeletti, P., et al. (2015) Insertion Torque of Dental Implants after Microvascular Fibular Grafting. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, 53, 647-649. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjoms.2015.03.016</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kumar, V.V., Jacob, P.C., Ebenezer, S., et al. (2016) Implant Supported Dental Rehabilitation Following Segmental Mandibular Reconstruction-Quality of Life Outcomes of a Prospective Randomized Trial. Journal of Cranio-Maxillofacial Surgery, 44, 800-810. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcms.2016.04.013</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chang, Y.M., Pan, Y.H., Shen, Y.F., et al. (2016) Success of Dental Implants in Vascularised Fibular Osteoseptocutaneous Flaps Used as Onlay Grafts after Marginal Mandibulectomy. British Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, 54, 1090-1094. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjoms.2016.07.006</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kumar, V.V., Jacob, P.C. and Kuriakose, M.A. (2016) Sub-Periosteal Dissection with Denture-Guided Epithelial Regeneration: A Novel Method for Peri-Implant Soft Tissue Management in Reconstructed Mandibles. Journal of Maxillofacial and Oral Surgery, 15, 449-455. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s12663-015-0854-6</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ernst, N., Sachse, C., Raguse, J.D., et al. (2016) Changes in Peri-Implant Bone Level and Effect of Potential Influential Factors on Dental Implants in Irradiated and Nonirradiated Patients Following Multimodal Therapy Due to Head and Neck Cancer: A Retrospective Study. Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, 74, 1965-1973.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joms.2016.06.005</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Sozzi, D., Novelli, G., Silva, R., et al. (2017) Implant Rehabilitation in Fibula-Free Flap Reconstruction: A Retrospective Study of Cases at 1-18 Years Following Surgery. Journal of Cranio-Maxillofacial Surgery, 45, 1655-1661.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcms.2017.06.021</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Meloni, S.M., Tallarico, M., De Riu, G., et al. (2015) Guided Implant Surgery after Free-Flap Reconstruction: Four- Year Results from a Prospective Clinical Trial. Journal of Cranio-Maxillofacial Surgery, 43, 1348-1355.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcms.2015.06.046</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Burgess, M., Leung, M., Chellapah, A., et al. (2017) Osseointegrated Implants into a Variety of Composite Free Flaps: A Comparative Analysis. Head Neck, 39, 443-447. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.24609</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wijbenga, J.G., Schepers, R.H., Werker, P.M., et al. (2016) A Systematic Review of Functional Outcome and Quality of Life Following Reconstruction of Maxillofacial Defects Using Vascularized Free Fibula Flaps and Dental Rehabilitation Reveals Poor Data Quality. Journal of Plastic, Reconstructive &amp; Aesthetic Surgery, 69, 1024-1036.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjps.2016.05.003</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Yoon, H.I. (2016) Prosthetic Rehabilitation after Fibular Free Flap Surgery of Mandibular Defects in a Patient with Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma. Journal of Craniofacial Surgery, 27, e685-e688.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/SCS.0000000000002761</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Alberga, J.M., Vosselman, N., Korfage, A., et al. (2021) What Is the Optimal Timing for Implant Placement in Oral Cancer Patients? A Scoping Literature Review. Oral Diseases, 27, 94-110. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/odi.13312</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Shen, Y.F., Rodriguez, E.D., Wei, F.C., et al. (2015) Aesthetic and Functional Mandibular Reconstruction with Immediate Dental Implants in a Free Fibular Flap and a Low-Profile Reconstruction Plate: Five-Year Follow-Up. Annals of Plastic Surgery, 74, 442-446. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1097/SAP.0b013e3182a0dedf</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Hakim, S.G., Kimmerle, H., Trenkle, T., et al. (2015) Masticatory Rehabilitation Following Upper and Lower Jaw Reconstruction Using Vascularised Free Fibula Flap and Enossal Implants-19 Years of Experience with a Comprehensive Concept. Clinical Oral Investigations, 19, 525-534. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s00784-014-1247-9</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Jacobsen, H.C., Wahnschaff, F., Trenkle, T., et al. (2016) Oral Rehabilitation with Dental Implants and Quality of Life Following Mandibular Reconstruction with Free Fibular Flap. Clinical Oral Investigations, 20, 187-192.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s00784-015-1487-3</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Zen Filho, E.V., Tolentino Ede, S. and Santos, P.S. (2016) Viability of Dental Implants in Head and Neck Irradiated Patients: A Systematic Review. Head Neck, 38, E2229-E2240. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.24098</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Curi, M.M., Condezo, A.F.B., Ribeiro, K., et al. (2018) Long-Term Success of Dental Implants in Patients with Head and Neck Cancer after Radiation Therapy. International Journal of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery, 47, 783-788.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijom.2018.01.012</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.42464-ref54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Chrcanovic, B.R., Albrektsson, T. and Wennerberg, A. (2016) Dental Implants in Irradiated versus Nonirradiated Patients: A Meta-Analysis. Head Neck, 38, 448-481. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/hed.23875</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>