<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "http://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/3.0/journalpublishing3.dtd"><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="3.0" xml:lang="en" article-type="research article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Advances in Psychology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2160-7273</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Scientific Research Publishing</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12677/AP.2021.116175</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">AP-43515</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>AP20210600000_19981348.pdf</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>人文社科</subject><subject> 合作期刊</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
 
 
  抑郁个体积极情绪缺陷的原因：动机对习惯性情绪调节策略的影响
  Causes of Positive Emotion Deficits in Depressed Individuals: The Influence of Motivation on Habitual Emotion Regulation Strategies
 
</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>丁</surname><given-names>鹏浩</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>井</surname><given-names>玉汝</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" xlink:type="simple"><name name-style="western"><surname>佟</surname><given-names>月华</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff2"><addr-line>济南大学，教育与心理科学学院，山东 济南</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>null</addr-line></aff><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>06</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>06</issue><fpage>1565</fpage><lpage>1575</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; Copyright  2014 by authors and Scientific Research Publishing Inc. </copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY). http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
 
 
  抑郁症的主要特征之一是负性情绪增加，积极情绪减少。抑郁个体的积极情绪缺陷与其习惯性情绪调节策略的使用有关，相较于正常个体，抑郁个体会更多地使用降低积极情绪的调节策略和更少地使用提高积极情绪的调节策略，这种策略使用失调受到多种动机驱动情绪偏向的影响。本文综合了情绪的过程模型和工具模型的视角，为探究抑郁个体的积极情绪缺陷的成因和抑郁症的干预提供了一个新的方向。
   Depression is characterized by increased levels of negative affect and decreased levels of positive affect. Positive emotion deficits in depression are associated with habitual use of emotion regulation strategies. Depressive individuals more frequently engage in strategies that serve to down-regulate positive emotion and less frequently use strategies that serve to up-regulate positive emotion relative to healthy individuals. The dysfunction in habitual emotion regulation strategy use is affected by emotional preference driven by multiple motivations. The paper synthesizes the perspectives of process model and tool model of emotion, and provides a new direction for exploring the causes of positive emotion deficits in depression and the intervention of depression.
 
</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>抑郁症，积极情绪，情绪调节，动机, Depression</kwd><kwd> Positive Emotion</kwd><kwd> Emotion Regulation</kwd><kwd> Motivation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>摘要</title><p>抑郁症的主要特征之一是负性情绪增加，积极情绪减少。抑郁个体的积极情绪缺陷与其习惯性情绪调节策略的使用有关，相较于正常个体，抑郁个体会更多地使用降低积极情绪的调节策略和更少地使用提高积极情绪的调节策略，这种策略使用失调受到多种动机驱动情绪偏向的影响。本文综合了情绪的过程模型和工具模型的视角，为探究抑郁个体的积极情绪缺陷的成因和抑郁症的干预提供了一个新的方向。</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>关键词</title><p>抑郁症，积极情绪，情绪调节，动机</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Causes of Positive Emotion Deficits in Depressed Individuals: The Influence of Motivation on Habitual Emotion Regulation Strategies<sup> </sup></title><p>Penghao Ding<sup>*</sup>, Yuru Jing, Yuehua Tong<sup>#</sup></p><p>School of Education and Psychology, University of Jinan, Jinan Shandong</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/27-1132338x4_hanspub.png" /></p><p>Received: May 24<sup>th</sup>, 2021; accepted: Jun. 21<sup>st</sup>, 2021; published: Jun. 28<sup>th</sup>, 2021</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/27-1132338x6_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>Depression is characterized by increased levels of negative affect and decreased levels of positive affect. Positive emotion deficits in depression are associated with habitual use of emotion regulation strategies. Depressive individuals more frequently engage in strategies that serve to down-regulate positive emotion and less frequently use strategies that serve to up-regulate positive emotion relative to healthy individuals. The dysfunction in habitual emotion regulation strategy use is affected by emotional preference driven by multiple motivations. The paper synthesizes the perspectives of process model and tool model of emotion, and provides a new direction for exploring the causes of positive emotion deficits in depression and the intervention of depression.</p><p>Keywords:Depression, Positive Emotion, Emotion Regulation, Motivation</p><disp-formula id="hanspub.43515-formula44"><graphic xlink:href="//html.hanspub.org/file/27-1132338x7_hanspub.png"  xlink:type="simple"/></disp-formula><p>Copyright &#169; 2021 by author(s) and Hans Publishers Inc.</p><p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution International License (CC BY 4.0).</p><p>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</p><p><img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/27-1132338x8_hanspub.png" /> <img src="//html.hanspub.org/file/27-1132338x9_hanspub.png" /></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>1. 引言</title><p>抑郁症是一种以心境低落和快感缺失为核心症状的情绪调节障碍，主要表现为持续性的消极情绪和积极情绪的缺失(American Psychiatric Association, 2013)。当前抑郁症已成为全球首要的公众心理健康问题(Ferrari et al., 2013)。抑郁症的终生患病率高达6.8%，其中重度抑郁的终生患病率为3.4% (Huang et al., 2019)。以往研究大多关注消极情绪对抑郁症的影响(Kube et al., 2021; Rockman, 2020)，而较少关注抑郁症患者的积极情绪缺陷，即积极情绪明显减少，且情绪持续时间较短。但是有研究发现，低积极情绪与抑郁程度的加重有关(Vrieze et al., 2013)，并且积极情绪障碍可以预测抑郁症治疗中的不良反应(Forbes et al., 2010; McMakin et al., 2012)。研究表明，抑郁个体对积极刺激的积极情绪反应减少，反应适应性降低(Forbes et al., 2005; Henriques &amp; Davidson, 2000; Rottenberg et al, 2002)。而有研究显示，抑郁个体的积极情绪障碍与其习惯性情绪调节策略有关(Domes et al., 2010; Heller et al., 2009; Carthy et al., 2010; Silvers et al., 2012; Liu &amp; Thompson, 2017; Rottenberg, 2017)。</p><p>习惯性情绪调节策略是指个体频繁使用的情绪调节策略(Gross, 2014)。研究发现，相对于非抑郁个体，抑郁个体习惯性情绪调节策略的适应性、功能性和灵活性更低(Campbell-Sills et al., 2006; Garnefski, &amp;Kraaij, 2006; Kashdan &amp; Rottenberg, 2010)。Gross (2014)的情绪调节过程模型对情抑郁个体的习惯性调节策略的特点进行了分析，却不能解释其形成的原因。即抑郁个体为什么会偏向使用某一种调节策略，而不使用其他的调节策略，其内在的心理机制是什么？而关于这一问题，Tamir (2016)从动机角度提出的情绪调节工具模型或许可以给出答案。</p><p>因此，本文首先以情绪调节的过程模型为参考框架，系统阐明抑郁个体的习惯性情绪调节策略特点，并从情绪调节工具模型的视角出发，从动机和情绪偏向的角度解释其形成的原因，综合两种模型，为了解抑郁个体积极情绪缺陷提供一个新的研究视角，并提出一种抑郁症的新的干预方向。</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>2. 抑郁个体的习惯性情绪调节策略</title><p>Gross (2014)的过程模型认为情绪调节策略的形成发生于情绪产生的一系列阶段中，根据不同情绪调节策略在情绪产生过程中发生主要作用的时间不同，Gross (2014)将情绪调节分为五个阶段：情境选择、情境修正、注意分配、认知改变和反应调整。在第一阶段(情境选择)，个体判断某种情境可能会带来哪些影响，进而选择趋近还是回避该情境(朱传林等人，2016)。在第二阶段(情境修正)，当情境无法被选择时，个体可以对这个情境进行改变来影响情绪。例如，将当你正在完成作业时，隔壁邻居大吵大闹，你可以去劝说邻居降低音量。第三阶段是注意分配，个体可以将注意力从刺激上转移以降低情绪反应，也可以分配更多的注意力以提高情绪反应。第四阶段是认知改变，指个体改变对环境的认知，重新评价刺激来改变情绪。例如，将一个人没有说“你好”解释为一种疏忽而不是刻意回避，就会产生较少的负面情绪。第五个阶段是反应调整，指个体形成特定的情绪后，对该情绪所诱发的主观心理感受、生理体验和行为表现进行干预，进而改变情绪的强弱或性质(孟昭兰，2005)。通过检索文献发现，当前关于抑郁个体在情景修正阶段的情绪调节策略的研究相对较少，因此本文将从情境选择、注意分配、认知改变和反应调整四个阶段介绍抑郁个体的习惯性情绪调节策略。</p><sec id="s6_1"><title>2.1. 抑郁个体在情境选择阶段的习惯性情绪调节策略</title><p>抑郁症的产生与选择难与引发积极情绪的情境有关。研究发现，抑郁和非抑郁个体在选择情绪诱发刺激时有显著差异，具体而言，抑郁个体比非抑郁个体更少的选择观看快乐的诱导图像，并且抑郁个体对快乐的偏好评分显著低于非抑郁个体(Millgram et al., 2015)。李红等人(2019)让抑郁组和健康控制组被试报告他们在日常中想要体验的快乐和悲伤程度，结果发现，对于快乐情绪的偏好程度，抑郁倾向组显著小于健康控制组。这些研究表明，抑郁个体在选择情境时，对能引发积极情绪的情境选择低于非抑郁个体，这可能导致了抑郁个体的积极情绪水平低下。</p></sec><sec id="s6_2"><title>2.2. 抑郁个体在注意偏向阶段的习惯性情绪调节策略</title><p>有偏向的信息处理是抑郁症的一个重要特征，即抑郁个体存在明显的注意偏向，他们会更少地注意积极刺激，而较多地注意消极刺激(Ellis, Beevers, &amp; Wells, 2011; Joormann &amp; Gotlib, 2007)。研究发现当同时呈现几种刺激时，抑郁组被试比非抑郁组被试在注意积极刺激上所花费的时间更少(Kellough et al., 2008)。Tang等人(2019)在实验中向被试呈现由情绪(积极的、消极的)图片和中性图片组成的刺激，并追踪被试的眼动过程。结果发现正常组被试相较于中性的和消极图片，会花费更多的时间去注意积极图片，而有抑郁倾向的被试对所有类型的词汇的注意程度相同，这表明，有抑郁倾向的被试会压抑自己对积极图片的注意。此外，抑郁个体对积极图片的注意显著慢于消极图片。这些研究表明，抑郁个体对积极刺激具有明显的回避性，这种回避型性可能加剧了抑郁个体的低积极情绪水平。</p></sec><sec id="s6_3"><title>2.3. 抑郁个体在认知改变阶段的习惯性情绪调节策略</title><p>抑郁个体在使用认知改变策略时，会习惯性地将当前情境评价为消极情境而非积极情境(Mathews &amp; MacLeod, 2005)。这种低积极评价倾向在很多研究中得到验证。例如，Rude等人(2002)向被试呈现由六个词语组成的乱序语句，要求被试从中选择五个词语组成符合逻辑的句子，组成的句子可以是积极的，也可以是消极的。结果发现抑郁组被试将句子加工成积极的要显著少于加工成消极的。Everaert等人(2018)让被试对模糊信息进行解释，发现相较于低抑郁水平被试，高抑郁水平的被试对模糊信息的解释由消极向积极的转变率更低，但由积极向消极转变率不存在显著差异，这种低积极解释转变率可能导致了抑郁程度的加重。</p><p>此外，研究发现抑郁个体很少会对先前的解释做出积极重评。积极重评(reappraisal)是指个体在认知上以更积极的方式重新定义一个消极事件(Gross, 2014)。积极重评会增加个体的积极情绪，减少消极情绪(Gross &amp; John, 2003)。较高的积极解释偏向与更多使用积极重评有关，而积极解释偏向与抑郁程度存在负相关。相较于正常个体，重度抑郁症患者会更少做出积极重评(D’Avanzato et al., 2013)。</p></sec><sec id="s6_4"><title>2.4. 抑郁个体在反应调整阶段的习惯性情绪调节策略</title><p>抑郁症个体较少使用保持或提高积极情绪的调节策略(如积极反刍、品味)，但更多使用有可能减少积极情绪的调节策略(如压抑、表达抑制) (Carl et al., 2013; Werner-Seidler et al., 2013)。</p><sec id="s6_4_1"><title>2.4.1. 压抑和表达抑制</title><p>患有抑郁症的个体相较于正常个体更有可能采用压抑(dampening)的情绪调节策略(Eisner, Johnson, &amp; Carver, 2009; Feldman, Joormnn, &amp; Johnson, 2008; Werner-Seidler et al., 2013)。压抑是指通过减少积极情绪的强度和持续时间来诱发更多的消极情绪的过程(Feldman, Joormann, &amp; Johnso, 2008)。在这个过程中，抑郁会体验到更低的积极情绪。研究发现，对积极情绪的高抑制倾向与抑郁症状的加重有关，且有研究采用自我报告法和问卷法的方式对抑郁个体调节情绪的方式进行研究，结果表明有抑郁病史(当前或以往)的个体比没有病史的个体有更高的压抑积极情绪的倾向(Nelis, Holmes, &amp; Raes, 2015; Werner-Seidler et al., 2013)。压抑积极情绪可以前瞻性的预测抑郁症状的加重程度(Raes et al., 2012)。这表明压抑积极情绪可能不只是抑郁症的临床特征之一，也可能是导致抑郁症发生的一个危险因素。</p><p>与压抑相同，使用表达抑制(expressive suppression)来调节积极情绪会抑制个体的积极情绪体验(Kalokerinos, Greenaway, &amp; Denson, 2015)。表达抑制是指主动的隐藏由情绪体验诱发的内部情绪体验的外在表现(Gross, 2002)，例如高兴时隐藏笑容、悲伤时停止哭泣。Beblo等人(2012)采用情绪接受问卷(EAQ)对39名重度抑郁个体和41名健康个体情绪抑制和情绪恐惧情况进行了调查，结果显示重度抑郁症患者具有习惯性抑制积极和消极情绪的倾向。Aker, Harmer, &amp; Landr&#248; (2014)也发现，与没有重度抑郁病史的女性相比，患有重度抑郁的女性自我报告会更频繁的抑制积极情绪的表达。</p></sec><sec id="s6_4_2"><title>2.4.2. 积极反刍和品味</title><p>除了较多使用减少积极情绪的情绪调节策略，抑郁个体也会较少使用可以提高积极情绪的策略，例如积极反刍(positive rumination)和品味(savoring)。积极反刍是以积极的情感体验、积极的自我品质和良好的生活环境为核心的情感调节策略(Larsen &amp; Prizmic, 2004)。研究发现，当经常使用积极反刍策略时，积极刺激会更显著地预测积极情绪的增加和抑郁症状的减轻。(Li, Starr, &amp; Hershenberg, 2017)。Harding和Hudson等人(2014)以209名本科生为被试，使用问卷法对被试的积极情绪、抑郁程度和认知策略进行了为期八周的纵向调查研究，发现低水平的积极情绪与较少使用积极反刍有关，而且低积极情绪特质对抑郁症状的影响部分是由对低水平的积极反刍中介的。除此之外，在对儿童的研究中也发现，积极反刍与儿童的高抑郁症状有关(Gilbert et al., 2017)。</p><p>较少使用品味策略是导致抑郁症患者快感缺乏的原因之一(Joormann &amp; Stanton, 2016)。品味是指通过注意、欣赏和增强积极事件或感觉来维护、加强或延长最初的积极情绪体验(Bryant &amp; Veroff, 2017)，是最常见的用来维持和增加积极情绪的情绪调节策略(Heiy &amp; Cheavens, 2014; Liu &amp; Thompson, 2017)。Beblo等人(2012)的研究发现重度抑郁个体使用积极品味策略的次数明显少于正常个体。相较于难以预测或回忆积极事件，对当下的积极刺激的品味缺陷更能预测抑郁症状的发展(Carver &amp; Johnson, 2009)。</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s7"><title>3. 动机抑郁个体情绪偏向及其对习惯性情绪调节策略的影响</title><sec id="s7_1"><title>3.1. 情绪偏向对情绪调节策略的影响</title><p>情绪偏向是指个体渴望达到的情绪状态，即情绪调节目标(Tamir, 2009)，情绪调节的目的就是获得个体偏向的情绪状态(Gross, 2015; Mauss &amp; Tamir, 2014; Tamir, 2016)。Tamir (2016)提出的情绪调节工具模型认为个体的情绪偏向会影响情绪调节策略的选择，这一观点也得到了其他研究的支持，Millgram和Sheppes等人(2019)通过指导被试提高或降低消极情绪来操作情绪偏向，并且随后测量被试是否选择了反刍和分心的调节策略。结果显示当被要求提高消极情绪时，被试大多会选择使用反刍的调节策略，而在被要求提高消极情绪时，被试往往会选择使用分心的调节策略。</p></sec><sec id="s7_2"><title>3.2. 动机对抑郁个体情绪偏向的影响</title><p>情绪调节工具模型认为个体进行情绪调节是为了达到偏向的情绪状态，是受到动机的影响，不同的动机会使个体产生不同的情绪偏向，进而影响个体采用何种情绪调节策略，即消极情绪偏向会使个体更多的使用消极的情绪调节策略和更少的使用积极的情绪调解策略。该模型将个体进行情绪调节的动机分为两类，即享乐动机和工具动机。</p><p>追求享乐动机的个体通过增加即时快乐，来最大化快乐和最小化痛苦，从而获得情绪调节的直接益处，一旦获得偏向的情绪状态，享乐动机就得到了满足。但个体的行为并不只是以当下的快乐或痛苦为导向的，还取决于未来的目标情绪状态。当个体希望通过特定行为实现某种目标，进而达到偏向的情绪状态时，就会产生工具动机。工具动机旨在寻求未来快乐的最大化，获得情绪调节的潜在益处，这种动机会在获得期望的情绪状态后得到满足，包含行为动机、认知动机、社会动机、幸福动机以及额外动机。接下来，本文将从享乐动机和工具动机的角度，来解释抑郁症个体情绪偏向的特点及其产生的原因。</p><sec id="s7_2_1"><title>3.2.1. 享乐动机对抑郁个体情绪偏向的影响</title><p>享乐动机包括正享乐动机(Prohedonic)和负享乐动机(Contrahedonic)。正享乐动机旨在直接增加快乐或减少痛苦，以促进整体的快乐平衡。有研究表明个体最常报告的情绪调节行为是增加愉快的情绪或减少不愉快的情绪(Gross, Richards, &amp; John, 2006; Riediger et al., 2009)。</p><p>然而在一些特殊情况下，个体可能会减少即时快乐或增加即时痛苦，这就是负享乐动机。在情绪调节过程中，个体可能认为相对于更剧烈的疼痛，不太剧烈的疼痛可能是愉快的。因此，人们可能会更有动机去体验不太强烈的疼痛(Fredrickson, 2000)。研究表明，患有广泛性焦虑症的个体通常会保持焦虑，部分原因是他们认为这有助于他们避免更糟糕的恐惧体验(Borkovec, Alcaine, &amp; Behar, 2004)。抑郁个体可能为了避免因情绪波动的落差而产生更大的痛苦，而选择更少的去体验积极情绪，并继续维持消极情绪，即使维持消极情绪一样会带来一定程度的痛苦体验。</p></sec><sec id="s7_2_2"><title>3.2.2. 工具动机对抑郁个体情绪偏向的影响</title><p>个体的行为并不总是面向即时的快乐或痛苦，很多时候是面向未来的最大化快乐和最小化痛苦(Higgins, 2011)。工具动机旨在未来获得所期望的情绪状态，包括行为动机、认知动机、社会动机、幸福动机和额外动机。</p><p>1) 行为动机对抑郁个体情绪偏向的影响</p><p>抑郁个体的情绪行为动机表现为通过采用一些下调积极情绪的策略，来维持较低的积极情绪水平，以防止情绪失控。个体可以通过调节情绪来塑造和调节相应的认知和行为，进而优化自己的表现(Forbes, 2011; Higgins, 2011)，而抑郁个体通常认为自己很难维持积极情绪，也不会从积极情绪中获益，当抑郁个体体验到积极情绪时，认为自己可能会在这种频率较低、不熟悉的情绪状态中失去行为控制，从而对此产生恐惧感，因此会试图减少对积极情绪的体验，避免因体验积极情绪而产生行为失控，进而保证自己行为表现的稳定。这种情况在其他情绪障碍疾病中也同样存在，例如Goldstein和Chambless (1978)提出的“对恐惧的恐惧”这一概念，他们认为对恐惧的恐惧在惊恐障碍的病理学原因中扮演着一个重要的角色，这些个体对焦虑体验和在强烈的焦虑状态中可能失去控制的情况存在恐惧。所以被诊断为惊恐障碍的个体会寻求避免高焦虑水平和相应的生理激活状态。因此，患有重度抑郁的个体同样会希望减少对积极情绪的体验，因为他们害怕他们在积极情绪状态中可能会失控。</p><p>2) 认知动机对抑郁个体情绪偏向的影响</p><p>患有重度抑郁的个体可能会持有这样一种观点，即认为慢性悲伤和悲观思想是其自我意识的核心，并可能因此来寻求相应的情绪体验。与自我提升相同，自我验证也可以成为个体调节自身情绪的动机，自我评价较低的个体会更少的改变消极情绪状态(Wood et al., 2009)，并且更可能去寻求消极情绪状态，因为这更符合他们的日常情绪状态(Ford &amp; Tamir, 2014)。Curland等人(2020)通过网络的形式对227名有抑郁症状的个体进行干预调查，以了解抑郁症患者试图改善或不去改善自己情绪状态的原因，被试采用自由回答的方式报告是否选择尝试改变现状的原因和顾虑。调查结果显示抑郁身份(Depressed Identity)是阻碍抑郁个体尝试改善自身情绪状态的主要原因之一，患有重度抑郁症的个体会认为慢性的和/或长期的悲伤状态是他们个人身份的一部分，因此更偏向于保持消极情绪状态，并且更少去体验积极情绪。</p><p>3) 社会动机对抑郁个体情绪偏向的影响</p><p>社会动机是指人们可能会为获得某种期望的社会利益而被激励去体验某种特定的情绪状态(Fischer et al., 2004)。有研究表明个体在建立新的社会关系时，会更倾向于寻求和保持积极的情绪状态，因为人们认为积极的人更具社会吸引力，更易于建立新的和(或)良好的社会关系(Diener, Wolsic, &amp; Fujita, 1995)。</p><p>有研究发现，相较于正常个体，有抑郁倾向的个体会表现出更低的奖赏反应性和更高的拒绝敏感性(Goldstein et al., 2020; De Rubeis et al., 2017)。这种高拒绝敏感性高会使个体在面对潜在的拒绝时会体验到更多的负面情绪，且对积极情绪刺激的反应能力下降(Leng, Qian, &amp; Zhu, 2018; Setterfield et al., 2016)。特别是在社会领域，这种低反应性和高拒绝性可能会使个体更少的去主动寻求和享受社交活动(Pegg, Arfer, &amp; Kujawa, 2021)。Curland等人(2020)的研究结果显示，回避责任(Avoiding Responsibilities)也是抑郁个体不愿去尝试改善自身情绪状态的主要原因之一，回避责任被定义为不想参加活动或者希望远离人群，其代表性的想法是“我可以用抑郁来与别人保持距离或当作借口”。因此在社交动机驱动的情绪偏向方面，相较于正常个体，抑郁症个体可能会更倾向于保持消极情绪状态，而不是去努力寻求积极情绪状态。</p></sec><sec id="s7_2_3"><title>3.2.3. 额外动机对抑郁个体情绪偏向的影响</title><p>除了特定的目标动机，其他可以影响自我调节系统的变化和稳定的过程同样可以驱动情绪调节，例如惯性和习惯化。正如牛顿在第一运动定律中所定义的那样，惯性包括对变化的阻力。从心理学的角度来看，人们保持当前的状态可能并不是因为他们渴望这种状态，而仅仅是因为他们不想做出改变这种状态所需的努力。在情绪领域，这意味着无论当前的情感状态是可取的还是不可取的，人们可能仅仅因为抵触改变而保持某种情感状态(Kuppens, Allen, &amp; Sheeber, 2010)，即抑郁个体可能仅仅是熟悉和习惯消极情绪状态，而不愿去寻求和体验积极情绪状态。</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s8"><title>4. 总结与展望</title><p>综上所述，已有研究显示，相较于没有抑郁病史的个体，抑郁个体在情绪产生的各个阶段均存在习惯性情绪调节策略使用的缺陷，即会更多地使用下调–调节积极情绪的策略和更少地使用上调–调节积极情绪的策略。情绪调节策略的选择会受到情绪偏向的影响，抑郁个体会因行为、认知和社会等动机而选择消极的情绪调节目标，并产生消极情绪偏向，进而产生这种习惯性情绪调节策略使用的缺陷。情绪偏向和习惯情绪调节策略使用的整合为理解抑郁症的积极情绪缺陷提供了一个可能的整体框架，但现有研究仍存在一定的局限，未来研究可以考虑从以下方面着手。</p><p>第一，采用多种测量方法，更加客观和综合地探究抑郁个体情绪调节和情绪偏向的特点。以往关于抑郁症调节策略使用的研究中采用的多为整体的、回顾性的自我报告测量法，测量方法较为单一，这种方法很可能存在实验者效应和社会期许效应，进而影响研究结果的客观性和科学性。未来研究可以采用更加客观的测量方法。例如运用行为选择范式研究抑郁症个体的刺激选择；注意分配可以选用反应时和眼动追踪范式；解释过程可以选用反应时和ERP范式或者评估个体依据新信息对先前解释进行更新的能力；情绪偏向可以选用反应时任务(例如情绪–调整IAT)。整合多种测量方法测量每一个过程不仅可以避免任意单一方法的局限性，还可以对这些过程提供一个整体性的理解，可以让研究者更容易地确认抑郁症中积极情绪调节的障碍。</p><p>第二，探究抑郁个体情绪偏向与情绪调节策略选择的关系及其他可能的策略选择的影响因素。情绪偏向是影响抑郁个体选择何种调节策略的因素之一，但其对策略选择的影响程度如何仍有待进一步研究，目前有两种方法可探究这一问题，一是操作个体的情绪偏向，这可以通过控制社会语境来实现，例如Tamir和Ford (2009)的研究结果显示，当个体期望加入一个合作性的社会互动而不是对抗性时，个体会更多地报告偏向于选择体验积极情绪。未来研究可以尝试在控制社会语境的情况下评估抑郁个体积极情绪管理策略的使用，并对自发使用的情绪管理策略进行评估。二是利用生态顺势评估法(EMA)检验情绪偏向是否可以预测后续的情绪管理策略的使用。虽然不像实验操作可以直接验证因果关系，但建立明确的时间关系同样可以证明情绪偏向对情绪管理策略选择的影响。此外，探究其他可能影响抑郁个体情绪调节策略选择的因素(如情绪强度，文化差异等)也是未来一个重要的研究方向。</p><p>第三，现有关于抑郁症积极情绪缺陷的研究仅关注了情绪调节障碍的一种形式，即习惯性情绪调节策略使用的缺陷对情绪功能性障碍的影响，对其他可能形式(例如使用情绪调节策略的能力)的研究较少。已有研究中，研究者通常首先指导个体如何使用特定的情绪调节策略，并要求被试在情绪唤起任务中使用该策略，并通过测量在策略使用中个体表现出的预期情绪变化的程度来衡量个体的情绪调节能力(Minkel et al., 2012; Ochsner et al., 2004; Yang et al., 2020)。目前尚没有研究探究抑郁症的情绪调节功能障碍是否与使用某种特定的情绪调节策略的能力的相对减弱有关。这样就能引出一个新的问题，即抑郁个体是否能够使用一个给定的情绪调节策略来增加积极情绪。探究抑郁个体上调积极情绪的能力也是未来的一个研究方向。</p><p>了解抑郁症的积极情绪缺陷特点及原因对治疗抑郁症来说具有重要的意义。根据因抑郁而导致个体积极情绪偏向相对较少这一特点，现有的治疗方案可以调整为情绪偏向的训练，而不仅是训练个体如何使用某种特定的情绪调节策略。目前已有临床医生开始尝试从提高积极情绪的角度对抑郁症患者进行干预治疗(Dunn et al., 2019; Craske et al., 2019)。研究显示，相较于传统的认知行为治疗法，着重提高积极情绪的认知行为疗法的治疗效果更好，且更易于被抑郁症患者接受(Geschwind et al., 2020)。但目前的相关研究还相对较少，这种治疗角度和方法的有效性和普遍性仍有待于进一步的验证。积极情绪的缺失对个体的身心健康带来损害(Spijker et al., 2001; Vrieze et al., 2013)，且恢复积极情绪对个体来说非常有益，研究显示积极情绪与创造力，社交能力，利他主义，生活满意度、自我恢复水平(Lyubomirsky, King, &amp; Diener, 2005)和应对消极情绪的能力均存在正相关(Fredrickson, 2001)。鉴于抑郁症的一个主要特点是积极情绪水平的降低和消极情绪水平的提高，积极情绪的恢复或许可以反过来促进消极情绪的降低，因此可以同时针对这两大核心特征对抑郁症患者进行干预。</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>文章引用</title><p>丁鹏浩,井玉汝,佟月华. 抑郁个体积极情绪缺陷的原因：动机对习惯性情绪调节策略的影响Causes of Positive Emotion Deficits in Depressed Individuals: The Influence of Motivation on Habitual Emotion Regulation Strategies[J]. 心理学进展, 2021, 11(06): 1565-1575. https://doi.org/10.12677/AP.2021.116175</p></sec><sec id="s10"><title>参考文献</title></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">李红, 杨小光, 郑文瑜, 王超(2019). 抑郁倾向对个体情绪调节目标的影响——来自事件相关电位的证据. 心理学报, 51(6), 637-647.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">孟昭兰(编) (2005). 情绪心理学. 北京: 北京大学出版社.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">朱传林, 李萍, 罗文波, 齐正阳, 何蔚祺(2016). 精神分裂症患者的情绪调节. 心理科学进展, 24(4), 556-572.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Aker, M., Harmer, C., &amp; Landrø, N. I. (2014). More Rumination and Less Effective Emotion Regulation in Previously Depressed Women with Preserved Executive Functions. BMC Psychiatry, 14, 1-10.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/s12888-014-0334-4</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">American Psychiatric Association (2013). Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (5th ed.). Washington DC: Author. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1176/appi.books.9780890425596</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Beblo, T., Fernando, S., Klocke, S., Griepenstroh, J., Aschenbrenner, S., &amp; Driessen, M. (2012). Increased Suppression of Negative and Positive Emotions in Major Depression. Journal of Affective Disorders, 141, 474-479.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2012.03.019</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Borkovec, T. D., Alcaine, O. M., &amp; Behar, E. (2004). Avoidance Theory of Worry and Generalized Anxiety Disorder.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Bryant, F. B., &amp; Veroff, J. (2017). Savoring: A New Model of Positive Experience. Hove: Psychology Press.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.4324/9781315088426</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Campbell-Sills, L., Barlow, D. H., Brown, T. A., &amp; Hofmann, S. G. (2006). Effects of Suppression and Acceptance on Emotional Responses of Individuals with Anxiety and Mood Disorders. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 44, 1251-1263.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brat.2005.10.001</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Carl, J. R., Soskin, D. P., Kerns, C., &amp; Barlow, D. H. (2013). Positive Emotion Regulation in Emotional Disorders: A Theoretical Review. Clinical Psychology Review, 33, 343-360. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cpr.2013.01.003</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Carthy, T., Horesh, N., Apter, A., Edge, M. D., &amp; Gross, J. J. (2010). Emotional Reactivity and Cognitive Regulation in Anxious Children. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 48, 384-393. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brat.2009.12.013</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Carver, C. S., &amp; Johnson, S. L. (2009). Tendencies toward Mania and Tendencies toward Depression Have Distinct Motivational, Affective, and Cognitive Correlates. Cognitive Therapy and Research, 33, 552.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10608-008-9213-y</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Craske, M. G., Meuret, A. E., Ritz, T., Treanor, M., Dour, H., &amp; Rosenfield, D. (2019). Positive Affect Treatment for Depression and Anxiety: A Randomized Clinical Trial for a Core Feature of Anhedonia. Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology, 87, 457. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/ccp0000396</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Curland, R. A., Tran, M. M., Barba, F., &amp; Leykin, Y. (2020). Depressed Individuals’ Reasons for and against Trying to Get Better. Clinical Psychologist, 24, 186-194. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/cp.12211</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">D’Avanzato, C., Joormann, J., Siemer, M., &amp; Gotlib, I. H. (2013). Emotion Regulation in Depression and Anxiety: Examining Diagnostic Specificity and Stability of Strategy Use. Cognitive Therapy and Research, 37, 968-980.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10608-013-9537-0</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">De Rubeis, J., Lugo, R. G., Witthöft, M., Sütterlin, S., Pawelzik, M. R., &amp; Vögele, C. (2017). Rejection Sensitivity as a Vulnerability Marker for Depressive Symptom Deterioration in Men. PLoS ONE, 12, e0185802.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0185802</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Diener, E., Wolsic, B., &amp; Fujita, F. (1995). Physical Attractiveness and Subjective Well-Being. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 69, 120. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.69.1.120</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Domes, G., Schulze, L., Böttger, M., Grossmann, A., Hauenstein, K., Wirtz, P. H., Heinrichs, M., &amp; Herpertz, S. C. (2010). The Neural Correlates of Sex Differences in Emotional Reactivity and Emotion Regulation. Human Brain Mapping, 31, 758-769. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1002/hbm.20903</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Dunn, B. D., Widnall, E., Reed, N., Taylor, R., Owens, C., Spencer, A., Kraag, G., Kok, G., Geschwind, N., Wright, K., Moberly, N. J., Moulds, M. L., Macleod, A. K., Handley, R., Richards, D., Campbell, J., &amp; Kuyken, W. (2019). Evaluating Augmented Depression Therapy (ADepT): Study Protocol for a Pilot Randomised Controlled Trial. Pilot and Feasibility Studies, 5, 1-16. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/s40814-019-0438-1</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Eisner, L. R., Johnson, S. L., &amp; Carver, C. S. (2009). Positive Affect Regulation in Anxiety Disorders. Journal of Anxiety Disorders, 23, 645-649. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.janxdis.2009.02.001</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ellis, A. J., Beevers, C. G., &amp; Wells, T. T. (2011). Attention Allocation and Incidental Recognition of Emotional Information in Dysphoria. Cognitive Therapy and Research, 35, 425-433. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10608-010-9305-3</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Everaert, J., Bronstein, M. V., Cannon, T. D., &amp; Joormann, J. (2018). Looking through Tinted Glasses: Depression and Social Anxiety Are Related to Both Interpretation Biases and Inflexible Negative Interpretations. Clinical Psychological Science, 6, 517-528. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/2167702617747968</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Feldman, G. C., Joormann, J., &amp; Johnson, S. L. (2008). Responses to Positive Affect: A Self-Report Measure of Rumination and Dampening. Cognitive Therapy and Research, 32, 507-525. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10608-006-9083-0</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ferrari, A. J., Somerville, A. J., Baxter, A. J., Norman, R., Patten, S. B., Vos, T., &amp; Whiteford, H. A. (2013). Global Variation in the Prevalence and Incidence of Major Depressive Disorder: A Systematic Review of the Epidemiological Literature. Psychological Medicine, 43, 471. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291712001511</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fischer, A. H., Manstead, A. S., Evers, C., Timmers, M., &amp; Valk, G. (2004). Motives and Norms Underlying Emotion Regulation. In R. Feldman, &amp; P. Philippot (Eds.), The Regulation of Emotion (pp. 187-210). Mahwah, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Forbes, D. L. (2011). Toward a Unified Model of Human Motivation. Review of General Psychology, 15, 85-98.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/a0023483</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Forbes, E. E., Miller, A., Cohn, J. F., Fox, N. A., &amp; Kovacs, M. (2005). Affect-Modulated Startle in Adults with Childhood-Onset Depression: Relations to Bipolar Course and Number of Lifetime Depressive Episodes. Psychiatry Research, 134, 11-25. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psychres.2005.01.001</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Forbes, E. E., Olino, T. M., Ryan, N. D., Birmaher, B., Axelson, D., Moyles, D. L., &amp; Dahl, R. E. (2010). Reward-Related Brain Function as a Predictor of Treatment Response in Adolescents with Major Depressive Disorder. Cognitive, Affective, &amp; Behavioral Neuroscience, 10, 107-118. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.3758/CABN.10.1.107</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ford, B. Q., &amp; Tamir, M. (2014). Preferring Familiar Emotions: As You Want (and Like) It? Cognition &amp; Emotion, 28, 311-324. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/02699931.2013.823381</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fredrickson, B. L. (2000). Extracting Meaning from Past Affective Experiences: The Importance of Peaks, Ends, and Specific Emotions. Cognition &amp; Emotion, 14, 577-606. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/026999300402808</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Fredrickson, B. L. (2001). The Role of Positive Emotions in Positive Psychology: The Broaden-and-Build Theory of Positive Emotions. American Psychologist, 56, 218. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0003-066X.56.3.218</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Garnefski, N., &amp; Kraaij, V. (2006). Relationships between Cognitive Emotion Regulation Strategies and Depressive Symptoms: A Comparative Study of Five Specific Samples. Personality and Individual Differences, 40, 1659-1669.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.paid.2005.12.009</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Geschwind, N., Bosgraaf, E., Bannink, F., &amp; Peeters, F. (2020). Positivity Pays Off: Clients’ Perspectives on Positive Compared with Traditional Cognitive Behavioral Therapy for Depression. Psychotherapy, 57, 366-378.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/pst0000288</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gilbert, K., Luking, K., Pagliaccio, D., Luby, J., &amp; Barch, D. (2017). Dampening, Positive Rumination, and Positive Life Events: Associations with Depressive Symptoms in Children at Risk for Depression. Cognitive Therapy and Research, 41, 31-42. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10608-016-9798-5</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Goldstein, A. J., &amp; Chambless, D. L. (1978). A Reanalysis of Agoraphobia. Behavior Therapy, 9, 47-59.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/S0005-7894(78)80053-7</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Goldstein, B. L., Kessel, E. M., Kujawa, A., Finsaas, M. C., Davila, J., Hajcak, G., &amp; Klein, D. N. (2020). Stressful Life Events Moderate the Effect of Neural Reward Responsiveness in Childhood on Depressive Symptoms in Adolescence. Psychological Medicine, 50, 1548-1555. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0033291719001557</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gross, J. J. (2002). Emotion Regulation: Affective, Cognitive, and Social Consequences. Psychophysiology, 39, 281-291.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0048577201393198</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gross, J. J. (2014). Emotion Regulation: Conceptual and Empirical Foundations. In Handbook of Emotion Regulation (Vol. 2, pp. 3-20). New York: Guilford Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gross, J. J. (2015). The Extended Process Model of Emotion Regulation: Elaborations, Applications, and Future Directions. Psychological Inquiry, 26, 130-137. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/1047840X.2015.989751</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gross, J. J., &amp; John, O. P. (2003). Individual Differences in Two Emotion Regulation Processes: Implications for Affect, Relationships, and Well-Being. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 85, 348.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0022-3514.85.2.348</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Gross, J. J., Richards, J. M., &amp; John, O. P. (2006). Emotion Regulation in Everyday Life. In Emotion Regulation in Couples and Families: Pathways to Dysfunction and Health (pp. 13-35). Washington DC: American Psychological Association.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/11468-001</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Harding, K. A., Hudson, M. R., &amp; Mezulis, A. (2014). Cognitive Mechanisms Linking Low Trait Positive Affect to Depressive Symptoms: A Prospective Diary Study. Cognition and Emotion, 28, 1502-1511.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/02699931.2014.889661</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Heiy, J. E., &amp; Cheavens, J. S. (2014). Back to Basics: A Naturalistic Assessment of the Experience and Regulation of Emotion. Emotion, 14, 878. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/a0037231</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Heller, A. S., Johnstone, T., Shackman, A. J., Light, S. N., Peterson, M. J., Kolden, G. G., Kalin, N. H., &amp; Davidson, R. J. (2009). Reduced Capacity to Sustain Positive Emotion in Major Depression Reflects Diminished Maintenance of Fronto-Striatal Brain Activation. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 106, 22445-22450.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0910651106</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Henriques, J. B., &amp; Davidson, R. J. (2000). Decreased Responsiveness to Reward in Depression. Cognition &amp; Emotion, 14, 711-724. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/02699930050117684</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Higgins, E. T. (2011). Beyond Pleasure and Pain: How Motivation Works. Oxford: Oxford University Press.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199765829.001.0001</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Huang, Y., Wang, Y. U., Wang, H., Liu, Z., Yu, X., Yan, J. et al. (2019). Prevalence of Mental Disorders in China: A Cross-Sectional Epidemiological Study. The Lancet Psychiatry, 6, 211-224.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/S2215-0366(18)30511-X</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Joormann, J., &amp; Gotlib, I. H. (2007). Selective Attention to Emotional Faces Following Recovery from Depression. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 116, 80. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0021-843X.116.1.80</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Joormann, J., &amp; Stanton, C. H. (2016). Examining Emotion Regulation in Depression: A Review and Future Directions. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 86, 35-49. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brat.2016.07.007</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kalokerinos, E. K., Greenaway, K. H., &amp; Denson, T. F. (2015). Reappraisal But Not Suppression Downregulates the Experience of Positive and Negative Emotion. Emotion, 15, 271. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/emo0000025</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kashdan, T. B., &amp; Rottenberg, J. (2010). Psychological Flexibility as a Fundamental Aspect of Health. Clinical Psychology Review, 30, 865-878. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cpr.2010.03.001</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kellough, J. L., Beevers, C. G., Ellis, A. J., &amp; Wells, T. T. (2008). Time Course of Selective Attention in Clinically Depressed Young Adults: An Eye Tracking Study. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 46, 1238-1243.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brat.2008.07.004</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kube, T., Kirchner, L., Gärtner, T., &amp; Glombiewski, J. (2021). How Negative Mood Hinders Belief Updating in Depression-Results from Two Experimental Studies. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.31234/osf.io/q76b4</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Kuppens, P., Allen, N. B., &amp; Sheeber, L. B. (2010). Emotional Inertia and Psychological Maladjustment. Psychological Science, 21, 984-991. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797610372634</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Larsen, R. J., &amp; Prizmic, Z. (2004). Affect Regulation. In R. F. Baumeister, &amp; K. D. Vohs (Eds.), Handbook of Self-Regulation: Research, Theory, and Applications (pp. 40-61). New York: The Guilford Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Leng, Y., Qian, X., &amp; Zhu, Y. (2018). Modulation of Brain Response to Peer Rejection by Rejection Sensitivity: An Exploratory Study. Neuropsychologia, 117, 389-397. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2018.07.003</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Li, Y. I., Starr, L. R., &amp; Hershenberg, R. (2017). Responses to Positive Affect in Daily Life: Positive Rumination and Dampening Moderate the Association between Daily Events and Depressive Symptoms. Journal of Psychopathology and Behavioral Assessment, 39, 412-425. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10862-017-9593-y</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Liu, D. Y., &amp; Thompson, R. J. (2017). Selection and Implementation of Emotion Regulation Strategies in Major Depressive Disorder: An Integrative Review. Clinical Psychology Review, 57, 183-194. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cpr.2017.07.004</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Lyubomirsky, S., King, L., &amp; Diener, E. (2005). The Benefits of Frequent Positive Affect: Does Happiness Lead to Success?. Psychological Bulletin, 131, 803. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.131.6.803</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref60"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mathews, A., &amp; MacLeod, C. (2005). Cognitive Vulnerability to Emotional Disorders. Annual Review of Clinical Psychology, 1, 167-195. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.clinpsy.1.102803.143916</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref61"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Mauss, I. B., &amp; Tamir, M. (2014). Emotion Goals: How Their Content, Structure, and Operation Shape Emotion Regulation. In J. J. Gross (Ed.), The Handbook of Emotion Regulation (pp. 361-375, 2nd ed.). New York: Guilford Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref62"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">McMakin, D. L., Olino, T. M., Porta, G., Dietz, L. J., Emslie, G., Clarke, G., Wagner, K. D., Asarnow, J. R., Ryan, N. D., Birmahei, B., Shamseddeen, W., Mayes, T., Kennard, B., Spirito, A., Keller, M., Lynch, F. L., Dickerson, J. F., &amp; Brent, D. A. (2012). Anhedonia Predicts Poorer Recovery among Youth with Selective Serotonin Reuptake Inhibitor Treatment-Resistant Depression. Journal of the American Academy of Child &amp; Adolescent Psychiatry, 51, 404-411.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jaac.2012.01.011</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref63"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Millgram, Y., Joormann, J., Huppert, J. D., &amp; Tamir, M. (2015). Sad as a Matter of Choice? Emotion-Regulation Goals in Depression. Psychological Science, 26, 1216-1228. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/0956797615583295</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref64"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Millgram, Y., Sheppes, G., Kalokerinos, E. K., Kuppens, P., &amp; Tamir, M. (2019). Do the Ends Dictate the Means in Emotion Regulation? Journal of Experimental Psychology: General, 148, 80-96.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref65"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Minkel, J. D., McNealy, K., Gianaros, P. J., Drabant, E. M., Gross, J. J., Manuck, S. B., &amp; Hariri, A. R. (2012). Sleep Quality and neural circuit function supporting emotion regulation. Biology of Mood &amp; Anxiety Disorders, 2, 1-9.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1186/2045-5380-2-22</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref66"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Nelis, S., Holmes, E. A., &amp; Raes, F. (2015). Response styles to positive affect and depression: Concurrent and prospective associations in a Community Sample. Cognitive Therapy and Research, 39, 480-491.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/s10608-015-9671-y</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref67"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Ochsner, K. N., Ray, R. D., Cooper, J. C., Robertson, E. R., Chopra, S., Gabrieli, J. D., &amp; Gross, J. J. (2004). For Better or for Worse: Neural Systems Supporting the Cognitive Down- and Up-Regulation of Negative Emotion. Neuroimage, 23, 483-499. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroimage.2004.06.030</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref68"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Pegg, S., Arfer, K. B., &amp; Kujawa, A. (2021). Altered Reward Responsiveness and Depressive Symptoms: An Examination of Social and Monetary Reward Domains and Interactions with Rejection Sensitivity. Journal of Affective Disorders, 282, 717-725. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2020.12.093</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref69"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Raes, F., Smets, J., Nelis, S., &amp; Schoofs, H. (2012). Dampening of Positive Affect Prospectively Predicts Depressive Symptoms in Non-Clinical Samples. Cognition &amp; Emotion, 26, 75-82. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/02699931.2011.555474</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref70"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Riediger, M., Schmiedek, F., Wagner, G. G., &amp; Lindenberger, U. (2009). Seeking Pleasure and Seeking Pain: Differences in Prohedonic and Contra-Hedonic Motivation from Adolescence to Old Age. Psychological Science, 20, 1529-1535.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-9280.2009.02473.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref71"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rockman, D. (2020). Negative Mood Regulation Expectancies, Cognitive Reappraisal and Mindfulness in Relation to Depression and Anxiety. Doctoral Dissertation, Fullerton, CA: California State University.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref72"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rottenberg, J. (2017). Emotions in Depression: What Do We Really Know? Annual Review of Clinical Psychology, 13, 241-263. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-clinpsy-032816-045252</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref73"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rottenberg, J., Kasch, K. L., Gross, J. J., &amp; Gotlib, I. H. (2002). Sadness and Amusement Reactivity Differentially Predict Concurrent and Prospective Functioning in Major Depressive Disorder. Emotion, 2, 135.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/1528-3542.2.2.135</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref74"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Rude, S. S., Wenzlaff, R. M., Gibbs, B., Vane, J., &amp; Whitney, T. (2002). Negative Processing Biases Predict Subsequent Depressive Symptoms. Cognition &amp; Emotion, 16, 423-440. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/02699930143000554</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref75"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Setterfield, M., Walsh, M., Frey, A. L., &amp; McCabe, C. (2016). Increased Social Anhedonia and Reduced Helping Behaviour in Young People with High Depressive Symptomatology. Journal of Affective Disorders, 205, 372-377.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2016.08.020</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref76"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Silvers, J. A., McRae, K., Gabrieli, J. D., Gross, J. J., Remy, K. A., &amp; Ochsner, K. N. (2012). Age-Related Differences in Emotional Reactivity, Regulation, and Rejection Sensitivity in Adolescence. Emotion, 12, 1235.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/a0028297</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref77"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Spijker, J., Bijl, R. V., De Graaf, R., &amp; Nolen, W. A. (2001). Determinants of Poor 1-Year Outcome of DSM-III-R Major Depression in the General Population: Results of the Netherlands Mental Health Survey and Incidence Study (NEMESIS). Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica, 103, 122-130. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1034/j.1600-0447.2001.103002122.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref78"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tamir, M. (2009). What Do People Want to Feel and Why? Pleasure and Utility in Emotion Regulation. Current Directions in Psychological Science, 18, 101-105. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-8721.2009.01617.x</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref79"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tamir, M. (2016). Why Do People Regulate Their Emotions? A Taxonomy of Motives in Emotion Regulation. Personality and Social Psychology Review, 20, 199-222. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1177/1088868315586325</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref80"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tamir, M., &amp; Ford, B. Q. (2009). Choosing to Be Afraid: Preferences for Fear as a Function of Goal Pursuit. Emotion, 9, 488.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/a0015882</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref81"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Tang, W., Bao, C., Xu, L., Zhu, J., Feng, W., Zhang, W.,Lin, C., Chen, L., Cheng, Q., Ding, P., Zhou, M., Bao, Y., Yu, X., Zhao, K., &amp; He, J. (2019). Depressive Symptoms in Late Pregnancy Disrupt Attentional Processing of Negative-Positive Emotion: An Eye-Movement Study. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 10, 780. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2019.00780</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref82"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Vrieze, E., Pizzagalli, D. A., Demyttenaere, K., Hompes, T., Sienaert, P., de Boer, P., Schmidt, M., &amp; Claes, S. (2013). Reduced Reward Learning Predicts Outcome in Major Depressive Disorder. Biological Psychiatry, 73, 639-645.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biopsych.2012.10.014</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref83"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Werner-Seidler, A., Banks, R., Dunn, B. D., &amp; Moulds, M. L. (2013). An Investigation of the Relationship between Positive Affect Regulation and Depression. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 51, 46-56.  
&lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brat.2012.11.001</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref84"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Wood, J. V., Heimpel, S. A., Manwell, L. A., &amp; Whittington, E. J. (2009). This Mood Is Familiar and I Don’t Deserve to Feel Better Anyway: Mechanisms Underlying Self-Esteem Differences in Motivation to Repair Sad Moods. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 96, 363. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1037/a0012881</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="hanspub.43515-ref85"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other" xlink:type="simple">Yang, J., Mao, Y., Niu, Y., Wei, D., Wang, X., &amp; Qiu, J. (2020). Individual Differences in Neuroticism Personality Trait in Emotion Regulation. Journal of Affective Disorders, 265, 468-474. &lt;br&gt;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jad.2020.01.086</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>